Hi, and welcome to Statistics One.
The purpose of this first lecture is, as
the
title suggests, to give you an
introduction to the course.
but it's also mainly designed to introduce
you to
some terminology that's necessary to
understand the first week's lectures.
As you see from the website, we did this
course last year.
And one of the, one of the first points of
feedback
we got on the discussion forms was that,
although this course is designed to
be a friendly introduction for anyone who
wants to take statistics, regardless of
background.
we learned early on that we used some
basic
terms and phrases, that not everyone is
familiar with.
So that's the main purpose of this, this
first lecture,
is to get everybody on the same page, and
to
clarify some of the terminology and
phrases that are
common in the first lecture and throughout
the course.
also if you have any questions about the
course, about the structure of the course.
Or if you have questions about particular
phrases or definitions of terms,
you can go to the website, we have a
glossary of terms that's on the website.
Or feel free
to ask a question in the discussion
forums.
So if you don't understand a phrase, if
you
don't understand a term that I used early
on.
please post a question in the discussion
forums, and either I or
my team or some other students will, will
answer it quickly, okay.
So let's launch into this first
introductory lecture.
So, lets start with a basic definition
of what is statistics?
you could define it in many ways.
For something as broad as this, you can
just Google statistics
definition, or statistics meaning, or just
look at the Wikipedia page.
I've defined it very broadly here, just as
the scientific discipline devoted to the
study of data.
that of course begs the question, well
what is data?
So, let's define data.
Data simply is a
collection of numbers.
assigned as values to quantitative
variables, or characters assigned as
values to qualitative variables.
That sounds kind of lingo-y and, and,
technical, so what do I mean exactly?
Let's look at an example.
So consider we have the academic record of
a bunch of children in elementary school.
And that might look something like this if
we organize it into a spreadsheet.
think Microsoft Excel if you're going to
be, we're going to be using our In R,
this would be called a data frame, we'll
get to that in the first lab.
Basically, its just a data structure
that has columns.
So here are the columns.
And it has a bunch of rows, its very
common for one row, to
pretend to one student or one case in your
data file.
So we have a student there initials in the
first column then the agenda.
This first student is TR male, there age
in months, so these are, as I mentioned,
Elementary,
Ed.
schoolchildren and then their grades in
certain classes.
So what do I mean by data?
Well, each one of these little points, so
like, TR's
really nice 95 in math is a data point.
We assigned a
value to a variable, math score for a
particular student,
that's a quantitative piece of data is
TR's name,
TR's gender, those are characters that we
assign
as values.
So those are examples of qualitative
data.
Another way to define data is, the
more technical, is it's the lowest level
of abstraction, from which
information and then knowledge can be
derived.
So at the lowest level, we have data.
From data, we can get to information.
And as we gather lots and lots of
information,
we can start to form a knowledge base, and
form.
knowledge structures and wisdom.
To be clear, a statistician is a
skilled person in applying the tools of
statistics.
so there are lots of examples of that.
This is not intended to be an exhaustive.
list of statisticians, just a sampling.
So, there are lots of statisticians who do
academic research.
That's, like, what, I do.
So, I'm a professor at Princeton.
I do research in cognitive psychology,
specifically in memory and attention and
intelligence.
And so I do academic research.
I apply statistical tools to do my
academic research.
there's lots of examples, not just in
psychology, but across the
disciplines in colleges and universities
all over the world of academic research.
There's lots of examples of medical
research that occurs in hospital settings.
there's lots of examples of survey
studies.
They're the most popular like poling
studies to predict election outcomes.
or like the census polls there's lots of
research that takes place
in the realm of education like that
academic records example.
there's lots of research in education and
online education going on right
now, trying to understand, how online
education is working.
then finally, there is a big sector that
used to be called market research, now
I think if falls under the phrase,
Analytics, also falls under the phrase,
Big Data.
A big area where statisticians are being
hired right now.
So again, to be clear in terminology, a
statistic is just
a quantity calculated from a sample of
data, and we're going to do this a lot.
We're going to get samples of data, and we
can calculate lots of statistics.
And I'm sure you've done this before, so
if you've been in school before.
You could get all of your grades and
calculate your average grade in a
particular subject, or your average across
all
your subjects to get your grade point
average.
so, an example in our academic records
example is
the average math grade or average age of
students.
We could also calculate how much
variability there is.
We'll talk about this in the second week,
how to calculate variability in a sample.
one of the most popular ways to do that is
through standard deviation.
We can calculate standard deviation of the
math grade.
That would tell us how much variability
across
the students is there in the math grade.
So I just mentioned the idea of a sample
there.
so it's, it's important at the beginning
to make this distinction between sample
and population.
We'll often be talking about samples in
populations
so populations, I'll start at the bottom
here.
are the entire collection of cases or
people or subjects
I might use that phrase, which we want to
generalize to.
So if I want to do a study about all
healthy undergraduate students
who were taking college courses or taking
courses online.
that's my population.
I typically can't get my hands on that
entire population to do my study, to
administer
my experiment, or administer my measures,
so I
would try and get a subset of that
population.
And that's called the sample.
So the sample is simply a subset of the
population.
A statistic as I defined just a moment
ago, is
a numerical measure that describes a
characteristic of a sample.
Statistics hopefully are good estimates of
parameters.
Parameters describe populations.
So you have samples, populations,
statistics, parameters.
A basic distinction at the beginning of
any
statistics course, if you pick up any
intro
to stats textbook, most of them start with
this distinction between descriptive
statistics and inferential statistics.
And in fact, we'll do the same.
The first couple weeks of this course will
mainly deal with descriptive statistics.
Just how do we summarize,
organize, just simplify data?
How do we tell a story about what's in a
sample's worth of data?
We'll then move on to the more difficult
task
of inferential statistics, which is where
we'll learn procedures.
Where we allow for generalizations about
the population parameters from the sample
statistics.
Again, we typically can't get our
hands on the entire population, so we'll
look at our sample statistics and try
and make inferences about the population.
Based on those statistics.
That piece is called inferential
statistics.
Finally, I just want to give you a brief
introduction to
different research methods, and this is
really the topic of week one.
There's two lectures in week one, where
we'll talk about correlational and
experimental research.
it's important to know what type of
research you're
engaged in, or what type of research
others are
engaged in as you evaluate data and as
you evaluate the statistics applied to the
data.
So, the simplest type of research method
is just descriptive
research, just, describing what's in a
sample's worth of data.
That's just organizing, summarizing,
describing the data.
So, in the example of academic, the
the academic records of elementary school
children.
We already did that.
We organized it into a spreadsheet, we
summarized it.
We could just give basic descriptive
statistics, like the mean of, of the
kids in terms of age or the mean math
score, average math score.
That's just descriptive, describing what's
in the data.
Another type of method is correlational
research.
So we might want examine the relationship
among variables in our data structure,
so we might want to say, well is math
grade correlated with history grade.
And is history, is history grade
correlated with the science grade?
Or is age correlated with math grade.
All of those are examples of correlational
research.
And that's going to be the main topic of
lecture two.
We'll spend an entire lecture talking
about correlational research.
And correlational methods.
And finally, there's experimental
research, and experimental
research is sort of the gold standard, if
you want to do research that gets at
statements
about causaility or if you want to get at.
Research methods that explain
causal mechanisms.
so, experimental research is very popular
and very powerful, and we're actually
going to spend all of lecture one, talking
about experimental research methods.
So, an example in the context of our
elementary school children
is, we might randomly assign students to
two types of schedule.
So some kids might be randomly assigned to
learn year-round, so they don't get a
summer
break, they just get small breaks
throughout the year.
and other kids might be randomly assigned
to
a summer break, more traditional academic
calendar condition.
And if we randomly assign kids to those
con, two conditions, we could then look
at, their
achievement at the end of the school year,
and
see if their achievement was affected by
that manipulation.
So, does year round schooling work better
than the traditional academic calendar?
And some people have actually done
research on that.
My final statement in this first, the
first lecture, is I want to
remind you that it is the Internet,
International Year of Statistics, 2013.
There's lots of information on this
website, statistics2013.org.
So there's lots of exciting happening
right now, there's,
as I mentioned, there's lots of jobs
opening up.
All around the world, especially in the
US, for people who have some
sort of skill in doing statistical
analysis.
So, you're in the right place, go, please
check out more about the international
year of statistics.
I just wanted to pick out one quote from
their website.
and it's here on this last slide.
Statistics is becoming more critical as
academia, businesses, and governments
come to rely on data driven decisions,
greatly expanding the
demand for statisticians.
So sit back, relax, enjoy Statistics One.
Again, if any of these terms are new to
you, if there're new phrases.
definitions that you need clarification
on, please check out
the glossary of terms on the website and
also feel
free to post a question of the discussion
forum, and
I or my team or other students will get
back
to you very quickly.
Thanks for tuning in, and I look forward
to seeing you in lecture one.
[BLANK_AUDIO]