Hi, and welcome back to Statistics one.
We're up to lecture six and the topic of
today's lecture is Measurement.
As I mentioned in lecture five, most intro
stats courses and most intro stats
textbooks don't spend too much time
talking about measurement issues.
But for me, this is a really critical
issue, and I feel should be a fundamental
part
of an intro stats course.
So we're going to devote an entire lecture
to just core measurement issues.
So in this lecture, we're going to, we're
going to divide it up into three segments.
In the first segment, I'll talk about
reliability.
In the second, I'll talk about validity
and in the
third we'll revisit this idea of random
and representative sampling.
So in this first segment let's look at
reliability.
The important concepts or topics to take
away
from this, are this broad theory that's
known as
classical test theory It's also known as
true
score theory, it comes out of psychology,
specifically psychometrics.
and I'll explain, just briefly what
classical test theory is about.
And then, we'll talk about how to
calculate reliability estimates.
So how do we know how reliable our
measures are.
To be clear, what I mean by a reliability
estimate
is just, if I use an instrument to measure
some
property one time, and then I use it
again, the,
the measurements from time one to time two
should be stable.
So just think of a scale.
As you step on a scale, you weigh
yourself, you get off, you step on
it again.
You should get about the same exact
weight, right?
If it's a reliable scale.
That's all we're talking about here, is,
do we have reliable measurements?
it's a little bit harder to evaluate
reliability
when you're dealing with things like
intelligence or personality.
Or attitudes.
weight and mass, those things are easier
to assess reliability.
So how do we deal with these fuzzier
constructs that are common in the social
sciences.
That's where classical test theory comes
in.
So these raw scores I've been talking
about, that I've been
giving the letter x to, they're never
perfect in the social sciences.
They're influenced by bias, they might be
influenced by chance error.
They're influenced by all sorts of
factors, they're, they're never perfect
assessments of whatever construct it is
we're setting out to measure.
Even body
temperature which is a, a, a pretty
concrete
example, is susceptible to bias and chance
error.
for example, with body temperature, there
are different methods to assess body
temperature.
You can assess body temperature orally,
internally, there's this new
thing called an infrared thermometer wand
that you can do.
Each of those give slightly different
measurements,
there could also just be random chance
error.
So if I'm If I'm trying to measure body
temperature of
my partner, and he just took a swig of
cold water,
and I didn't know that, then I'm going to
get a cold reading.
And that's just random chance error.
So measurement is always susceptible to
chance error.
It's always susceptible to er has the
potential to be susceptible to bias.
So here's the heart of classical test
theory is
in a perfect world, it would be possible
to get
the true score for whatever it is we're
trying to assess.
So it should be possible for me to get the
true body temperature.
But I can't, there's always going to be
just chance error.
There might be systematic bias.
So any raw score x is actually the true
score plus some bias if it exists plus
some chance error.
And as I said this is also known in
psychometrics as true score theory.
So, as a measure x, approaches the true
score, it's considered to be reliable.
The problem there is we don't know what
the true scores are.
if we can't actually get th, assessments
of
the true score, then we can't judge how
far
we are From the true score by looking
at the difference between raw scores and
true scores.
So we just have to estimate reliability
and
there are several ways to do that and I'm
going to
walk you through three of them here in
this segment.
The three that'll talk about and there are
more
ways to do this, but I'm just going to
emphasize three.
there's one, test re-test.
Another is known as parallel tests.
And the third is known as inter-item
estimates.
I'll walk through each of these.
For now, let's go back to this body
temperature example.
Forgive me if I'm harping on this one, but
it works really well for several examples.
Then it'll work again.
next week in one of the lectures, then
I'll drop it.
so, two more times I'm going to use body
temperature.
again, think of three different ways to
measure body temperature.
Orally, through a thermometer in your
mouth.
Internally, there are ways you can do
that.
and then, with this new wand.
If you're not familiar with that It looks
something like this, and
all you have to do is just wave it over
the forehead
of a patient and it will give you a
reading.
My partner is actually a nurse, so I'm
very familiar with this,
and he tells me that these tend to run a
little hot.
So they have a systematic bias, is what
he's saying.
They tend to give readings that are a
little
ab, a little higher, than say an oral
thermometer.
So, that's a systematic bias.
because, not,
it's not that it runs a little hot for
men, not for women.
Or, for people with hair, not for people
with hair.
It's a systematic bias, for everybody it
runs a little hot.
That's bias instead of chance there.
So let's go back and look at histograms.
So here's a histogram.
This is from way back in the lecture on
distributions.
This is a histogram
of body temperature in degrees Fahrenheit.
It's a normal distribution.
If you're not used to Fahrenheit, the
normal average body temperature in
Fahrenheit is 98.6.
And you can see, that's, like, right
around here.
So this is a nice normal distribution.
I know, probably the majority of of
the students out there are more
comfortable with
Celsius, so I just replotted it.
And Celsius, same exact data.
In Celsius, normal body temperature
average is 37 and that's like right here.
Okay, so we have nice, normal
distributions.
let's assume these were measured with the
oral thermometer.
That tends to give distributions like
this.
Now let's assume that we used this
infrared
thermometer, that we know runs a little
high.
Here it is in Fahrenheit.
We still have a relatively normal
distribution, there's
this one guy out here, but it's pretty
normal.
But if you look at the scale of the X
axis, it's just shifted.
And, you see, that the average is now,
it's right about 99.5,
maybe a little higher, say 99.6, it's
almost like a degree higher.
But it's a degree higher for everyone.
That's systematic biased.
It's not random chance error, it's
systematic
biased because it's affecting the entire
distribution.
And again if you're more comfortable with
celsius.
Same exact data, just plotted in celsius.
And now you see the average is where
[INAUDIBLE]
the average it's like, right about here.
It's, it's approaching 38 degrees.
It's like, maybe 37 7.
So again, it's running a little hot.
But it's, it's running hot for the entire
distribution.
That's a systematic bias.
So, how do we detect these kinds of
biases, chance
errors, and how do we estimate the
reliability of a measure.
Well, the first way I'm going to describe
is the test, re-test method.
So, it's very simple.
Just like this scale example.
Just measure every one twice.
Let's take the oral thermometer, measure
everybody in a sample, then wait a few
hours, do it again, and their measurements
should be correlated.
Those people who are a little, have a
little bit higher body
temperature at time one should have the
same thing at time two.
There should be a strong correlation.
In fact, the correlation between X1 and X2
is the reliability estimate.
If there's no correlation between
measuring say
your weight on a scale the first time and
weight on a scale
the second time, if there's no
correlation, then that's a completely
unreliable scale.
Right, that's unreliable the correlation
zero.
What that means for correlational analysis
is if something correlates
with itself at zero, it can't possibly
correlate with anything else.
Right.
So the reliability estimate is
actually the celing.
For the magnitude of correlation you could
ever
find with some other construct or some
other measure.
So that's why it's so critical to have
strong high reliability estimates.
Because they limit how high your
correlations
can go as you do correlational studies.
So this test retest method.
We just look at the correlation between x1
and x2.
The pr-, the only problem with the
test/retest method is, it wouldn't detect
the bias.
The systematic bias in the instrument,
right?
So if we use the infrared meter.
I did that, say, on everybody in a
classroom once.
I did it on everybody in the classroom
again a couple hours later, and the
correlation
was really high.
If I only looked at the correlation, it
wouldn't tell me about the bias.
I would have to look at the histogram.
I would have to look at the mean of the
sample.
So so the idea of parallel tests is like
doing the oral thermometer and the
infrared
thermometer, seeing how they're correlated
but also comparing their distributions.
So this would give us a reliability
estimate.
Again the correlation would be the
reliability estimate.
But comparing the means and the histograms
that would also reveal a systematic
biased, so that's the difference between
the test, retest and the parallel test.
I'm going to finally drop this body
temperature for
the third method.
and talk about inter-item estimates and
these are
actually the most common in the social
sciences.
Because tests re-tests and parallel tests
are actually hard to do.
when we conduct research in social
sciences
we're often doing research on human
subjects.
And that takes a lot of people's time, and
often, money.
so it's hard to
get them to say, take one assessment, and
then come back a couple weeks
later and just do it again, so that we can
get a reliability estimate.
Instead, as we try to build in a
reliability estimate in one meaurement And
one time point.
So let's go back to the idea of the,
personality surveys.
and assessing extraversion.
Suppose we had a 20 item survey tha was
designed to get at extraversion.
Or agreeableness or anyone of the
personality traits.
What's typical is we'll administer several
questions that get at each personality
trait.
So if you remember back to the
personality, the
correlational studies lecture where we
talked about personality There
was one question that got at extraversion
that said, I'm the life of the party.
Strongly disagree, strongly agree.
And then there was another one that said,
I don't mind being the center of
attention.
Strongly disagree, strongly agree.
There are several like that built into the
survey, and what we can
do is look for correlations among those
items that purportedly measure the same
trait.
What we can do to estimate reliability
is just take 1/2 of the items that are
designed
to get at extra version and call that
subset A.
And then, take the other 1/2 and call that
subset B.
Now we have 2 assessments of extra version
built into 1.
Assessment.
One overall survey.
If they're all getting at this one
personality
trait, extraversion, then sub-set A should
be correlated
with sub-set B.
And that correlation will be used as the
reliability estimate.
It's a very common method in the social
sciences.
It's called inter-item estimates of
reliability.
So, to summarize this first segment on
measurement issues, the main topic here is
reliability.
And I introduce reliability by just giving
a quick overview
of this very broad theory in psychometrics
called classical test theory.
Or true score theory.
And then we talked about three ways to get
reliability estimates, test re-test,
parallel tests, and inter-item estimates.