Hi.
Welcome back to Statistics One.
We're up to lecture 12, and in the last
lecture we talked about multiple
regression which is one of the more
difficult topics that we'll cover in this
course.
And in the next two lectures, lectures 13
and 14,
will cover advanced techniques in multiple
regression, moderation, and mediation.
Before we do that.
I want to take a step back, and
just talk about the mathematical frame
work underlying
all of these approaches.
And that is called the general linear
model.
So the topic for today in lecture 12, is
GLM or General Linear model.
I've divided this lecture into two
segments.
First I'll talk about the generally linear
model.
And then in the second segment I'll talk
about sort of more tedious details.
procedure called dumby coding.
So in this
first segment lets talk about the GLM.
As I said, it's a mathematical framework
that underlies multiple regression.
But also analysis of variance, which is a
topic that we'll get to after multiple
regression.
a lot of people think of those two topics
as separate, so multiple regression
is often taught in one course and then
ANOVA is taught in another course.
But analysis
of variance, or ANOVA, is Just a special
case of multiple regression, and
you'll see how that's, or why that's the
case here when I talk about the GLM.
So there are two main characteristics of
the General Linear model and that
is one, that we assume linear
relationships
between the predictors and the outcome
measure.
That is between the Xs and Y and
we assume that the effects of each
predictor are additive with one another.
But that doesn't mean that the GLM can't
handle non-additive or non-linear effects.
We can sort of trick the GLM to test those
kind of effects.
For us and that's what we were going to
do next week when we do moderation for
example.
We will trick the GLM into testing for a
non-additive effect
or a moderating effect or an ANOVA will
call that an interaction.
So the GLM can accommodate such tests.
for example non-linear relations
we could just transform variables to make
them linear and then fit it into the GLM.
and as I said we can add in interaction
terms or moderation terms.
So that we can do a moderation analysis
and test for non-additive.
Added of facts.
So, let's look at a few examples, this
will
help make this more concrete and explained
the general framework.
So, when we looked at a simple regression,
we just
had one predictor, one outcome so faculty
salary was the outcome.
And years since PHD was the predictor.
We could do a multiple regression, and add
in other predictors.
So we
added in we had years since the PHD.
And then we also added in number of
publications.
but we could add in a third predictor
that's the product of those first 2
predictors.
And that would allow us to test for
non-additive effects.
It would allow us to see if number of
publications moderates the relationship
between year since PhD and salary.
And you might think that's, that's the
case, so
perhaps like number of publications
matters a lot more.
For a determined salary earlier in your
career rather than later.
So, there might be an interaction or
moderation effect.
If that were the case, then that predictor
x3, that would
be a significant predictor of the outcome
measure of faculty salary.
But this is a way that the GLM
can handle testing non additive effects.
Notice the GLM, the equation itself,
is still linear and additive, but I'm
tricking it by throwing in X3,
a non additive effect.
So, that's how it accomodates.
These things, and that's how we're, that's
what we're going
to do next week, when we talk about
moderation analysis.
This is the same exact logic underlying
one-way ANOVA
and factorial ANOVA, which we'll get to
following moderation.
Its just that we do ANOVA's sort have been
a special
case where we have categorical predictors
rather than these continuous predictors.
So I might predict faculty salary from say
just
gender that's a categorical predictor and
its a nominal variable.
That's different from, like, number of
years since the PhD, or
number of publications, where we can
assume a nice continuous normal
distribution.
That's a different, this is a different
case.
So, when we have categorical predictors,
we'll do ANOVA.
And, just as we did with the multiple
regression, testing
for moderation effects, we can test for
interaction effects, and ANOVA.
So, I could put in gender as one
predictor, race as another predictor,
again, a categorical predictor.
And then for X3, the third predictor, I
could look at the interaction
of gender and race and do, does that
interaction effect Predict faculty salary.
Again notice the glm itself is linear and
additive and
it's just handling categorical predictors
here and that's why it's an
ANOVA, and it's a factorial ANOVA because
we have multiple predictors.
So we'll get to analysis of variance,
after
we cover these other topics in multiple
regression.
That is moderation, and mediation.
It's most appropriate for situations where
we have true independent variables.
Go back to the first week of the, of the
course,
where we talked about the difference
between experimental research and
correlational research.
we typically reserve analysis of variants
for situations
where we're doing experimental research,
where there's true independent variable.
but we can use it in any case where we
have categorical predictors.
And if there's only 2 levels of
categorical
predictors, like, think of the the polio
vaccine example,
where the children were just given, either
vaccine
or placebo, then we could just do a
t-test.
We don't need to do this fancy analysis of
variance.
And we'll cover all of that After we cover
moderation and mediation.
I just wanted to sort of pause before we
went into that to demonstrate
that the general linear model accommodates
all of these kinds of analyses.
So, to sum up this segment, again the GLM
is just an underlying mathematical
framework that we're using.
Not only for multiple regression.
But also going forward for things like
ANOVA and factorial ANOVA, and t tests.
And the main thing to remember about it is
that the framework itself is linear.
Li, linear and additive.
But we can trick it to test for non linear
effects.
Or not additive, additive effects and in
multiple regression we're going to call
that moderation.
In fact,
[UNKNOWN],
we're call that interaction.