Hi, welcome back.
We're in lecture 12, segment 2.
And in this segment, I'm going to talk
about dummy coding.
It's necessary to talk about dummy coding
in the context of the general linear model
to show you how categorical predictors are
handled in this framework.
And we also use it as we move forward in
more
complex multiple regression analysis, like
moderation which will be the topic
in lecture 13.
So let's examine how dummy coding works.
So, dummy coding is conceptually real
easy, but it's sort
of a tedious process and students
sometimes get tripped by it.
So conceptually, it's real simple, it's
just a system to code categorical
variables in a regression analysis.
So
I'm going to use an example here sticking
with the sort of faculty salary example.
imagine that we had a categorical
predictor that we wanted to add into that
analysis and imagine that that categorical
predictor
is what area of research a psychology
professor engages in.
So typical psychology departments, they
have some cognitive
psychologists, some clinical
psychologists, some
social psychologists, and so on.
So imagine I can just code each professor
according to one of theses
areas or groups and then look at the
number of publications that they have.
So that's my dependent variable or outcome
variable in this example.
Your data frame might look something like
this.
We could have a professor ID like the
initials of the professor.
what groups are in cognitive, clinical,
developmental, whatever.
and then the number of publications that
they have.
so assume these are like senior
professors, there's a lot
of publications so toward their end, end
of their career.
How are we going to code this if we wanted
to run it in a regression analysis, for
example using the LM function in R.
We can't put group into the LM function
because that's a character variable, or a
string variable.
We need to make it a numeric variable in
some way, so that's where dummy coding
comes in.
This is a simple scheme to, put a numeric
value on each of these groups and I'm
using cognitive, as what's called the
reference group.
And I did that because I'm a cognitive
psychologist, so for me that was easy to
remember.
That cognitive is going to get 0 across
the board, for
dummy code 1, dummy code 2 and dummy code
3.
So why do I have three dummy codes?
Well, because I have four levels of
my independent variable or my grouping
variable.
It's always the number of levels or number
of groups minus one.
And you make one of your groups the
reference.
And I decided to make cognitive the
just because I'm in cognitive.
And then you just code each group so, with
a one for one of the dummy codes.
So the clinical group got a 1 in D1,
the developmental in D2 and social in D3.
This make look a little bit odd and a lot
of students they, they tend to think that
you need four codes if there's four
groups, but
remember it's always the number of groups
minus one.
And if you think about how the regression
equation works,
this might start to make a little bit of
sense.
Now remember what's the regression
constant in a multiple regression?
It's the predicted score on the outcome
variable, when all the Xs are zero.
Well I now have a really meaningful group
there.
I have the cognitive group.
That's all Xs are 0, so my regression
constant is
going to be the predicted score for the
cognitive group.
So let's see how that works.
I would just add those dummy codes to my
dataframe,
so now I have a larger dataframe, I have
three more columns.
So, this is what it would look like in R.
Then I can run, the LM.
Before I show you the output of that, I
just want to show you the summary
statistics so you know what to expect.
So it looks like the cognitive group has a
mean of about 93 publications, clinical
less than that, about 60,
developmental a little more, 103, social a
little less, 70 and so on.
Those are standard deviations and also
notice there's
a different number of professors in each
group.
That's going to be important in a moment.
So the regression model would look like
this.
We just put in the three dummy codes.
So now we have three predictors.
And this will allow us to look at
the pair all these pair-wise comparisons
between groups.
And here's what the output looks like.
So this first number here, is the
regression constant.
That's the predicted score,
when all Xs are zero.
So that's the predicted score for
cognitive.
If I go back and look at the mean for
cognitive, it was 93.31.
And
that's exactly what I get for the
regression constant.
It's the mean for cognitive because I made
cognitive the reference group.
Now what is the negative 32.64, what is
that mean for clinical?
Well its a one unit increase in X is
associated with
that much of a predicted change in Y, or a
one unit increase in X took you from
cognitive to clinical for D1.
So that means clinical has, on average, 32
publications less than cognitive,
and if you look back at the summary
statistics, that's about right.
Developmental had slightly more than
cognitive 10.19, and
social had less than cognitive, 23.
And you might want to ask, are those
differences significant?
Well, then you just look out here to your
P values, and you can see that
the difference between clinical and
cognitive is significant,
the difference between developmental and
cognitive is not significant.
And the difference between cognitive and
social is significant
if we're using 0.05 as our cutoff, which
is standard.
Now you might want to know, I want to
compare say,
developmental to clinical or want to
compare clinical to social.
So if you wanted to do that, you would
have to change your reference group and
rerun this.
Which is why we typically don't do this,
we don't take this approach if we're just
looking at, a cat, one categorical
predictor and
these pairwise comparisons, I would do a
one-way
ANOVA instead.
But this is a way that you can
code a categorical variable in a multiple
regression analysis.
Because as you will see next week when we
do moderation
we are going to have some of our
predictors are categorical some of
them are continuous and then we want to
put them together in
a moderation analysis we have to have this
sort of coding scheme.
you might also want to change it so that
this number is not
the predictive score for cognitive but
just the
predictive score for all professors,
across all groups.
That, if you wanted to do that kind of
coding, its called effects coding.
The first effects coding I'm going to show
you is
unweighted and then I'll do a weighted
effects coding.
So, effects coding, you'll see I, I still
took cognitive as my reference group and,
but you'll see now
I gave them negative 1s across the board
and then, for
the rest of the codes, which I'm calling
C1, C2, and
C3, now, to call them effects codes
instead of dummy codes.
now you'll see well what's the predicted
score when all x's are 0?
Well it doesn't represent any one group
but it, what it does represent is
the average across all these groups.
So if I run that and look at the
coefficients.
Now what's changed, is the regression
constant, it's 81.9.
If you look back at the summaries
statistics, the mean is about 81.6,
so it's not exactly the mean for the
entire group.
And the reason for that is it's
unweighted,
it doesn't take into account the fact that
there are different number of professors
in each group.
So, in a second, we'll do the weighted
effects coding, and
that would get us the exact mean, 81.69, I
think it was.
But now, what do these regression
coefficients, tell me?
Well, this one is the difference between
the overall mean and clinical.
And this
one is the difference between the overall
mean and developmental and so on.
And again if you wanted to know the
difference between the overall mean
and cognitive, then you would have to
re-code this with a difference reference
group.
and again if you were just looking at
this, this example and you just wanted to
do.
just ask this question, are the number of
qualifications are different across these
groups then you wouldn't
do this sort of clumsy dummy coding or
effects
coding you just run a one way and over.
Again we need the system when we have
examples like
we'll cover next week where we have some
categorical predictors.
Like this one.
Like group, in the same model as
continuous predictors.
Like years, since phd or number of
publications.
And then if want it, look at the mod-,
those, those two predictors
together in one model we're going to have
to come up with this demi-coding scheme.
So finally, the way that it affects
coding,
if you wanted to get that regression
constant
to be the exact mean of all the
professors, then you would just have to
weight each
of them by the number of, sorry, the
number of professors in each group.
So instead of negative 1, it's just
negative N for number of professors in the
clinical group divided by N number of
professors in the cognitive group and so
on.
Just do instead of negative 1, just do
these
fractions and that would get you the exact
mean which
is just slightly off of 81.9.
I didn't actually run that one but I
wanted to show you exactly how you would
do
that if you ever come across a situation
where
you needed to do that, that's Weighted
Effects Coding.
So to wrap this up, its again conceptually
really simple.
Its just, you have categorical variables
that are nominal, so you can't throw them
into GLM or into the LM function NR
because they're string variables.
So you have to make them numeric in some
way
and the classic way of doing that is
called dummy coding.
Where you just pick one level of
your independent variable, or your
categorical variable and
make it the reference group.
That one gets all zeroes across
all the codes, and then you have just as
many
codes as groups minus1.
And then that's it.
And that allows you to look at categorical
predictors in the same model as
continuous predictors and put them
together in moderation analyses which
is what we're going to do in lecture 13.