Hi, and welcome back to Statistics One.
We're up to Lecture 7 now, and the
topic of Lecture 7 is Introduction to
Regression.
This is a pretty critical lecture in that
we're going to make a sort of
a transition point, away from correlation
and
descriptive statistics into regression,
prediction and inferential statistics.
So this is a really crucial lecture.
This lecture is divided into three
segments.
So in the first segment, I'll just give
you an overview of regression.
just what does it do, what is it used for?
Just the basics.
In the second segment, we'll do some math,
we'll talk about the calculation of the
regression coefficients.
And then in the third segment we'll talk
about assumptions underlying a linear
regression analysis, which is
what we're starting with here.
So let's dive into just the basics of
regression.
The most important concepts and topics to
take away from this segment are
just to understand the simple difference
or
distinction between simple regression and
multiple regression.
And then understand the components of the
regression equation.
And also understand what it means to have
a regression model and how to evaluate a
model.
So, last week we spent a lot of time
talking about correlation and one of
the things I asked and kept repeatedly
asking
is, what is, what are correlations good
for?
Well, correlations are good for
prediction.
That is, if I know that two variables are
highly
correlated then I can use one to predict
the other.
That's exactly what regression analysis is
designed to do.
So now we'll formally
specify one variable as an outcome
variable, and
another variable or a set of variables as
predictors.
And we'll create a regression equation,
regression
model to predict scores on that outcome
variable.
So that's regression in a nutshell.
And very simply, the distinction
between simple regression and multiple
regression, is simple regression only
involves one predictor variable.
Whereas multiple regression, we can have
as many predictor variables as we want.
So, most of the time, we'll be doing
multiple regression, but
for this first intro segment, I'll mainly
stick with simple regression.
You'll see it's so easy that I'll just,
I'll have to
sneak in a little bit of multiple
regression, just one example.
just to show you the power of multiple
regression.
The example I'm going to use for this
segment is
an example that you should be used to by
now.
It's the IMPACT data set.
We used it way back in Lab 2.
We actually used it in Lab 3 as well.
but if you're only following the lectures,
if you're not watching the labs then you
can go to this website and get a feel for
what the IMPACT assessment tool does.
It's an online assessment tool designed to
investigate the effects of sports-related
concussion.
And again, we looked at these data in, in
Labs 2 and 3 actually.
and we're going to look at them again here
in this segment in, on regression.
So if you recall, IMPACT provides data on
six measures or six variables.
It assesses your cognitive performance.
And also asks athletes
about symptoms that they might be
experiencing, perhaps after
suffering a really bad injury while
playing a sport or while practicing.
So the main measures are verbal memory,
visual memory,
visual motor speed, reaction time, impulse
control, and symptom score.
Symptom score is just a checklist really
of how the athlete is feeling.
So that's something that most athletic
departments, even high school athletic
departments, will have at their disposal.
All these other cognitive online
measures are, are more modern and that's
where IMPACT is designed to provide.
so what we're going to do in this segment
is see
if we can predict symptom score from these
newer measures.
So, if you go back to the Labs, and
particularly
Lab 3, we saw this correlation matrix.
So remember,
the topic of last week was correlation and
measurement.
And in the Lab, we talked about
correlation matrices.
so you, you've seen this before but let's
review.
these are the correlations among the six
main measures before athletes incurred any
injury.
So, you see some things that make sense,
so for example, if we look at the
correlation
between verbal memory and visual memory,
that's about 0.442, it's positive,
so that's good, that makes sense.
their two memory measures.
we also see a correlation of negative 0.5
between visual motor speed and overall
reaction time.
The reason it's negative is because higher
scores on visual motor speed
meant better performance whereas lower
scores, faster
reaction times, and overall reaction time
meant better performance.
But they're both speed measures, so the
fact that they're correlated is good.
But remember, the other thing to notice in
this pre-injury data set is symptom score
doesn't really correlate with anything.
And that's because the athletes aren't
really experiencing any symptoms.
They're healthy.
No one's suffered an injury yet.
And we demonstrated this graphically in
our fancy scatter plot matrix
organized by color so the brighter colors
indicate stronger correlations.
So you see, here's the correlation between
verbal memory and visual memory
that I referred to.
but again, the other thing to notice here
is where is symptom score on this graph?
It's, it's in the periphery, and most of
its correlations are colored blue.
That's because most people are at the
floor, or they don't show any
symptom score, so if there's no variance
in symptoms, then we can't have
co-variance in symptoms.
so symptoms isn't correlating any, with
anything before an injury.
So let's look at the data post-injury.
So now, I'm just looking at athletes after
suffering a
concussion and now you start to see some
things change.
Particularly in this bottom row with
respect to symptom score.
So now, symptom score is showing some
action.
And in particular, this correlation here
with impulse control, of 0.4.
So, this new measure of impulse control
that was
designed by the developers of this online
website IMPACT,
their, their measure of impulse control is
correlating with
symptom score, which is just a survey
checklist at 0.4.
So it's a pretty impressive post-injury.
What this means is their impulse control
measure
is pretty diagnostic of an injury, most
likely.
So we could use that to predict symptom
score, and that's what we'll do.
again we could demonstrate those
correlations graphically and in
a scatter plot matrix colored by magnitude
of correlation.
so now you see here
symptom score, it's no longer out in the
periphery.
All color blue not correlating with
anything.
It's correlated pretty well with impulse
control.
It's also correlated with verbal memory.
those are the two I'm going to enter into
the regression equation in this example.
So for this example and this is just for
illustrative purposes.
There's, you could, you could flip things
around and predict,
you know, impulse control from symptom
Score and so on.
I'm just doing this as an example because
we're familiar with this data.
but for this example let's put symptom
score in
as the outcome variable, so it's going to
be variable Y.
And then for the simple regression we'll
just put in one variable.
That's going to be impulse control.
And then, as I said, I want to show you a
multiple regression so we'll put in
impulse control and verbal memory.
But before we do that, let's take a closer
look at the actual regression equation.
I'm going to show you, show you the
regression equation with two different
forms of notation.
This first form notation I'm only
presenting because I think some of you
might be familiar with it, from maybe a
high school geometry class.
it's the formula for a line, right?
It says that Y is a linear function of X,
m is just the intercept, b is the slope.
So if you remember this from high school
geometry,
the b, the slope is the rise over run.
Remember that?
That's all we're looking at here.
That's all a simple regression does.
but I'm going to switch to this notation,
because this is more common in statistics,
and it's a more general notation that
allows us to move into multiple
regression.
and you'll see this in textbooks and on
websites if you're looking for other
information about statistics.
So, we're going to use B for the
regression coefficients, and
B subzero is the intercept.
And another name for that is the
regression constant B sub 1 is just the
slope relating X1 to Y.
Again it's the same formula.
It's just a formula for a line.
One other thing, or one other component of
regression that I want to highlight now,
is we can also look at the model, the
overall models, R squared.
This tells us the proportion of variance
in
the outcome measure that is explained by
the predictors.
At first when we just do simple
regression, it's
just going to be the correlation
coefficient, little r squared.
but when we build bigger models with
more, more predictors this will get more
interesting.
So you just want to highlight it now, that
we'll be looking at this multiple
correlation coefficient, and particularly
R squared, the percentage
of variance in y explained by the model.
So now let's go back to the example.
again, I'm going to put in symptom score
as the outcome measure.
Impulse control as the predictor and then
solve for the regression coefficients.
And I am just going to do this is R using
the function lm.
You'll get a chance to play with this
function a lot in Lab this week.
Lm just stands for linear model.
So here's the scatter plot relating
impulse control to symptom score.
You see there's a positive relationship.
Remember, if you look back at the
correlation matrix, the correlation was
about 0.4.
Yep, I made a note of it, 0.4.
and here are the regression coefficients.
So the constant is 20.48.
Again, that's just the intercept, that's
the predicted score on
Y when X is zero.
So 20.48, that's right there.
It's the predicted score on Y when X is
zero.
And then the slope of this line is 1.43.
What that tells us is, with every
one unit increase in X, there's a 1.43
increase in Y.
This last part, again,
has to do with the model R squared.
Since this is just a simple regression,
all I do is just square little r.
So, r was 0.4, r squared is 0.16, so
impulse
control is explaining 16% of the variance
in symptoms.
Now, I got all of those numbers from the
output that
I that I, that I got from R when I ran
this lm function.
And again, you'll have a chance to do this
in Lab but just notice at the top, I call
this function lm with symptom as the
outcome, impulse control
as the predictor, and then I asked for a
summary.
There's a lot of information here and
we'll cover a lot this in Lab.
And then a, some more of it next week when
we cover multiple regression in depth.
I just want to point out here, this is
where the regression coefficients came
from.
So there's that 20.48, and 1.43 and
then down at the bottom, there's my 0.16
or 16% as
R squared.
But the other thing you'll notice, and I
want
to highlight, and this is, this is where
I'm
referring to this lecture as sort of a
transition
lecture, is there's all this other stuff
over here.
R gives us all this other stuff, these
t-values and p-values, because now
when we're doing regression, we're most
likely engaging in inferential statistics.
We're not really interested
in just describing this sample, we want to
know if this sample,
the results from this sample are going to
generalize to other samples.
For example, if I'm a high school football
coach and
I want to know, does this online
assessment tool work.
I'm going to look at somebody else's data
and then just use it at my own school.
I'm not really interested in the
descriptives in, in these data.
I want to know if I can make an
inference from these sample data to a more
general population.
And we, when we engage in inferential
statistics, we're
going to start looking at these p values
and
making probability judgments, and I'm
going to have a
lot to say about that in the next two
lectures.
but I just wanted to highlight it for you
now.
Okay, so as I said, we're going to build
regression models
that are much more interesting than just
having one predictor.
We'll typically have two, three, lots of
predictors in there, and
we'll just keep adding in more predictors
until we get better models.
So to produce better models we can add
more predictors or we could just develop
better predictors.
So remember the lecture on measurement, we
could come up
with more reliable measures or more valid
measures of our construct.
So it doesn't always have to be just
adding in more predictors.
But to see how this works, let's just do a
very quick example.
I know this segment's getting a little
long,
so let's just zip through this second
example.
I'm just going to add in verbal memory as
a second predictor into this regression.
Again, you can just use the function lm
and R, which you'll do in Lab this week.
Here are the results.
On the left is the entire R output, on
the right I've summarized everything with
the regression equation.
Again, I just took the regression
coefficients
from this column and the output in R.
And I just took the R squared from the
bottom here, it's 0.2167.
I rounded up to about 22%.
So by adding in verbal memory
we went from 16% of the variance explained
in symptoms up to 22% of the variance
explained.
So our model got better by adding in
another predictor.
And the model might get even better if we
added in more, right?
IMPACT has six measures five excluding
symptoms, so we
could probably boost that percentage of
variance explained even more.
but I just wanted to illustrate the
difference
between simple and multiple.
The trick with multiple regression, and
we'll cover this
in detail next week in a full lecture on
multiple regression, is you can't
visualize it all in
one scatter plot, because now there are
two predictors.
And imagine if we have say, six
predictors.
You can't visualize it in one graphic.
Here on the left is the scatter plot
relating impulse control to symptoms.
On the right, verbal memory to symptoms.
There is one way
though, to capture it all in one scatter
plot.
And again, that's through the model R and
R squared.
Remember R is the multiple correlation
coefficient.
It's the correlation between the predicted
scores and the observed scores and
it tells you how well you're doing in
predicting the observed scores.
So if I save my predicted scores in R, and
we'll show you how to do that in the Lab,
then you could plot another scatter plot
with the predicted scores on
the x axis and the actual observed scores
on the y axis.
Again, I know from my output that that was
22%.
If I take the square root of that, what
that indicates
is the correlation between the observed
and the predicted scores is 0.47.
And that was higher than any correlation I
saw in my correlation matrix because,
I put in two predictors and the linear
combination of those two
predictors does better at predicting the
outcome than any one predictor by itself.
So that's the power of putting multiple
predictors
in and that's the power of multiple
regression.
So just a glimpse of that now, we'll get
to it in more detail next week.
So to wrap up this segment, again, the
most important concepts to take away
are just the distinction between simple
and multiple regression.
The components of the regression equation.
And the idea that we can build regression
models and look at the model r squared,
which
is the percentage of variance explained in
the outcome
measure by that set of predictors in the
model.