Hi, welcome back to Statistics One.
We're up to lecture 5, and the topic of
this lecture is correlation.
This is a big topic in statistics.
I'm sure you've heard lots about
correlations, or seen
correlations reported in the news or on
the Internet.
Or perhaps in research studies.
And this first lecture, I'm going to start
with
a broad overview, just to talk about the
concept.
And then we'll do some actual
mathematical calculations.
And then we'll talk about some
of the assumptions underlying
correlational analysis.
So this lecture is split into three
segments.
As I said in the first segment, what I'd
like to do is
just give you a broad overview of the
concept of correlation and some examples.
In the second segment, we'll walk
through the mathematical calculation of
the correlation
coefficient r, that's Pearson's product
moment correlation.
Which I'll have a lot to say about in
segment two.
And then finally in segment three, we'll
talk about
some of the assumptions underlying a
typical correlation analysis.
So let's launch into segment one.
The important concepts and topics to take
away from this first segment.
This first, obviously, what is
correlation?
And then, what are they used for?
and we're also going to look at a lot of
scatterplots.
You saw some scatterplots in Lecture Two,
when
I talked about the method of correlational
studies.
But now we'll really investigate
scatterplots and look at all the details.
then there's
a lot of words of caution.
[LAUGH]
So, I can talk about what are correlations
used to do?
And I'm, and with the caution I'm going to
say
what are correlations not supposed to be
used for?
so we'll go through a lot of a lot of
cautionary notes toward the end.
And then I'll just list some other types
of correlations beyond the
Pearson product moment correlation which
is the one we're going to emphasize today.
So first, what is a correlation procedure?
It's just a statistical analysis used to
measure or describe the relationship
between two variables.
Correlation coefficients can range between
positive 1 and negative 1.
A positive one indicates a perfect
positive correlation.
A negative 1 indicates a perfect negative
correlation.
0 of course, indicates there's no
relationship at all.
That's independence.
So perfect positive correlation means, as
the scores on one
variable go up, the scores on the other
variable go up.
Perfect negative correlation would be, as
the scores go up
on one variable, the scores go down on the
other.
And I'll show you exa, examples of that in
scatterplots.
It's best to just look at it in a
scatterplot.
So, what are they used for?
Well, we've already seen some, uses of
correlation in lecture 2.
Very simply, if we have two variables,
let's call
them X and Y, and they're correlated, if I
know
an individual's value on X, then I can
predict their
score on Y, particularly if there's a very
strong correlation.
And there're lots of these examples that
you're probably familiar with.
one is IQ and academic achievement.
Right?
So if you're high on IQ, and I know that,
then
I'm going to predict you're probably going
to do pretty well in school.
some newer research is coming out which is
very interesting is
socioeconomic status in very young kids is
also correlated with academic achievement.
So if I know socioeconomic status, I might
be able
to predict academic achievement years
later.
once we know that, hopefully we can
do something to intervene with that
relationship.
Right?
So, that's what correlation is mainly used
for,
to describe relationships and then, it's
used for predictions.
Which leads us to the next topic,
regression.
So, let's go back to this example of
working memory capacity and intelligence.
So I've mentioned that this is my area of
expertise in my own research.
And in the first lecture on experimental
designs, we talked about
this study and this whole sort of
literature that's booming right now.
It's actually an industry that's booming
online.
Where people are trying to train their
working memory to enhance
their intelligence.
Well, where did that idea come from?
Well, it came from years of research.
Some if it done by my graduate adviser,
Randy Ingle.
Some of it done by myself and my
colleagues showing that.
Scores on tests of working memory capacity
are highly
correlated with traditional standardized
tests of intelligence or IQ.
So we know that working
memory is correlated with IQ.
So if I know a person's IQ, then I could
predict how well they're
going to do in my lab when they come and
take a working memory task.
So here is an example of a scatterplot
illustrating that correlation.
This is actually really strong
correlation.
We exaggerated it to make it clear that
it's a very strong positive correlation.
What we're looking at a correlation
between intelligence and working memory.
So on the x axis, I have IQ scores.
And you'll notice that they're
standardized, right?
They're standardized on that z scale.
And I know that, because the mean is 0.
The same thing is true of the working
memory task.
So the working memory task in this example
is the N-back task.
That was the task that was used in that
experimental example that
I described back in lecture one, where
subjects had to do that N-back
task every day for, for weeks.
That was their working memory training.
So the N-back task is a measure of working
memory capacity.
But more importantly what this shows is
each
dot in the scatterplot, each dot is an
individual
and the line that runs through the dots
is called the regression line or the
prediction line.
And it just runs right through the middle
of that scatterplot.
And what this shows is.
If, you know, if you're above average on
IQ, then
you tend to be above average on working
memory capacity.
That's a positive correlation, and it's a
pretty strong positive correlation.
If you see up here, little r is 0.8.
We're going to, in the next segment, I'll
show you how to calculate
that little r, but just for now, know that
that's a really high correlation
coefficient.
It's actually rare that we seem that high.
Now here's where all the cautionary notes
and tales come in.
the first one is one that you've all heard
before,
but to me it's not really the most
important one.
I've put it first because I know most
people are familiar with it.
So we know that correlation does not imply
causation.
Well, let's unpack that.
What does that mean?
It means that working memory capacity
doesn't cause intelligence.
And likewise, intelligence doesn't cause
working memory capacity.
There could be intervening variables, most
likely there are lots of
intervening variables associated with the
brain,
particularly prefrontal cortex and
parietal cortex.
We know there's certain regions that are
very important for working memory.
And for intelligence.
so we can't say from this correlational
study, that one causes the other.
they're just related, we know that they're
correlated, there's an association there.
So, correlation does not imply causation.
A great example my assistant
[INAUDIBLE]
came up with.
Is going to bed with your boots on is
correlated with hanging, having a headache
in the morning.
[LAUGH]
That's an association.
It doesn't mean having your boots on
caused
the headache, what's more likely is that
you
were drunk and fell asleep with your boots
on and were hung over in the morning.
And that's why you had the headache.
There're lots of fun examples of this if
you Google correlation and fun examples.
so I think we all know that correlation
does not imply causation.
More importantly, and this is what I'm
going to focus on in lecture six
primarily, is the magnitude of a
correlation depends on a lot of factors.
Including sampling, which we've already
talked about.
That idea of getting a random and
representative sample.
It also depends critically on measurement
of
your variables, so measurement of x and y.
Specifically, do you have reliable
measures?
And do you have valid measures?
So for example, in the intelligence
literature.
We need to know that we have reliable
assessments of intelligence, we need, we
need to know
that they're valid assessments of
intelligence, in order for
us to make any sense of the correlation
analysis.
So we're going to spend a lot of time
talking about that in lecture 6.
For now, let's just look at one of these
assumptions.
The idea that we have random and
representative sampling.
So, I showed you that there's a strong
correlation
between working memory capacity and
intelligence in healthy young adults.
And I've seen that in my own research.
It's been replicated many, many times
over the last couple of decades, but
that's if we look at all young,
healthy adults.
If we get a heterogeneous sample.
Of say, all high school graduates.
What if we relied on a more convenient
sample, let's say, a prestigious selective
school of higher
education like Princeton.
and we might want to
ask, what is the correlation between IQ
and working
memory among college graduates?
It's a different kind of sample.
So let's look at that scatterplot.
This is a bit exaggerated again.
We made up the data.
but now you'll see the correlation is not
very strong.
It's only 0.2.
And why is that?
Well, if you look at the IQ distribution,
again we exaggerated this.
But everybody's above average on IQ
because they're college graduates.
They were selected into college most
likely on the basis
of some sort of standardized tests like an
IQ test.
so this is not that far-fetched.
And, actually, in my own research, I did
look at
the relationship between working memory
and intelligence
in a selective institution, not Princeton,
and
the correlation was 0.22, where I'm used
to finding a correlation of about 0.66.
This is known as attenuation of
correlation due
to restriction of range in one of your
variables.
So the fact that we only have this really
smart people restricts our range.
In other words,
it restricts our variance.
Which doesn't allow for us to find
covariance.
And finally is, is the last cautionary
note.
And it's perhaps the most important for
general consumers of statistics.
And particularly correlations.
Is a lot of people get upset when they
hear.
Let's say you know, your score on some
standardized test predicts how well you're
going to do in college.
but it's only a sample statistic.
A correlation coefficient
is a sample statistic just like a mean is
a sample statistic.
And it may not be representative Of
everyone
in the sample, unless the correlation is
1.0.
Alright, so, I, I'm, I'm a perfect example
of this.
when I took the standardized tests here in
the US, they're called the
SAT, I scored really well on the math and
really poor on the verbal,
[LAUGH]
that's why I'm a statistics teacher.
and in school I tended to have very high
grades in math and science.
But not so high in things like history and
language despite the fact that those
things are correlated, right?
If you go back to lecture two on
correlational studies we saw that this was
the example I used for a moderate
correlation between say math and language.
So, if you look at the dots, you see that
on average,
as you go up on one, you go up on the
other.
But let's say this is math, and let's say
this is history.
You know, I was like this guy out here.
[LAUGH]
Off the charts on math, but really below
average on history.
frankly because at that age, I didn't have
the patience to sit down and read long
texts.
so I didn't do very well in things like
History or, or English.
It wasn't quite that low, maybe about
there but the point is.
as you go up on one, as, on average, as
people go up one one score, they go up on
the
other score, that's a positive
correlation.
But, it may not be represented if for
every individual in the sample, okay.
That's one of the most important things
to take away from thinking about
correlations.
This final note is, there're several types
of correlation coefficients,
depending on the types of variables that
you're looking at.
So, go back to lecture three, where we
talked about types of variables.
I'm going to emphasize this one right
here,
the Pearson product-moment correlation
coefficient, or little r.
That's what we're going to focus on in the
next segment.
and that's the most common one.
Because it, it provides us with the most
amount of information.
We have a continuous variable x and a
continuous variable
y and we can look at the correlation
between the two.
If one of our variables is continuous and
one is dichotomous, it's just 0
or 1 Then there's a different coefficient,
it's called the point bi-serial
correlation function.
Also if we have
two dichotomous variables, if both x and y
are dichotomous, then we'll calculate the
Phi coefficient.
And if we have both X and Y as ranked or
ordinal variables, then we can calculate
what's called the Spearman rank-order
correlation.
I'm just listing these here so that you're
aware of them.
For now, since this is just an intro stats
course, we're going to focus on just the
Pearson product-moment
correlation, little r.
It's by far the most common one that
you'll see, that you'll encounter.
But just remember and for your own
knowledge, know that there are other
types.
And it depends on what kinds of variables
you're looking at.
So to sum up this, this segment, we talked
about
just, what is a correlation, what are they
used for.
We're going to look at scatter plots a lot
when we're talking about correlations.
There's a lot of cautionary notes that you
have to keep in mind and then
remember, there're different types of
correlations depending
on the types of variables that you're
analyzing.
And that wraps up this segment.
[BLANK_AUDIO]