[BLANK_AUDIO].
Hi!
Welcome, to Statistics One.
This is the first lecture, and the topic
for this lecture is Experimental Research.
As I mentioned in the introduction video,
it's
important to know as either a consumer of,
of statistics, or as someone engaged in
statistical
analyses, what type of research are you
doing?
What kinds of questions are you
asking, and, and what kinds of questions
might you ask of your data?
So, in this first week, we'll talk about
first experimental research
here in lecture one, and then
correlational research in lecture 2.
Because they have a very different feel
and they,
they typically work with very different
kinds of data.
so let's hear this first lecture, talk
about
experimental research.
This first lecture is broken
up into 3 segments, and that'll be common
as we go through the course.
each lecture will be typically broken,
into either 2 or 3 segments
hopefully around 10 minutes each, but
that'll fluctuate a bit.
so in this first lecture we have 3
segments.
The first one, I'll give you just an
example
of experimental research in action the
polio vaccine trials.
another in the second segment, I'll give
you
another example more recent research on
working memory training.
>> And then, in the third segment,
we'll talk more, about this concept of
randomness.
you'll see an important aspect to
experimental research, is random selection
from a population, and random assignment
to conditions.
So let's go into this first segment.
In the first half of the twentieth
century, there were approximately 20,000
cases of polio, per year, in the USA.
In 1952, was a particularly bad year.
There were 58,000 cases, just in that one
year alone.
And polio was a very debilitating disease.
It was very frightening
>> it ha, it, it, was, happened among
children
of all, backgrounds, and, some years, as I
noted here, in
1952, were particularly bad and, and, and,
and worrying.
so in 1952, the first effective polio
vaccine, was developed by Dr. Jonas Salk.
And how do we know, in retrospect you
know, over
60 years later, how do we know that it was
effective?
Well, through experimental research.
More specifically through, randomized
controlled experiments.
And this set of studies, is now known as
the Salk vaccine trials.
one of the greatest examples of
experimental research, put to use to
solve a very critical problem facing
modern society, and it's a
really great success story of ex, of
experimental research.
So how did it work?
Well, to do experimental research.
Again, go back to the introductory
lecture.
We need
a sample, and we need a population.
So what was the population?
At first, the population was all children
in the USA.
And it, it, actually, the population
really is all children worldwide.
But these initial studies, were funded by
the U.S. government.
The Salk vaccine trials.
I'll define the population, as all
children in the U.S. that's what Salk was
hoping he could generalize his vaccine
results to, is all children in the U.S.
The sample, of course he couldn't get his
hands on all children in the US.
So the sample initially, was just 4000
children from the state of Virginia.
That turned out to be pretty promising
results
from that first sample, so the US
government
funded the research further, and they
expanded the sample ultimately to
include 1.8 million children from 44 of
the fifty United States.
So in this experiment, the independent
variable, or what some
people may call the treatment.
>> Is what the child actually received.
So some children received the actual live
vaccine,
the polio vaccine, and other children
received a placebo.
So they got a vaccine, but there was no,
live
[INAUDIBLE],
live polio vaccine, it was just, placebo.
The dependent variable is what you measure
after the treatment.
So the dependent variable was, you can
think of this in one of two ways.
One if you look at the level of the
individual child.
You could think of it as a polio
diagnosis.
So each individual child, is either going
to have a polio diagnosis,
so we could score that as a one or not be
diagnosed with polio.
You would score that as a 0.
Or, if we look at the level of a
community of children, look at towns or
villages or states.
Then we could look at the rate of polio,
among a certain number of, of children.
So two different ways, to score this
dependent variable.
One of the cool things about using the
Salk vaccine trial, as an
example to start this course, is it was a
double blind experiment.
Those are actually.
>> Pretty rare in experiment, in
experimental psychology, or in, in,
experimental trials, in general, because
it's difficult to do.
What
I mean by double-blind, is that the
experimenter
didn't know if the treatment that they
were giving
>> To the child was the placebo or was
the vaccine.
So the person administering the actual
vaccine, didn't know if
the child was getting the vaccine, or
getting the placebo.
So no one on site at the time knew which
one the child was getting, and
the child and the parents, they didn't
know
if they were getting the vaccine, or the
placebo.
The final results, from several trials can
be summarized here.
This is the rate per 100,000.
So, children who were given the vaccine,
28 out of 100,000
went on to develop polio, versus the
control, who got a placebo.
71 out of 100,000 developed polio.
So, you can see, almost, 3 times
more children, who did not receive the
vaccine went on to develop polio.
So, we can see, just looking at these
numbers, that this was a
success story and sure enough, the US
continued to use the Salk vaccine.
And by 1994, polio had been completely
eradicated, from all of the Americas.
So this is a great success story, of how
we can see experimental research.
>> Put to use to solve a problem, and
eradicate what I call bad stuff.
so to summarize this segment, the major
benefit of experiemental
research, is that they allow for strong
claims about causality.
So why does stuff happen?
So why was the polio vaccine happening?
There was this disease that was spreading
through communities.
Salk thought he had a vaccine that could
prevent it.
And sure enough, if he gave the
vaccination to enough
children, they were able to prevent the
bad stuff from happening.
So again,
experiments allow us to make causal
claims, about why stuff happens.
So that allows us to predict stuff, which
mean we
can pre, prevent bad stuff, and we can
promote good stuff.
[LAUGH].
So we use it in very basic terms, right?
so this is a good example where societies
are.
We have a lot of bad stuff happening.
We have this disease, we have to
eradicate, and
if we can do an experiment to predict why
it's
happening, and how we can stop it, then
indeed, we
can stop it, and that's what the Salk
vaccine trials.
>> were able to do.
These strong causal
claims require a lot of things, so, they
require what I call true independent
variables.
That is, a group of, of subjects, or in
this case, a group of children Come to a
facility, and
they're randomly assigned to receive one,
level of
variable or another.
So they were randomly assigned to receive
the vaccine or the placebo.
That's a true independent variable.
I'll talk in the next lecture about, some
quasi independent variables,
that aren't as strong as this.
it requires a random,
and representative sample so initially the
Salk vaccine
trials only were done on children from
Virginia.
And maybe it only worked in that subset of
children.
Maybe it wouldn't generalize to the entire
United States.
They had to see, so they had to broaden
their sample, get a more
random representative sample, of the
entire United
States, to see if it really worked.
Fortunately, it did.
and finally.
Experimental research in these strong
causal claims depend on the,
require that we don't have any confounds
in the experiment.
And that's almost impossible, to rule out
entirely.
There might always be confounds.
So there could have been confounds, in
terms of the age
of children, or again the geographical
location, or their socioeconomic status.
There could have been lots of confounds,
in this example.
Fortunately they
ruled out most of those in the research as
they were doing the, the vaccine trials.
But its something to keep in mind, as we
look at experimental research.
These strong causal claims, require that
there are no confounds lurking behind,
lurking in the shadows.
And we'll address that issue, a little
more directly in the next segment as
we look at Working memory training.