Welcome to Statistics one, lab five.
The goals in today's lab will be, will
repeat a lot of the steps that we've
done in previous labs, so we'll read a
data file into R, we'll print some summary
statistics.
But the emphasis this week is on null
hypothesis significance testing.
As well as standard error, confidence
intervals and model comparison.
So we'll do correlation and regression
analyses
again but emphasizing significance tests
and the problems
with significance tests and how to
supplement them
with things like confidence intervals and
model comparisons.
And I'm going to use the same example that
I used last week the correlational study
investigating
[SOUND]
the predictors of physical endurance in
adults the outcome variable is physical
endurance.
The predictors are age and number of years
actively engaged in exercise.
The initial analyses are the same as last
week, so we're going to assume a sample
size of
200, but then to show you the importance
and the impact of sample size I'll reduce
that,
I'll take a random subset of the 200, just
20.
And then we'll rerun the analyses.
again, I've commented out all this
beginning stuff.
So just make sure you're in the right
working directory.
you might need to install a new package
here.
We're going to use ggplot 2, which we'll
use a lot going forward in the course.
It's a, it's, it's sort of the premier
graphics package in R.
so go ahead and install that package.
Now I'm going to start right here.
I'm going to load my packages with the
library function.
I'll read in the data I don't need to look
at it because we've seen
this before but then I'll run the
describe function just to get the summary
statistics.
[SOUND]
So here are the summary statistics.
And this is what we saw last week.
We have 200 subjects with a, a mean age of
about 49.
Active years about ten and a half.
Endurance, remember was this scale that
went from zero to 60, an arbitrary scale.
But we did all that last week.
So let's quickly go back.
To the script.
In this lab I'm going to illustrate some
of the calculations of these values
because we're not doing a lot of hand
calculations which is different from my
live class.
so I just want to show you where these
numbers are coming from.
So just in that describe output you saw
standard error.
So standard error, if you look at this
line here in my, in my script.
Standard error's just the standard
deviation divided
by the square root of sample size.
Remember standard error is just how much
sampling error on average do we expect?
And this is the formula.
So standard error is standard deviation
over the square root of n.
So what I can do in R is I can take
that described function and I can save it
into a table.
I'll call it table 1.
And if I do that, let's execute those two
lines of code.
Then, I just have table 1.
It's the same exact thing as I just, as I
just got from the describe function.
But now
I can access the values inside that table,
which becomes
really handy and we'll do this a lot going
forward.
So for example, if I want the standard
deviation
for the age variable, then I could just go
into the table and go to row 2, column
4, because that's where standard deviation
for age is.
And if I want the sample size, I can go to
row 2, column 2.
So let's
just execute those.
[SOUND]
So the standard deviation for age is in
this table, and it's in row 2, column 4.
So if I go to row 2, there's age.
And column 4, 1, 2, 3, 4.
There's standard deviation.
Okay, so it's, it's going to return 10.48.
And the sample size for age well its the
same for all variables but it's, it's
table 1.
Row 2 column 2.
So row 2.
Again, age.
Column 2, 200.
The reason I'm showing you that is we
could, we don't need
to do this because R gives it to you in
the describe function.
But you could calculate the standard error
of age based on those values.
So I could just calculate the standard
error
of age based on the standard deviation and
the square root of the sample size.
So if I execute that line of code, I get
0.74 for the standard error
of age, and if we go back up in the table,
yep, there it is.
So we did the calculation correctly.
Just to be really sure, I could test it
and see if my calculation equals
Table 1, row 2, column 13, that's where
standard error was.
so if I execute
that, I get true.
Okay?
So we did it right.
The point of that is to illustrate that
you
can save output in R into tables, like I
did
here, save it into table 1, and then you
can access the values in that table to do
calculations.
And that's going to be handy, going
forward.
Okay, so let's go back to the main topic,
correlation regression.
we ran
this correlation analysis last week, but
what we, what we didn't do is, core.test.
So, we can run a null hypothesis
significance test on
each of these correlations, to see if they
are statistically significant.
In other words, the null hypothesis is
that the correlation coefficient is 0.
And this will give us a p value.
Which stands for the probability of
obtaining this correlation given the
assumption that the, null is true.
So let's see what we get from these.
[SOUND]
Let me go back up a little bit.
So, remember these are the same data from
last
week, so we had, like, correlations of
0.33 between age
and active years, and between endurance
and active years,
but then not much going on between age and
endurance.
Here's the output for, for core.test.
It gives the Pearson product moment
correlation.
Here is the correlation, 0.33.
.
And here's
the p values.
It's a very low p value.
That's significant.
same is true for the correlation between
endurance and active years, 0.33.
Low p-value.
But then for endurance and age that's a
correlation of
negative 08 and that's a P value of 0.23,
so there we would have to retain the null.
That's not a statistically
significant correlation.
Okay, I'm going to save those correlations
into a table.
Table 2, because we're going to use them
to illustrate some calculations in the
regression analysis.
So let me just save that, table 2, go
back into the console, looks like it did
it fine.
Great.
Okay, let's move on to the regression
analyses.
I'll start with unstandardized an
unstandardized regression analysis,
just a simple regression.
Again, we did this last week, so I'm going
to try and go through this quickly.
So here is that first model predicting
endurance
from age, and of course, that's not
significant.
And if you notice, the p-value here is
0.232 for that regression coefficient.
It's the same exact p-value as up here for
the correlation coefficient.
All right, that's true because we're just
doing a simple regression with one
predictor.
But now let's illustrate some calculations
again.
So, how would we calculate that regression
coefficient?
Well, I talked about it in lecture where
we, I talked about calculating the
sums of squares residual, and the sums of
squares for the model, and so on.
but another formula I gave you for
the regression coefficient is this formula
right here.
The regression coefficient can be
calculated by taking the correlation
coefficient and multiplying by the
standard deviation of y over the standard
deviation of x.
Well, I have all these values now in
tables,
right, so in table 2, that's my
correlation matrix.
I'm looking at the relationship between
age and endurance.
So, let's go back into the console here.
If I look at the correlation matrix, it's
going to be row 3, column 1 to get this
correlation coefficient for this model.
That's why I get row 3, column 1.
So the model's regression coefficient,
model 1's B,
is the correlation coefficient, which is
in table 2,
row 3, column 1, times the standard
deviation
of y, which is in the first table.
Row 4, column 4, and the standard devia-,
deviation
of X, which is in row 2, column 4.
So let me just execute all of that.
[SOUND]
And what we see here is we have a, we
calculated a
regression coefficient of negative 0.08.
If you go back up into our output from
the LM, that's exactly what we get.
Little bit of rounding error but we did it
right.
So here's just illustrating
how you can calculate these values.
from the basic formulas that I gave you
in lecture rather than just relying on the
LM function to give it, to give it to you.
just helps to sort of understand this at
first.
Of course, you'd never do this piece
again, this is just to help you learn the
concepts and learn the math underlying.
linear regression.
Okay, so now let's look at how the
standard error is calculated.
So standard error of a regression
coefficient is, it's a little bit
more difficult, the formula, it's not
quite as intuitive, but here it is.
It's the square root of the sums of
squares residual, over and minus 2,
divided by the sums of squares for X.
So, VertNet's sort of in notation
form here.
Standard error for the regression
coefficient is the square root of sums of
squares residual over N minus two, divided
by sums of squares for X.
I'm going to create one more table here
using the ANOVA function.
And that's going to give me the sums of
squares residual.
Of'course we could calculate it by hand
right.
We could go through all 200 subjects and
get their predicted score and their actual
score and
get the residual and square it and sum it.
but that would be pretty tedious, and this
is going to be a long lab anyway.
So let's just use that ANOVA function.
So what the ANOVA function returns are
these sums of squares for the model.
So if you think back to lecture, where I
talked about sums of squares for
model and sums of squares for residual,
this is sums of squares for the model.
This is sums of squares, residual.
So we're going to use this value to
calculate standard error.
So, sums of the squares
residual is in table 3, row 2, column 2.
Just to make sure we did that right, let's
execute that.
[SOUND]
Right.
So there's the table.
Row two, column two, 23,000.
I now want to divide that
by n minus 2.
Well, that's degrees of freedom.
We'll ha, we'll talk a lot about degrees
of freedom when we cover analysis of
variance.
but for now, in this example it's just n
minus 2.
So, that was in the table.
It's,
it's in the, row 2, column 1, so let me
just grab
that.
So if you look at
this table, row 2, column 1, remember
there are
200 subjects, so 200 minus 2 is 198, and
there I have that value.
The sums of squares for X, the entire
value, variable X Is the sums of squares
for the model, and the sums of squares of
the residual.
So I can go back into the table in column
2.
And just take row 1 and row 2 and add
them together, and that'll give me sums of
squares x.
So, lemme do that.
So now I have sums of squares x.
It's just the sum of, oops.
Just the sum of this column here.
So now we can calculate the standard error
of the regression coefficient.
It's the square root of the sums of
squares, rigid, residual which
we got from table 3 which we got from
running the ANOVA function.
Degrees of freedom also came from that
ANOVA
table but we could have just plugged it
in.
It's the total number of subjects minus 2.
And sums of squares x, again, we got from
the ANOVA table, it's just the
sums of squares for the model plus sums of
squares residual.
So now, if I do that.
[SOUND]
The standard error for the regression
coefficient according to our calculations
is 0.07 if we go back up to where we ran
the LM function.
You see the standard error is 0.07.
Great.
So we did it right, and it matches up.
Again, going forward when you do multiple
regression,
you're just going to rely on this LM call
and
you're going to rely on r to do the
calculations for you.
But I think it's nice to go through this
once when
you're first learning it to see where the
numbers are coming from.
Okay, so, now let's move to confidence
intervals.
It's really easy to get confidence
intervals in r.
So if I want the 95 percent confidence
interval
around that regression coefficient, all I
need to do is
use the function confint, So confint
around model 1.
You can use the confint function around
any fitted model.
So if I do that,
it returns the 95% confidence interval for
the regression, the regression constant,
but also
the regression coefficient, and that's
what we
really are concerned with, is this
interval.
Alright so it goes from negative 23 to
positive 0.05.
The fact that it spans 0 indicates to you
that it's not going to
be a significant regression coefficient.
Okay, because we are in,
in the 95% confidence interval is included
0,
no relationship so that's a sign right
there
that this is that we're going to retail
the null and that this is not significant.
We could also illustrate the calculation
of that confidence interval.
So, the upper value of a con, confidence
interval, to get the higher value, you
take
the regression coefficient and you add a
product
term, which is a function of standard
error.
It's just standard error times some,
critical t
value which is based on degrees of freedom
and
the degree of confidence.
It turns out there's a really nifty way
you can get that in R using this QT
function
so.
I combine 0.025 and 0.975, because
that puts 2.5% of the distribution on the
lower end
of the sampling distribution, and 2.5% on
the higher end.
And then my degrees of freedom is 198.
So, right here is where I'm telling it
that I want 95%, here is where I'm telling
it what degrees of freedom are.
And remember I have to, I have to
indicate degrees of freedom because
remember there's a
family of t distributions and they differ
slightly
according to sample size and degrees of
freedom.
So this tcrit
value depends on not just the degree of
confidence but also
degrees of freedom.
So let me run that, and,
that tcrit value is about 1.97.
In a perfect Gaussian distribution a, a
perfect
normal distribution the z distribution
that corresponds to 1.96.
So we're pretty close because this is a
large sample size.
it's just a little wider.
So now I could calculate the interval as
the regression coefficient.
Which was negative 0.08 plus T crit times
standard error.
And I get my interval.
Negative 22 to positive 0.05.
That's the same thing we got when we ran
the conf int function.
Little bit of rounding error.
again we'll never do this piece again
we'll just use the conf int function but.
Again, I wanted to illustrate where these
numbers are
coming from, and that's, that's the
formula right there.
Okay, let's go back into the script.
now we're just going to look at the
scatter plot again, but now we're going to
make
use of these fancier graphics that, exist
in the ggplot package, and they're really
cool.
And, what I like about this scatter plot,
and I, I really
encourage my colleagues and my, my
collaborators to do this, is to
plot confidence intervals around a
regression line.
Because remember a regression coefficient
is just a point estimate.
And it's susceptible to sampling error.
So we should be explicit about that in our
graphical representation of
the correlation, and of the scatter plot.
Ggplot allows us to do that.
So let's see what it looks like.
And there we go.
That is very cool.
so I plotted age on the x axis, endurance
on the y axis.
Remember, the dots are all just individual
participants.
And they're sort of all over the place,
because
there's, there's not much of a correlation
here, right?
It was like, negative 0.08 or something,
so there's
a slight negative slope.
But notice this shaded region around it.
That represents the 95% confidence
interval around that regression
coefficient.
And that's a really nice thing to do when
plotting scatter plots.
And unfortunately it's just not done
enough at least in the social sciences
but hopefully we can, we can encourage
people to do this more often.
I think it looks pretty cool.
Okay, so now let's look at model 2.
I'm not going to go through all these
illustrations
of calculations again, because that takes
a while.
and we did this last week.
so let's just print the, the output of the
model and the confidence intervals.
So here we're predicting endurance from
active years, and the
t-value for that regression coefficient is
4.8, and that's significant.
Right.
We're now explaining about 11% of the
variance.
And if you look at the confidence interval
it goes from about 0.44 to 1.06.
So 0 is nowhere near that 95% confidence
interval.
Another sign that this is a significant
predictor.
Let's look at our cool new scatter plot
with the confidence interval on it.
Nice.
There we go.
we got a nice strong positive correlation.
And we put in the confidence interval
around the regression line.
Le'ts quickly just move through model 3.
we, again, we did this last week, so I'm
just
going to zip through it and just show you
the plot.
[SOUND]
There we go.
The, the slope is a little bit steeper
here.
as we go back into the output we're now
explaining about 15% of the variance.
So we're doing a little better by putting
both
predictors in than by just putting active
years in.
And the final thing we can do is conduct a
model comparison,
an actual null hypothesis significance
test.
To determine whether model 3 is
significantly better than model 2.
And it's real simple, we use this ANOVA
function again.
So we just do ANOVA model 2 model 3, and
that will give me a p-value indicating
whether I should reject or retain the null
hypothesis,
where the null hypothesis is that model 2
and
model 3.
Are equivalent in terms of how well they
explain the outcome variable.
So here's the output from that model
comparison, line of code.
And here it gives us an F statistic, which
we're going to talk a lot more about when
we
get to analysis of variance, so just bear
with
me here, I'm going to gloss over some of
the details.
but it's, it's a lot like the T statistic
it,
you get a certain value, and then it has a
corresponding
p-value based on a sampling distribution.
Again, we'll talk about this more in-depth
when we cover ANOVA.
But the key point here is that the p-value
is less than 0.05, so we can say
that the difference between model 2 and
model 3 is statistically significant.
So model 3 is doing better.
Also notice that this p-value, is exactly
the same p-value as the one
for age, when age was added in with active
years.
Because that's the difference between
model 1 and model 2, right?
It's the same thing.
Okay.
Now let's go back to the script.
I just want to show you the standardized
solutions.
Again, we did this last week, but I just
want to run through it, and show you the
confidence intervals.
I'm going to run them all at once, because
I
want to get through this, so we can move
on
to the final part of this script.
So
here's where the, the standardized
regression analyses started.
The thing to notice in the standardized is
the regression constant is always
right around zero, and this is out to, you
know, 18 significant digits, right?
oops, didn't want to do that.
But its zero right we're standardizing it
so that the intercept is zero.
But if you look at say,
you know the model R squared percentage of
variance explained
that's exactly the same and the width of
the confidence intervals.
Those will be exactly the same.
It's just the, the intercept that changes.
Okay.
.
So just to drive that point home, we
could do that same model comparison To
compare model
2 and model 3 standardized, but you're
going to
get the same exact thing that you got
before.
All right?
So, let's run it.
So, here's the standardized model
comparison.
Here's the F value and the P value.
That same P value, 0.002.
Just to show you it's exactly the same,
I reran the unstandardized, there are the
values.
Okay.
The sums of squares, those change, right?
Because they change the scale of the, of
the variables, but
the F ratio and the P value are exactly
the same.
Okay?
Okay, so the last thing I want to do in
this lab is now just radically reduce the
sample size.
So we had a really nice sample size of
200.
Now let's cut it down to 20, and see what
happens to some of these significance
tests and confidence intervals.
So I'm just going to take a random sample
of 20 from this data
frame PE.
And I'm going to call it PE20.
And the way to do that is to use a
function called sample.
And I'm just going to take out 20 rows.
I want all, I still want all the columns,
I
want all the variables but I just want 20
subjects.
So I'm going to do that and run the
describe function and now I have just 20
subjects.
and you'll notice that the standard errors
are a lot larger because there's more
sampling error if we're only getting
samples of, of 20.
So what happens with the correlations?
Remember that this is just a random sample
of 20, so
I'm not sure what the actual correlation
values will be, let's see.
let me go back up in the output.
pretty close to before, although now we
got a 0.2.
so we've got 0.33, 0.38, and 0.2.
this is randomized differently each time,
so I
wasn't sure what I was going to get there.
sort of nice that we got a 0.33, right,
because we had 0.33 with an n of 200.
So let's go to that 0.33 with an n of 20,
and see if it's significant.
So age and active years is right here.
And there's that 0.33, and here's the
p-value.
It's 0.16.
So the same exact magnitude correlation,
0.33, is
now no longer significant with an n of 20.
That's because the standard error is
higher.
So, again this illustrates one of the
problems with null hypothesis significance
testing is it's biased by sample size.
That same exact correlation coefficient
before
we could have claimed was statistically
significant
with an n of 200, now with an n of 20, we
can't.
so that's a little bit funky.
even here, a correlation of 0.38, still
not significant, the p is 0.09.
Okay, so when you're doing correlational
analyses or correlational studies, you
typically need large samples.
[SOUND]
Now let's look at what happens to the
regression models.
So again, I'm just going to run all of
these
at once, because I think you get the gist.
and let me go down to model 3, model 3.20,
which has
both predictors in the equation.
And if we go to the table of coefficients.
What we see is, neither one of them is
significant.
So remember that's different from before,
in when we
had an n of 200, both of these were
significant.
Now neither one is significant.
Also notice the confidence intervals are
much much wider.
Again that's because the sample size is
so much smaller we expect more sampling
error.
We have a higher standard error, wider
confidence intervals.
Okay.
Finally let's just do that model
comparison.
And you guessed it.
It's not going to be significant.
So the f is really low and we have a p
value of 0.7, so now I can't claim that
model 3
is any better than model 2 even though it
does account
for a little bit more of the variance in
the outcome variable.
but again, that's because
we don't have a sufficient sample size
with 20
to detect statistical significance and
reject the null hypothesis.
So again, that's, that's the importance of
sample size when doing NHST.
and that I believe, yep, wraps it up.
so this is all you'll need to do
assignment 5.
Again, it'll be on correlation and
regression.
But with an emphasis on model comparisons
and confidence intervals.
Good luck on that, and I'll talk to you
next week.