Hi, welcome back.
We're in lecture 11 and this is segment 3.
The topic of the lecture is multiple
regression.
In this last segment, we're going to look
at exactly
how the regression coefficients are
estimated using matrix algebra.
So again, if you're not familiar with
matrix algebra, go back
to segment two, it provides a little bit
of a refresher.
but assuming you've done that, or you're,
you're already comfortable with
matrix algebra, let's go ahead and
see how these regression coefficients are
estimated.
so again, just like regular simple
regression, the values of
these coefficients are estimated such that
the model yields optimal predictions.
And again, how do we do that?
Well, we just minimize the residuals.
So, remember the residuals are just the
difference between the actual score on
Y or the observed score on Y, and the
predicted score on Y.
We get the sums of squares residual by
taking all of those deviations and
squaring them.
So sum of squared residuals gives us sum
of squares.
We want to minimize that value, that's
ordinary least squares estimation.
So, how do we do that when we have
multiple predictors in
the model, we have to solve for multiple
regression coefficients at once?
Well we do that through matrix algebra.
So, to make this a little simpler, I,
I'm going to just do this in standardized
form.
So what that means is we can take out the
regression constant.
Assume the regression constant is zero.
So the predicted score on
Y when all Xs are zero is zero.
So we can just drop that
out of the equation.
So we dropped that out of the equation,
then the regression equation for the
predicted score is just B times X.
And now think of everything as a matrix.
Okay?
There's a little bit of a, a change in
perspective if you're not
used to matrix algebra, so just, wrap your
head around that if this
is new to you.
Everything is a matrix.
So, the predicted scores are a matrix.
They're are just they're actually just a
vector, because
we just get one predicted score on each
individual.
but it's an N by 1 vector.
That is, there are N rows for your number
of people and there's
just one column, because we're only
getting one predicted score in multiple
regression.
The betas or the, the regression
coefficients, is a k by one vector and k
is just the number of predictors.
And then X is going to be an N by k
matrix with n number of rows times k
number of predictors.
So, here is the formula.
What we want to do is solve for B.
So, that's not that hard, just we have to
apply some basic algebra.
Right?
So, to solve for B, what I did first was,
was, I'm going to replace the predicted
scores with the observed scores, because
we don't know the predicted scores.
Right?
And then I'm going to conform X and
B to make them conformable for matrix
multiplication.
So, what I wind up with is this formula, Y
equals X times B.
So, I have Y equals X times B, but I still
need to solve for B.
So how am I going to do that?
Well, let's make X square and symmetric.
And to do that, I'm going to pre-multiply
both sides
of the equation by the transpose of X, X
superscript T.
If I pre-multiply X by its transpose,
that's going to make it
square and symmetric.
And remember, anything I do to one side of
the equation, I have to do to the other
side.
So, now, if I multiply each side of the
equation
by the transpose of X, I get this formula
here.
Now, to solve for B, what I want to do is
get
rid of everything that's on the right hand
side of the equation.
So I want to get rid of X transpose X.
To get rid of something in basic algebra,
you would just divide by that.
Alright.
So I would divide by X transpose X.
We can't do that in Matrix algebra.
What we do is we take the inverse and
pre-multiply by the inverse.
So the inverse of a matrix times itself
is an identity matrix, which is
essentially like 1.
So, it's the, it's the, it's the same
as like dividing by and eliminating that,
that term.
So, if we do that, we multiply each side
of the equation by
X transpose X to the negative 1.
That's the inverse of X transpose X.
So, I do that on the right side, do that
on the left side.
as I said,
X transpose X pre-multiplied by it's own
inverse gives us what's called the
identity matrix.
The identity matrix times another matrix
gives you just that matrix.
So I times B equals B.
So we've succeeded in eliminating
everything from the right hand side of
the equation, except for what we're
solving for, that is the regression
coefficients.
So now, I have a formula I can work with.
So here's our solution, we can now
solve for B with just X transpose X, the
inverse of that, times X transpose Y.
We know the X values, we know the Y
values.
Right?
Those are our variables.
So that's the formula that we were
going to use, that's what R uses
to calculate these regression
coefficients.
So let's use that formula to calculate the
regression coefficients from
the same data that we used to illustrate
matrix algebra.
So here was the the raw data matrix.
And what I'm doing is I'm going to
consider this first column Y and then the
next one X1, and the next one X2.
Because we need one of the variables to be
the outcome measure.
So again, I'm going to get the row vector
of sums, we did this in the last segment.
The row vector of means, did that before.
Matrix of means, matrix of deviation
scores, and finally
this sums of squares and sum of cross
product matrix.
Now, since I have deviation scores, I can
substitute that S sub xx
for X transpose X, and S sub xy for X
transpose Y.
So now, the regression equation, I can
just
write in terms of those S mat, matrices.
Then when I do that calculation, I get
my regression coefficients, and here are
the regression coefficients.
They're are two of them because I had two
X's and one Y.
One of them is negative 0.19, the other is
negative 0.01.
To check myself.
And if you want to check yourself, if you
didn't trust that, I went a little faster
at
the end.
you could plug that row data into R.
Right?
And then just run an LM with the first
column as
the outcome, and then next two columns as
the two predictors.
Run the LM and you will see I, I run
exactly that.
I did LM where the formula was demo, this
is a, just a demo of, of matrix algebra.
So I did
demo Y as a function of demo X1 and X2.
And you'll see,
we've got exactly what we did when we
calculated it by hand.
So I got a negative 0.188.
So I got, I got 0.19.
I've, I did a little rounding here when I
did it by hand.
And a negative 0.008.
I got negative 0.01, again a little
rounding error just by hand.
So, I just ran it in R to make sure I did
it right as I did it by hand.
But there you see, if you wanted to
[LAUGH],
you could do multiple regression by hand.
Of course, we're not going to do that,
because it's so simple just writing in LMY
till the X1 plus X2 plus X3.
Right?
So you'll just do that in R.
But now at least, once in your life
[LAUGH],
you've gone through and you've seen how to
do it
by hand if you had to do it that way.