Hi, welcome back to Statistics One.
We're up to lecture nine, and the topic in
lecture nine is the central limit theorem.
In the last segment, I started to talk
about inferential statistics.
And the idea of null hypothesis
significance testing.
And even two lectures ago, when we were
talking about regression, I pointed
out in the R output some t values and p
values and this idea of,
of certain p values being statistically
significant, well, I didn't
really give you a detailed description of
where those p values come from
and how we determine if a certain p value
is statiscally significant or not.
The nitty gritty and the details for all
of
that come from this idea of the central
limit theorem.
So in this lecture we'll get to the bottom
of where do those p
values actually come from.
And to understand the central limit
theorem I first
have to introduce this idea of a sampling
distribution.
So there will be two segments.
First we'll talk about sampling
distributions.
And then I'll go into the formal statement
of the central limit theorem, which again
provides the foundation of where these p
values come from in null hypothesis
significance testing.
So first.
What are sampling distributions?
This is notoriously a difficult lecture in
intro stats.
So, I've been teaching intro stats for 16
years,
and almost every semester, this is the
stumbling block.
So, please pay attention to this lecture
closely.
Maybe watch it a couple of times.
it's a, it's a little bit of a difficult
concept to wrap your head around.
So I'm going to sort of ease you through
it slowly.
And the way I'm going to do this is to go
back to a review of simple histograms.
So remember, way back in the second week,
we talked about histograms.
And they're used to display distributions.
And one that I relied upon
a lot was a histogram to display
distribution of individuals and their body
temperatures.
So, if we converted every thing to
z-scores it looked like this.
Again I'm, I'm assuming I have a random
sample of healthy individuals,
and I measured their body temperature, and
then converted it to z-scores
so that the mean body temperature is zero.
If you prefer,
I could plot it in degrees fahrenheit so
the mean is about 98.6 or if
you prefer again, we could look at it in
celcius.
Okay?
We did this to look at a distribution of
individuals and their body temperature.
This is natural variation.
Some people
are a little above average.
Some are a little below average.
But, this is a healthy sample.
So no one's really, really high, running a
really high fever.
If a distribution is perfectly normal.
Those weren't perfectly normal, there's
always some sampling error, right.
But if it's perfectly normal, then we know
the properties of the distribution.
So here is a perfectly normal
distribution, and again standardized.
So the mean is zero, one standard
deviation falls
about here, and two standard deviations is
out here.
And two standard deviations below the mean
down here.
So a couple things to notice about
this perfectly normal distribution, one,
it's symmetrical,
right, so 50% of the distribution falls
above the mean, 50% falls below the mean.
The other thing to notice is the majority
of
the distribution falls within two standard
deviations of the mean.
So if you are two standard deviations
above the mean, so up here
or two standard deviations below the mean.
Down here, you're, you're a pretty
extreme score in a normal distribution.
We can use that information to make
probability judgments.
So, the normal distribution combined with
the idea of probability.
Allows us to make predictions about the
distribution.
Now, keep in mind that predictions aren't
certain.
They're probabilistic.
Again, just like the MHST, logical
reasoning is probabilistic.
We're getting engaged in some
probabilistic predictions.
So we're going to get p values.
Associated with certain questions.
So for example, just talking about a
histogram, looking
at a distribution of individuals, I could
ask, if one person was randomly
selected from the sample, what's the
probability that his
or her body temperature is less than a z
equal to 0?
Or, less than 98.6 or less then 37
Celsius.
That's real easy, z of zero was the
mean, so what's the probability of that
happening?
Well its 0.5, half of the distribution is
below a z
of zero, so the probability of that
happening is a 0.5.
Let's make it more interesting.
If one person is randomly selected from
the sample what's
the probability that his or her body
temperature is greater than z equals 2.
I just showed you that a very
small percentage of the distribution falls
beyond two.
Alright?
So, this is going to be a very unlikely
outcome.
And, it turns out the probability is
about.
02 .
So this is a very unlikely event.
It might make
me want to rethink my assumption that
everybody in this sample is healthy.
Do you see now the connection to NHST?
I made an assumption.
I looked and calculated the probability of
an outcome.
I got a really low probability that might
make me rethink the initial assumption.
That's what we are going to do but at the
level of samples.
So, here I can wide i out, out just like I
did when we are talking about NHST.
If the sample is healthy then no one
should have a fever that is run a really
high temperature, but I detected a person
with
a fever, therefore this sample is not 100%
healthy.
That's exactly the logic we engage in when
we do NHST.
But we do it with sampling distributions.
Not distributions of individuals,
distributions of sample statistics.
So, to be clear, a sampling distribution,
is
a distribution of sample statistics
obtained from multiple samples.
So we could do this for any sample static,
we could
get a distribution of sample means, we
could get a distribution
of sample correlations, we could get a
distribution of regression coefficients.
The trick about this concept and why
students stumble here
is because we don't actually do this,
right, when I do
and experiment or I study I just get one
sample and
I go from there, so, this sampling
distribution, is a hypothetical.
I don't have actually a sampling
distribution, I estimate it.
So, it's hypothetical.
So, let's assume that I get a mean
calculated from a sample, and that sample
is obtained randomly from the population.
And let's assume a certain sample size, N.
Now again, assume I do that over and over
and over and over and over
again I get multiple samples, again we
don't
do this in practice, we do one sample,
we calculate our statistics, we try to
make inferences about the population.
But for the sake of this, this segment and
understanding the
idea of sampling distribution, imagine we,
imagine that we do that.
If I get multiple samples, then I would
have multiple sample means
and they would all differ a little bit
because of sampling error.
Alright?
So, I would have a distribution of sample
means and
those collectively would be a sampling
distribution.
I give you that with any sample statistic.
Then, I could take a sampling
distribution, marry it with
probability and now you see how we're
moving towards NHST.
So I can say, if one sample is obtained
from a normal healthy
population, what's the probability that
the sample mean is less than z equals 0?
Well, again, that's easy.
z equals 0 is the mean, so it's just p
equals 0.5.
Let's go to the most extreme example.
If one sample is obtained from a normal,
healthy population, what's
the probability that the sample mean is
greater than z equals two.
That would be really unlikely.
Again the p value be about 0.02.
In other words, the p value is
less than 0.05, that magic cut off, right.
Which means I
would rethink my assumption that this
population is healthy.
I might want to reject that assumption.
That's exactly what we're doing with NHST.
So to be clear, in NHST we say if this
population is healthy, that's
an assumption, then no one sample should
have a high mean body temperature, I've
obtained
a very high sample mean, therefore I'm
going to
reject that initial assumption that the
population is healthy.
Now I've glossed over again a little bit
of
the detail and what exactly is very high
and
very low and what exactly are the cutoffs
where exactly do we get the p values from?
In the next segment, we'll walk through
the
logic of the central limit theorem, and
look at
multiple sampling distributions to see
exactly where those
p values come from, in particular in the
context
of regression.
But for this segment, just understand what
a sampling distribution is.
It's a distribution of sample statistics
obtained from multiple samples
assuming that they all have an equal
sample size n.
And again remember that this is a
hypothetical idea this
sampling distribution but we need it to
engage in null
hypothesis significance testing and to
obtain p
values and make probability judgments
about samples.
And again we can get sampling
distributions for any sample statistic,
the mean,
the correlations, or regression
coefficients and lots
of others going forward in the course.