Hi welcome back, we are in lecture 11
and the topic in the lecture is Multiple
Regression.
In the first segment I did an overview, we
talked
about how to interpret coefficients in a
multiple regression equation.
Now we are going to talk about how those
coefficients are escalated and
to understand that you need to know a
little bit about matrix algebra.
So I'm throwing in this segment for those
of you who have no exposure
to Matrix algebra or if you feel like you
need a little brush up.
If you're really comfortable with matrix
algebra, then you might want to
go ahead and skip this segment and go on
to segment three.
So this is a very skimpy but basic
introduction to matrix algebra.
We are just going to do
some simple things, addition, subtraction,
multiplication
and I will point out some very special
types of matrices
along the way that hopefully you will
recognize and you will see the connection
between matrix algebra and statistics
particularly multiple regression.
So first to start out, What's a matrix?
so a matrix is just a rectangular
table, of known or unknown numbers.
so.
it has a number of rows, a number of
columns the order
of the matrix is always number of rows
first then number of columns.
So this matrix that I am showing you here
M is a 4 by 2 matrix 4 rows, 2 columns.
But again to, to reinforce that its rows
then columns, I always tell my students
here at Princeton the way to remember that
is matrix algebra is really cool, rows,
columns.
It's really cool.
So, rows, columns.
It's a 4 by 2.
So one common manipulation of a matrix in
matrix algebra and particularly
when you're doing calculations for
multiple
regression, is to take the transpose
of the matrix.
And to transpose a matrix, you just change
the rows and columns.
So here, to take the transpose of M, M sub
superscript T, all I
did was just flip the matrix so that the
rows are now the columns.
So now, instead of having a 4 by 2, I have
a 2 by 4.
Addition and subtraction in matrix algebra
is really simple, and it doesn't
take really much, knowing much more than
just basic addition and subtraction.
The only thing to know is that, the only
way you can add or
subtract 2 matrices is they have to be the
same size with the same order.
So if I want to add say matrix M and N
they both need to be
the same size, they both are 4 by 2 here
and then
to add them I just take each corresponding
element and add them.
So I go to row 1, column 1 In matrix M,
row 1 column 1, in matrix N,
add those and I get my result and I just
do that for each cell and each matrix.
That's real simple.
Matrix multiplication is a little bit
trickier but again not too difficult.
the one thing to know and remember as
we're going through these calculations is
that 2 matrices can only be multiplied if
they're what's called conformable.
And what that means is the number of
columns
in the first matrix, must be equal to the
number of rows in the second matrix.
That's what it means for 2 matrices to be
conformable.
This is the technical way it's written out
for mat, matrix, matrix
multiplication, what we're going to do is
take the transpose of matrix
M and multiply it by matrix N.
Remember I, I, I cu, can't multiply
M and N, because they're the same order.
They're both 4 by 2.
So it I take the transpose of M, then I
have a 2 by 4 multiplied by a 4 by 2.
then that works.
So it's
[UNKNOWN].
So let's see how this works.
So I took the transpose of M, so M was a 4
by 2.
Now it's a 2 by 4 and I'm going to
multiply it by N.
So I have a 2 by 4 matrix multiplied by a
4 by 2, 4 by 2.
So this is, 2 by 4, and I'm going to
multiply
that by a 4 by 2.
What that will give
me is a 2 by 2 product matrix.
It's a 2 by 2 so number of rows in the
first matrix and the number of columns in
the second matrix.
That's an easy way to start learning how
to do matrix multiplication is think
about what's the product going to look
like.
So if I'm multiplying a 2 by 4 times a 4
by
2 then I know I'm going to wind up with a
product matrix.
That's a 2 by 2 and this is the product
out here.
So the way I'd like this when I first
started leaning how to do this
way back in grad school is think about the
product matrix and how will I get
row 1, column 1 of this matrix.
Well to get,
the way to get row 1, column 1 is to go
across row
1 of the first matrix and down column 1 of
the second matrix.
So what I am going to do is take the first
element in row 1, that's the number 1
times the first element of column 1 in the
second matrix, that's the number 2.
So its 1 times 2, and then I am going to
add
the second element in the first row of the
first matrix
times the second element of the first
column in the second matrix.
So it's 5 times 4.
So what
I'm doing is 1 times 2, plus 5 times 4,
plus 3 times 1, plus 4 times 3.
So let's go through that again.
That's 1 times 2 is 2 plus 5 times 4 is 20
so
I'm at 22, plus 3 times 1 so now I'm at 25
plus 4 times 3 that's 12.
That gives me 37.
So how did I get row 1 column 1 of the
product matrix?
I went across row 1 of the first, first
matrix, down column 1 of the second
matrix, I multiplied each corresponding
element, and took the sum of the products.
And that got me 37.
We could do that for row 2, column 1 so
now I am in row 2,
column 1, so its 2 times 2
is 4 plus 1 times 4 is 4 that's 8 plus
4 times 1 is 12 plus 2 times 3, gives me
18.
Okay, that's how matrix multiplication
works.
Fortunately, R does this for us.
[LAUGH]
Right?
but, it's sort of essential to understand
how it works.
So you can see how the regression
coefficients are estimated when you are
doing multiple
regression, because that's what, this is
what R
is using as it estimates the regression
coefficients.
So in the next 10 slides to illustrate
addition, subtraction, multiplication.
I'm going to go from a raw data matrix.
You can think of this like a data frame.
An R to a correlation matrix.
Just in ten thoughts.
So here let's look at a raw data frame.
this is a matrix.
Again, if you think about a data frame
it's a matrix.
Right?
we talked about that in Lab one.
for, when we were first learning about how
to manipulate objects in R.
so we can think of this as having ten
rows.
That's like having ten subjects in a, in,
in a, study measured on
three variables.
And you can imagine these are numbers on
like a
Likert scale of like 1 to 5 or 1 to 7.
So we just have 10 people and 3 variables.
the first thing I want to do is sum up
those columns.
And again, think about how you would do
this just in regular algebra.
Forget matrix algebra.
how would we calculate the correlation
coefficient?
No, we did that way back in I think week 2
or 3.
How do we calculate correlation
coefficients?
Well we've got the sums of squares, the
sums of cross products.
Right it's the sum of cross products over
the sum of squares.
How do you get sum of squares?
Well the first thing you do is you get the
mean, then you
get the deviation scores, then you square
the deviation scores, you get some
squares.
So, that's exactly what we're going to do
here, it's just we're doing
it in matrix algebra, which sounds fancy,
but it's the same thing.
So the first step is sum all
the scores in a column.
Because I want to get means.
So I sum all the scores and that gets me
this
matrix, it's a 1 by 3 matrix, or it's just
a vector,
right.
I got those sums because then
I want to get means.
So if I multiply that matrix
of sums times 10 to the negative 1 that's
the same as saying
dividing by 10, but that's how we write
this in matrix algebra,
then I get the means.
So now I have a matrix of means or what I
call here a row vector of means.
Now I can get an entire matrix of means if
I just take a column vector of 1s.
That's this guy.
It's a column vector because it's just 1
vector.
I'm sorry, 1 column.
Multiply it by this row vector of means,
now I have a matrix of means.
Why do I want a matrix of means?
Well because,
I want to get a matrix of deviation
scores.
Remember how did we do this in basic
algebra?
We calculated deviation scores, and then
we squared deviation scores.
So now, if I just take my matrix, my, my
original data matrix
and subtract the matrix of, of means, then
my result is a matrix of deviation scores.
Now this is the really cool parts, the
most important piece.
If I take that matrix of deviation scores
and pre-multiply
it by its own transpose, then what do we
get?
We get a matrix of sum of squares and sum
of prospects.
Isn't that cool?
I think that's cool.
So down here, this matrix is the sum
of squares and the sum of cross products.
The sum of squares are in a diagonal,
and the sum of cross products are in the
off diagonal.
Why is that?
Well, what's in the diagonal?
Let's go to row 1 column 1.
I would go across row 1, down column 1.
What I'm doing is taking each deviation
score, and multiplying it by itself.
That's the deviation score squared, and
then summing them all, right?
That's sum of squares, pretty cool huh?
How do I get some cross products well it's
just by doing x and y, same thing.
So, this is a really nice trick and a
fundamental pieces of statistics that
matrix algebra, there are some, some
special matrices that correspond to
really conceptually important pieces of,
of basic stats in multiple regression.
So now I think you see we're near the
finish line.
We have these sum of the squares and sums
of cross products.
So now if we just divide by N again I am
doing multiple, I am
doing matrix algebra and notations so we
will multiply times N to the negative 1.
then I get a variance, co variance matrix
and I can standardized that by multiplying
by the
standard deviation matrix.
And if I do that then I finish with the
correlation matrix.
So that last piece was just a standardized
things so that I get a diagonal of 1s.
Because each variable correlated with
itself is 1.
And then in the off-diagonals, again this
is a symmetrical matrix.
so the correlation between the first
column and second column is negative.19
and
between the first column and third column
is negative.09 and second, third column
is.44.
So that's the correlation matrix.
Again important things to take away this
is
really just purely a mathematical lesson
so that
we can move on to the next segment
and learn how to interpret the regression
coefficients.
know how to add, subtract, and multiply
matrices
and recognize that there's some sort of
special matrices.
In matrix algebra that correspond directly
to really important
concepts in, in basic stats, like the
correlation matrix,
sum of squares, sum of cross products and
variance/covariance matrix.