Hi, welcome back.
We're in Lecture 1, Segment 2.
We're talking about experimental research.
In the first segment, we talked about the
polio
vaccine trials, a clear success story of
experimental research.
In this segment, we'll talk about more
recent research on memory training, and
the idea
that you can use memory training
techniques or
online brain games to enhance your memory
and
perhaps enhance your intelligence.
The jury is still out as to whether this
type
of experimental research is as successful
as the polio vaccine trials.
So I'll describe one experiment to you to
give you a flavor for how this works, and
we'll talk about why there's still some
controversy around this research.
So the idea behind Memory Training, and
you may have seen some of these things
online are referred to as brain games
that you can train your memory, train your
attention to enhance
your intelligence.
is, you, you
engage in days and days and days perhaps
weeks up to a month of
memory training and you do a, a test
before,
a test after training, that's called a
pre-post test
design to see if you can enhance your
intelligence.
And there are lots of websites, I'm not
going to give
them free advertising on here, but there
are lots of websites.
they typically fall under the title of
brain games that promote
this idea that you can enhance your
intelligence by doing Memory Training.
And again this is you can
do experimental research to answer this
question, so I'm using
the, the my sort of basic lingo from last
segment.
We could promote good stuff so if we know
why this happens, why we can enhance
memory and intelligence, perhaps we could
promote good
stuff by by doing this Memory Training
research.
So the way an experiment works to get at
Memory Training is,
of course, the population we're talking
about here, just all healthy adults.
That's what I want to focus on.
so there are some brain training games or
Memory Training games focused at children.
what I'm going to talk about today in
this,
in this lecture are just some experiments
designed for
healthy adults.
So our sample in the sample from the
experiment that
I'm going to talk about, is just a sample
of college students.
So it's not exactly a random
representative sample of all healthy
adults.
college students aren't they're not
random.
They're not completely representative.
but that's typically how research is done
because we
have, we can get our hands on them here
on a, on a college campus.
The way that these experiments are set
up is the independent variable is the
training
condition so whether you go through some
sort of memory training or whether you
don't.
And this is an interesting aspect of these
training experiments.
what I'm going to describe to you in this
first example is a No training
control group, where the control group
just did nothing.
So there's Memory Training versus nothing.
there's other ways to do this that are
sort of
stronger tests of this claim that Memory
Training enhances intelligence.
but for now, we'll just keep it simple.
The dependent variables is the gain on an
IQ test.
So, as I mentioned, subjects in these
experiments, they take
an IQ test before training and then they
take an IQ test after training.
And we can look at the difference to see
how much
does an individual subject's IQ increase
as a function of training.
So the dependent variable here is IQ gain.
The idea being that subjects in
the training condition, their IQ is going
to increase more
so than subjects who are assigned to the
No training condition,
okay?
So the procedure in this one experiment
that I'll describe to you is the treatment
group, the, the Memory Training group.
They engaged in memory training for half
an hour a day, everyday for weeks.
I think it was up to like four weeks, four
or five weeks.
And I'll show you the training procedure
on the next slide.
and as mentioned, they, they took an IQ
test,
a reliable, standard measure of IQ, before
and after training.
Now, here's what the memory training
paradigm looked like,
if you're not familiar with the idea of
working
memory or short-term memory, this may look
a little
odd to you, so let me take some time
to explain it.
This task a 2-back task.
and very simply, what you're supposed to
do as the
student in this task or someone who's
engaging in this training paradigm,
as, you're going to see, stimulate popup
on the screen or you're going to hear
stimulate presented over headphones very
rapidly one at a time.
So you're going to see either locations,
squares,
excuse me, squares show up in different
locations
on a screen or you're going to hear
letters come, presented to you auditorally
over headphones.
And your job is just to press a button
when the
stimulus on the current slide, the one
that you see or
the one that you hear, matches the
stimulus end back in the stream.
And in this example, you're just doing a
2-back task, which is actually a pretty
easy task.
We could start with one-back, but that's
really, really simple.
so in a 2-back task, this one right here
is a visual
target because it's in the same location
as the stimulus 2-back in the stream.
Similarly in the auditory stream, this one
is an auditory target.
Because it matches the one 2-back in the
stream.
In this case, this is known as a dual end
back procedure.
The subject was supposed to press the
button only when the stimulus matched
in both the visual and auditory stream.
So again, this right here
is when the subject would press the
button,
saying yes, this stimulus matches the one
2-back up.
As I mentioned, subjects in a Memory
Training condition, they engaged in this
for this training procedure for half an
hour a day, everyday up to 19,
you can see 19 sessions down here in the
x-axis.
So what I'm plotting here on this graph
was on the x-axis
is session number so how many training
sessions
that they engaged in.
And what I'm plotting on the y-axis is the
min end back score.
So as you can see, people started out down
here around 3-back and as they engage
in training over 19 sessions, 19 days of
doing this for half an hour a day,
they got better and better and better up
to about 5-back.
Some people probably got as high as six
back, okay?
So, if you've done this task before, if
you have any familiarity with some of
these
brain game websites, 2-back is really
easy, 3-back
is sort of challenging, 4-back is really
challenging.
So the fact that these people got up to
5-back is pretty impressive.
So they're clearly training something.
The jury is still out as to exactly what
they're training.
so some people argue they're training a
core memory capacity that's related to
intelligence.
other people would argue that m, they're
training they're
just getting faster at doing tasks online
or something else.
but these are some of the basic results
from this study.
The bigger question is whether there was
transfer to intelligence.
So people clearly get better at the task
that they're training in as they do the
training procedure every day.
the bigger question is whether those
people in the training condition got
better
on the intelligence test relative to a
control group that didn't do the training.
And here are the results from a study by
Jaeggi et al, the reference is here.
if you want to look it up, it's Jaeggi et
al, 2008.
Here is the
primary result from that study that caused
a lot of buzz and, and generated a lot
of attention in this area of research is,
if you look before the training, so what
I'm plotting here
on the x-axis is pre and post, so this is
just
time.
So, before training there's
no difference between the experimental
group and the
control group, that is between the Memory
Training
group and the true, the placebo group, if
you will, the group that did no training.
There's no difference in their
intelligence scores.
So what I'm, what I'm plotting here is
their score on an intelligence test.
But what you see after training, so, post
training, the group
that did the Memory Training procedure,
they gained more on the
IQ tests than did the group that didn't do
the training, the control group.
The control group went up a little.
That's probably just a practice effect.
They took this intelligence test before.
This is their second time taking it so
there's a little bit of a practice effect.
But the bigger point is this difference
here.
The group that did the training gained
more
than the group that didn't do the
training.
So the conclusion from this experiment
then is engaging in this
memory training procedure, doing this end
back task for a half
an hour every day for 19 sessions, not
only enhances your
ability to do that end back task or
enhances your memory capacity.
But it also, according to these
authors, enhances your basic intelligence,
your general intelligence.
And that, of course, created a lot of
excitement in
the field of Psychology and Education
because the conventional wisdom
in those fields is that intelligence and
sort of a
memory capacity are sort of fixed once you
get to adulthood.
It's, they're very hard, it's very hard to
change your level IQ.
This result right here called all that
into question.
Now, as I said, the jury is still out on a
lot of these works so it's said here, it
doesn't really work.
there are lots of people who are
[UNKNOWN]
that does not work and this is, this is a
fluke result.
Jaeggi et al have follow, followed up on
this research and argued no, that this,
this
result is real and that you can engage
in this memory training task to enhance
intelligence.
my perspective on this, I do research in
this area, I
study working memory and intelligence is,
I would argue so far,
there's not enough evidence to suggest
that these things really work.
So if I were you, I would not go out to
these websites and spend any money on
these thing, not just yet.
I think we need more experimental research
to get at
to see if the, if these results are, are
really strong and if we can replicate
them with different kinds of Memory
Training paradigms and most
importantly, with better control groups.
So in this example, the control group did
nothing.
So that's a really poor control group.
So when you do experimental research, you
really want
the difference between the experimental
group and the control group
to be as small as possible so that you
can make that causal claim about why the
outcome happened.
You can link, you can
link it to the, that small difference
between the experimental group and the
control group.
Here there are so many things that were
different between the experimental group
and the control group.
The experimental group came to this lab
everyday for 19 days.
They got better on a task that they were
doing on a computer everyday.
So it was rewarding, they felt better
about themselves.
They had maybe just a more
positive feeling about this lab, about
cognitive tasks in general.
So when they came back for the post test
on the
IQ they could've just done better because
they felt better about themselves.
they could have felt better in that
environment.
there's all sorts of reasons why this
result could have happened.
that has nothing to do with memory
training per se, or IQ per se.
and if you're interested in this line of
research
again, Google, you can just Google working
memory training.
there's lots and lots of studies now, on
that, on that topic.
And I would argue that the evidence isn't
strong enough to claim that this really
works.
clearly, it doesn't work like the polio
vaccine work, all right?
So this is an example of experimental
research, that's not quite as good as, as
those polio vaccine studies.
If this is sort of not not sort
of high quality experimental research,
lots of potential confounds.
Okay.
So to, to summarize, this is the same
summary from Segment 1.
The major benefit of randomized controlled
experiments is that they allow for strong
claims about causality.
They allow us to get at mechanism, why
things happen.
again, we can predict stuff that allows us
to prevent bad stuff
like polio and potentially allows us to
promote good stuff like intelligence.
If we could use working memory training to
enhance intelligence, then great, that's a
great idea.
I think everybody's behind that idea but
not everybody believes that it
really works so far.
And I'm, I'm still pretty skeptical myself
And again, that's because
we need really good independent variables,
random and representative samples.
Again, that was another problem with that
study, it wasn't
truly a random representative sample of
all young adults, right?
There was college students.
and we need no confounds and there are
lots of potential
confounds I, I encourage you to post on
the discussion forums, your
own ideas of the potential confounds in,
in, in this line of research.
there's lots and lots of confounds that I
didn't mentioned here
but you could mention in the discussion
forums if you like.
so this is an example where it's true
experimental research.
It's true
that those subjects came to the lab.
They were randomly assigned to do either
training or no training.
And they were assessed on some dependent
measure.
So it's a nice example of a randomized
controlled experiment.
But it's, it's an ex, example of an
experiment that's not, that doesn't allow
for strong cause of claims yet because of
all these potential confounds,
unlike the polio vaccine example.