Hi, welcome back to Statistics One.
We're up to Lecture 10, and the topic in
Lecture 10 is confidence intervals.
Last week we talked a lot about null
hypothesis significance testing.
And we talked about some of the problems
inherent in NHST.
And a lot of the criticisms of the entire
approach of NHST.
So in this lecture, we'll talk about an
entirely different approach
which is just to report confidence
intervals around sample
statistics, rather than engage in
inferential statistics per se.
Let me explain what I mean.
So in this lecture I'll divide the, the
topic
of confidence intervals for now into just
two segments.
In the first segment I'll talk about
confidence intervals around sample means,
and then
hopefully reinforce the idea of confidence
intervals
by talking about confidence intervals
around regression coefficients.
Since we've spent a good bit of time
on regression and, and again in the next
lecture
we be talking about multiple regression so
this
should be fresh in your minds at this
point.
So lets launch into the first segment.
Here we'll just talk about Confidence
intervals around sample means.
This is sort of the easiest and most
obvious place to start when talking about
confidence intervals.
Now, what do I mean by a confidence
interval?
Well, remember that all sample statistics
be
it a mean, a correlation, a regression
coefficient.
Whatever sample statistic we take are
simply what statisticians would call point
estimates.
That is, they're just one point in an
entire possible
sampling distribution.
Remember the whole idea of sampling error,
and sampling
distributions and the concept of the
central limit theorem.
What that implies is any one sample will
never be
perfect if we're only getting a random
sample from a population.
So the statistical phrase for that is we
can only get a point estimate from a
sample.
So if we think about sampling
distributions,
remember this was the family of tea
distributions.
These are all sampling distributions.
They vary slightly, remember, due to
sample size.
So these degrees of freedom, that's just n
minus one in the simplest case.
You can think of that as sample size.
But each of these are sampling
distributions.
And when we get a sample mean From a
distribution we just fall somewhere in
that sampling distribution.
We're one point in that sampling
distribution.
That's the point of a sample mean or any
sample statistic.
It's just one point in this entire
possible Range of values this entire
distribution.
So, the logic of confidence intervals,
which statisticians really approve of.
They, it's, a statistician would always
recommend, always report your confidence
intervals.
Those of us who are more applied, we tend
not to do it and you will see one of the
reasons why is they are so wide.
One author called it embarrassingly large.
[LAUGH]
The point estimates just seem more
accurate because of an illusion.
Again, the logic of the confidence
intervals is to report
a range of values, rather than just a
single value.
So there are, rather than just report the
sample
mean, report a range, a possible range of
value.
And we'll call that an interval estimate,
rather than a point estimate.
So, to be clear, a confidence interval is
an interval
estimate of a population parameter based
on one random sample.
The degree of confidence, how confident we
want to be in this interval.
For example, 95%, that's one of
the most common confidence intervals
that's reported.
When we do this in lab and we do this in
the R software,
that's the default confidence interval is
95%.
that represents the probability that the
interval will capture the true population
parameter.
Okay, so this is the formal definition of
confidence interval.
And again, the main argument for interval
estimates is the reality of sampling
error.
We know that we have sampling error, so
let's just be upfront about that.
We, when we, if we're just reporting a
point estimate than we could be fooling
ourselves.
Worse yet we could be fooling our
audience, our readers.
So why not report the interval and just
acknowledge the fact
that we have sampling error?
Sampling error, remember, implies that
every point estimate, any one
point estimate, is going to be off by some
degree.
How much is it going to be off?
Well, that Has to do with how much
sampling error we can expect.
And that, we estimate, remember was
standard error.
So, the bottom line here, this is where
the phrase confidence
interval comes from, is researchers will
be more confident, or
should be more confident in the accuracy
of what they're reporting.
If they report an interval estimate rather
than a point estimate.
So let's get back to the specific topic of
confidence intervals for a sample mean.
And again I'm going to use the example of
the impact data.
We've used these a few times so I thought
I'd use this again to, to illustrate
confidence intervals.
let's assume we took just random samples
of only 30 athletes from those impact
data.
Remember, we had more than that, but let's
assume
that we just took random samples of 30,
and we repeated
that random sampling process and we would
get a sampling distribution, right?
We don't actually do that, we just get one
sample.
but let's assume we did it multiple times.
Here I'm just showing you actually I did
it to prepare this lecture I, I did it and
now I just randomly sampled samples of 30,
and I got the symptoms score at baseline.
Remember symptoms score at baseline should
be zero, because these are healthy
athletes.
Not everybody is at zero some athletes
come
in at baseline and then might reveal some
symptoms.
so the mean isn't exactly zero.
And if I get repeated random samples of
size 30 then the means
not going to be exactly the same each time
because of sampling error.
So, the first time I did it I got a mean
of 0.05 then I got 0.07 then I got 0.03.
So, it's close to zero.
There's not a lot of fluctuation beacuase
my sample size is not
bad considering there's not much variance
in this, in this variable at baseline.
Now let's decrease the sample size to ten,
and do it again.
So now I've decreased the sample size to
ten, I get symptom score at baseline.
Again the mean is going to be near zero
because these athletes are healthy,
but notice I got 0.01, I got a 0.2 in
there, and a 00.
So now there's more fluctuation in my
point estimates, in my sample means.
As I do that over and over again.
Now let's look at symptom score post
injury.
Now the mean isn't, shouldn't be zero
anymore because these athletes have been
concussed.
they're going to show a lot of symptoms.
So first let's do it again with N equals
30.
I got a few random samples.
I got a mean of 12 point 03.
Then I got a mean of 12 point 9.
Then I got a mean of 14 point 13.
So a little bit of fluctuation.
Again, that's just due to chance.
That's sampling error.
But let's decrease our N to 10 and do it
again.
Now these are athletes post injury, but
smaller sample, random samples of 10.
I got 19.7 and then only 8, and then 13.3.
And again,
you get more fluctuation.
with the lower N because there's more
sampling error when we have a smaller
sample size.
The other thing to notice is we get more
fluctuation in the post-injury scores than
in the base lines scores because there's
more variability post-injury.
Right?
So, the point of that little exercise is
the width
of a confidence interval is going to
depend on two things.
Sample
size.
So a sample size goes up my, the width of
the interval is
going to get tighter because I'm going to
be more confident about my estimate.
Right?
The other thing that will influence the
width is the variance in the population,
and
therefore the variance in the sample if
we're
getting a random representative sample
from the population.
So more variability in the sample means
more
very, very or wider width in that, in that
confidence interval.
All that is to say is standard error
is going to drive the width of the
confidence interval,
because remember standard error is the
standard deviation
of the sample over the square root of M.
Remember, that's where if we could jack up
N
and get really big samples, we get really
little
standard error.
Because standard error is how much
sampling error would I
expect just due to chance on average,
that's standard error.
So I ran this in r, and you'll be doing
this in lab, so with the sample size of
30, and using symptom score as my
variable, the 95% confidence
interval at baseline was negative 03 to
just.
1 .
So right around zero.
Notice it goes below zero which doesn't
make any sense,
that's not a possible score on the symptom
score.
But what it does is you will see the
calculation in a moment, it just
calculates the mean of the sample times
standard
error and time some function of standard
error.
So it might go below zero if the true
score is zero
but notice how type that is it's, it's not
a very wide interval.
I have 95% confidence that the true score
is somewhere in there, and it should be.
The true score should be zero or very
close to
zero, because these are healthy athletes,
they're taking this at baseline.
so it's right around zero, it's a very
tight interval.
If I go down to a sample size of 10,
again,
I just ran this in R to see what I would
get.
now I'm going a little bit even further
below zero, which is weird.
but now I"m up to 0.5.
Again it's, it's right around zero.
That's because there's not much
variability in this variable at baseline.
But you see how the width of the
confidence interval gets wider as sample
size goes down.
That's because we have more standard
error.
When sample size is lower.
Now this is more interesting.
Let's look at symptoms score after the
injury.
again let's start with sample size of 30.
Again I just random in R with a random
sample of 30 and
here is my 95% confidence interval It's
7.5 to 18.3.
So, that's a pretty wide range.
And I have a sample size
of 30.
it seemed much more accurate before,
right?
When we just reported the point estimate.
We just said, well, the average symptom
score is say, 12.
You know, then that would be, through like
a
walk away, alright, this is how serious
the injury is.
They have about a 12 on the symptom score.
But again, that's a point estimate just
from one sample and
there's some degree of sampling error
associated with any one individual sample.
So it would be more honest and more
accurate, and I could be more
confident in my reporting, if I reported
this interval estimate, rather than a
point estimate.
But, I would have to show just how wide
the interval is, and here it's 7.5 to
18.3.
It gets worse as sample size goes down of
course.
So, now let's look at it with an N of 10.
Now, let's look at the 95% confidence
interval, 2.7 to 23.9.
It's basically saying with an N of 10 I
don't know where you're going to fall on
this thing.
2.7 is closed to zero, that's close to
showing no symptoms at all,
and 23.9 is almost off the charts on this
scale.
so with a sample size of 10 if you
want 95% confidence that your capturing
the true population parameters.
you're going to have to report a really
wide interval.
And again this is why I think most
researchers
don't actually do 95% confidence
intervals, because as I
said, as one author called them,
embarrassingly large.
This is a good example of one that's
So how did R actually calculate those
confidence intervals?
Where it should be sort of intuitive to
you by now that what we
do is just take the sample mean, because
remember we only have one actual sample.
We take that sample mean and to get the
upper bound of the interval, we're
going to add standard error.
Because a standard go, standard error goes
up, we want to, we want to increase
the width of it.
but we want to multiply that by a t value,
which we get from the t distribution.
And then to get the lower bound, we do
the same thing, except we subtract t times
standard error.
Where standard error is still just
standard error, the standard
deviation of the sample over the square
root of M.
This T statistic it just depends on the
level of confidence desired so
for now lets stick with 95% confidence
levels and
that corresponds to a alpha of point 05,
that idea.
You need p less than.
05 to reject the null hypothesis, that's
why 95%
confidence intervals are sort of the
standard, because alpha of.
05 is also the standard.
So that t, the actual t value that gets
plugged into this formula,
depends on the level of confidence
desired, say 95%, and sample size.
Why sample size well, because again, the
sampling
distribution that we assume, depends on,
the exact
size of your sample, where the width of
the sampling distribution, gets a little
bit wider.
With smaller samples, right?
Smaller samples are going to give me more
standard error, so if I want 95% of that
distribution,
then I'm going to have to go little bit
further out.
I'm going to need a slightly higher T
value.
So that's why it depends on both standard
error and the T value.
So to wrap up this segment, remember that
all sample statistics, and this is a
critical
thing to remember as a consumer of
statistics,
that any one sample is just a point
estimate.
And now that we know about this idea of
sampling error, we know that
there exists out there in the world
this, this hypothetical idea of a sampling
distribution.
So you should know
that any one sample is just a point
estimate in that possible
sampling distribution.
so this any one sample mean
is just represents one point, and a larger
distribution.
So the logic of confidence intervals is to
report a range of
values, rather than just a single value,
and in statistics that's called reporting
an interval estimate rather than a point
estimate.
And, perhaps most importantly, just know
that the
width of the confidence interval, what
influences that?
Well, standard error.
And what influences standard error?
Sample size and variance in the
population.
And that hopefully now conceptually rings
true to you.
But also mathematically should make sense
to you, because
we've dealt with this formula a few times
now.
So standard error is standard deviation
over the square root of N.
So as variance in the population goes up,
standard deviation in
my sample should go up if I'm getting a
good estimate.
So it's standard deviation goes up,
standard air goes up.
And as I've said repeatedly now if sample
size
goes up then the denominator of standard
air goes up,
standard air is going to go down.
Okay, so the width is going to depend on
those two elements, and put together just
standard error.