Hi, welcome back.
We're in Lecture 2, Segment 2.
The topic of this lecture is correlational
research, and the topic of
this segment is intelligence research,
which is my own area of expertise.
And the point of this segment is, again,
to talk about how correlational research,
is used.
To understand the structure of human
intelligence,
and to develop theories, about human
intelligence.
So what is intelligence?
Intelligence, is famously difficult to
define, so I took a pretty popular
definition, from the Wall Street Journal.
back in 1994, this was an agreed upon
definition,
by top researchers in the field at the
time.
And they defined intelligence, as a very
general
mental capability that, among other
things, involves the ability
to reason, plan, solve problems, think
abstractly, comprehend complex ideas.
Learn quickly, and learn from experience,
is not merely
book learning, a narrow academic skill, or
test taking smarts.
Rather, it reflects a broader, and
deeper capability, for comprehending our
surroundings.
It's catching on, it's making sense of
things, or figuring out what to do.
Now, what type of research supports that
idea, or supports even
the idea, that there is such a thing, as a
general intelligence?
Well over 100 years of research, that
mainly employs, correlational research
methods, supports that idea.
So basically, the idea that, if you score
well in 1 type of
subject in school, you're going to score
well on another type of subject, or
if you score well on 1 kind of mental
test,
you tend to score well, on another type of
mental test.
This has been observed, over and over
again, for over 100 years, in intelligence
research.
And so, as this slide indicates, we know
this
from examining lots, and lots of patterns
of correlations.
And, I'll refer to these types of
investigations
as studies, just like the personality
research.
is, they're mainly studies.
They're not experiments, and there's, it's
an
important distinction is these are just
studies
of behavior, and that nothing is
manipulated,
whereas in experimental research there's a
manipulation.
the polio vaccine trials There is a
A child received a vaccine, or
a placebo.
In the working memory training
experiments, there was a manipulation.
They either did the training, or they
didn't do the training.
These are just studies, of behavior.
We go out.
We measure lots of things, and look for
patterns of correlation.
There's no manipulations in these, in
these studies.
So important distinction, between study,
and experiment.
So here's an example, again, of a positive
correlation, and this is what we typically
see,
if we administer some sort of mental test,
or IQ tests to lots, and lots of people.
what tends to happen is, if we have 1 IQ
test here, on the x axis
people who do well on this test, they tend
to do well, on another
IQ test.
So, you see, all, each dot in this.
This is called, the scatter plot.
We'll get into this more, on the lecture
on correlation,
and in the lab, in the second lab, on
correlation regression.
people who do well, on 1 test tend to do
well, on another kind of test.
And this has been observed, for over 100,
100 years and lots, and lots, and
lots of studies, of Intelligence.
So that lead, to the first sort of idea,
or theory of intelligence, proposed by
Charles Spearman in 1904.
That there is some sort, of general
intelligence,
that must account for this positive
correlation across.
All sorts of test, or all cites, all sorts
of types of material
in school, so if we looked at kids' grades
in History,
in a Language class, in a Math class, in a
Science class, they all
tend to show that positive correlation.
So there must
be some factor, or some trait, among
individuals, or
among kids in school that causes this
variance, or causes these
correlations across all these different
kinds of tests.
And Spearman referred that, referred to
that as g, or general intelligence.
1, of Spearman's early critics, Therstone,
observed
that well some correlations, are stronger
than others.
Yes, all the correlations across the, the
children's school grades
are positive, but some of them, are
stronger than others.
So for example,
if I look at a correlation between Math,
and Science.
That correlation tends to be higher, than
say Math, and History.
Even though this is a positive
correlation,
the slope of this line's going up.
this line is going up.
It's a positive correlation.
The correlation between math, and science
scores
tends to be higher, than the correlation
between
math, and history scores.
So, Thurstone argued, that there are
different types, of intelligence.
So there's something like verbal ability,
and perhaps spatial, or mathematical
ability.
And those are separable, and so verbal
ability, is more important for history
class, and language class, and spatial
ability, or quantitative ability,
is more important in math class, and
science class.
And there's some support for that, theory
of intelligence.
The only problem with that approach, is
that there
still tends, to be a positive correlation
between these guys.
So even among verbal, and spacial ability,
there's still some positive correlation.
As you saw, in the scatter plot with math,
and history scores.
There's still positive.
So what that led people, to propose is
what's known, as a hierarchical model of
intelligence.
And this is, remains the most dominant
model,
of the structure of human intelligence, to
this day.
Is the idea that, there's still this
general
intelligence, or g factor, if you've heard
of that.
in, in the media there's
a general intelligence, and then there's
several of
these sort, of group factors as they're
known.
that predict performance, in lots of
different, either academic
classrooms, or in different kinds of
mental tests, different types of IQ tests.
So this is sort of, the dominant
prevailing theory of intelligence, and
it's supported
by years, and years, and years, and
studies, and
studies, and studies, that have examined
patterns on correlations.
So this hierarchical model, of
intelligence is supported, just like the
big 5 factor model of personality is
supported by correlational research.
and that's summarized here, in this slide.
There's a general ability, and then
there's several
more specific abilities, and you need both
of those
to fully account, for all the patterns of
correlations,
that we observe, in these types of
correlational studies.
And again it, this is, I just
want to use this an example, of
correlational research.
I don't want to get into a big debate
about
intelligence but if you do want to know
more about.
Intelligence research, feel free to look
at my own research, I do research on this.
or if you want to know more about that
hierarchical model I
just showed you, just Google, the Cattell
Horn Carroll theory of intelligence.
That's sort of the prominent theory, of
intelligence right now.
Again, why is it the prominent theory of
intelligence, because it's
supported by.
Years of correlational research, looking
at patterns of correlations
among lots of different test scores, no
experimental research per say.
We're not manipulating anything in those
studies.
We're just looking at the patterns of
correlations, across test scores, or task
scores.
And that's the end, of that segment.