Hi.
Welcome back.
We're in lecture two of Statistics One.
The topic of this lecture is correlational
research.
So in lecture one, we talked about
experimental research.
And I made the argument about how powerful
experimental research
is because it allows us to make strong
claims about causality.
Correlational research is the opposite.
In fact it gets sort of a, a, a bad rap
because the famous quote that everybody
knows about
correlational research is that correlation
does not imply causation.
Indeed, we can't make strong causal
arguments like
we can from experimental research with
correlational research.
That's not to say that core, correlational
research doesn't have its
place or isn't powerful, in fact it's very
powerful and, and we've
learned a lot.
from correlational research particularly
in the social sciences.
And those are the examples I'm going to
show you in this lecture.
So this lecture is broken down into three
segments.
The first segment I'll talk about
personality research and how
much we've learned in terms Of
correlational research in personality.
The second segment is on intelligence
research, and again we've learned
a lot about the structure of
human intelligence, based on correlational
research.
And, then I'll talk about correlational
research
that sort of looks like experimental
research.
And that's research that involves what I
call quasi-independent variables.
And I'll use a medical.
An example of medical research there, I'll
talk about sports related concussion.
So, but in this first segment let's talk
about personality research.
In personality research, in psychology
there's this famous quote
from Harvard psychologist Steven Pinker
who said, as any parent
of more than one child knows, children are
not
indistingui-, indistinguishable lumps of
raw material waiting to be shaped.
They are little people, born with little
personalities.
In other words he's arguing there's,
there's some thing that might be innate or
at least a very fine, a very hard grained
trait such
as personality trait.
So here's an example of a
baby who is clearly very extroverted very
fun
seeking clearly not shy, introverted
probably
not very neurotic, okay?
And these things can be measured from very
early on and how do we measure them, and
how do we test that idea of
Pinker's that there are different
personalities in different
kids and that they're relatively stable
over time.
Well, it's hard to do experimental
research on this.
We can do experimental research to try and
prime
people to be more introverted or to be
more extroverted.
but to look at people sort of stable
trait-like qualities over time, it's
easier just to do correlational research.
so first let me be clear about what I mean
about a personality traits.
Traits are considered to be relatively
stable, distinguishable qualities of
a person and stable over the course of a
life time.
In personality psychology the dominant
theory in
personality research is known as the Big
Five personality model.
So there's five different personality
traits that seem to
emerge as you look for correlations across
people.
So there's openness,
conscientiousness,extroversion,
agreeableness and neuroticism.
And a lot of people use this acronym,
OCEAN, to remember that.
So the big five theory and, or known as
the OCEAN theory of personality.
Now, how do we study this?
One of the most popular ways to study this
is just to administer surveys.
So, ask people questions.
Like, I am the life of the party.
Is that true for you?
Or is that not true for you?
Give you a scale from one to seven.
How much do you agree or disagree with
that statement.
So if you think back to that picture of
the
little kid, that little kid grown up now
would probably
be, yep I strongly agree.
I am typically the life of the party.
or the second question.
I don't mind being the center of
attention.
Looks like that kid didn't mind being the
center of attention, right?
and as a grown up, that kid
probably doesn't mind being the center of
attention.
This is what the personalities surveys
online typically look
like, so they're a series of questions
like that,
so this first one is, I am the life of the
party, and it, you're just asked to.
Strongly disagree or strongly agree, or
maybe you're somewhere
in between, maybe you're a little
ambivalent on that question.
And there are lots of different kinds of
questions.
I feel little concern for
others, that would be low on
conscientiousness
[LAUGH],
I'm always prepared, I tend to manipulate
others to get my way.
I don't like some of these people.
[LAUGH]
I get stressed out easily and so on.
Okay?
what we can do is take people's responses
to those
questions and then we can look for
correlations across.
Those questions.
So, if I take the question, I am the life
of
the party and I don't mind being the
center of attention.
Those two questions,
if I asked hundreds of people, people's
responses to those two questions should be
correlated.
Such that if I score high on one of them,
say.
This is, I am the life of the party.
And say I score high on that one.
then chances are you're going to
score high on this question that says, I
don't mind being the center of attention.
So, that would be.
This, people represented by that dot are
high on each question.
They score a five, I strongly agree that I
don't, that I I am the life of the
party, and I strongly agree that I don't
mind being the center of attention.
So that's why these dots here Along th,
this line
are larger than the dots that are off of
the line like,
this dot are harder to see, even this dot
because so
few people are low on one score and high
on the other.
So it's, it'd be very rare for example for
someone to score right here,
which is yes I'm very high on I'm the life
of the
party but no I don't like to be the center
of attention.
That doesn't make much sense.
So that's why those dots are much smaller.
Very few people land there.
If we do these types of surveys.
It's more common that they land along
this line which indicates a strong
positive correlation.
We'll get into correlations in more detail
next week.
And the, there's an entire lecture on
correlations.
But, the point of this slide is just to
show that there's
a strong positive correlation among those
types of questions in personality surveys.
And years and years of research, not just
on surveys, but using the
surveys correlated with observations of
behavior and
people's reports about others' behavior,
their friends,
their family members.
support this idea that there are stable
personality traits consistent with the big
five model.
Here is just the same slide with what's
known as the regression line thrown in.
Again, we'll get to the details of
that when we cover correlation regression
next week.
So, this theory of the five components of
personality is supported by
years and years of correlational research.
Primarily correlational research.
Not much experimental research has gone
into this, but lots of correlational
research.
So surveys like the on I just
demonstrated.
As I mentioned, interviews with friends
and family.
And just obersvations of people's
behavior.
these things tend to correlate, so people
who say I am the
life of the party, I don't mind being the
center of attention.
Then if you do an observational study, And
you just see how they behave in certain
environments.
They tend to be the more extroverted
types.
These things tend to be positively
correlated.
And we can observe that through
correlational research.
so that's the point of correlational
research.
And if you're interested in personality
research, you know, this course
is not going to be about psychology or
personality per se, but If
you're interested in learning more about
that, you can just Google the
Five Factor Model of Personality if you
want to learn more about that.