Hi, welcome back.
We're in segment three of lecture one on
experimental research.
This last, last segment is very short and
it's based on
the feedback we got last year in the
discussion forums, is
not everybody Fully understood what I
meant when I said random selection
from a population and random assignment to
conditions in an experiment.
So
I want to talk a little bit more about
this concept of random.
So As mentioned in the first two segments
of lecture one experimental
research critically depends upon random
selection and random assignment.
So what do we mean by those?
So random selection means that individuals
included
in a sample should be randomly selected.
From the population.
So, in the polio
vaccines trials, what that means is, we
should be randomly selecting
children from the entire United States if
all children in the United
States is the population that we want to
make our inferences about.
in the working memory training example, if
we're, if we want to
make inferences about all young healthy
adults, then we should
get a random sample from all young healthy
adults.
Of course, that didn't happen in the one
experiment I showed you.
that's the idea is we have a population,
and
if we want to make an inference about that
population,
if we want to generalize to that
population, then we
need to get a random sample from that
population.
That's random selection Once we get that
random
selection, then we want to do random
assignment to conditions.
The way I want to illustrate this is
through this color wheel.
Okay, so imagine we have this color wheel,
and I can spin this color wheel.
So, make my pen work.
We can spin it like on a game show.
I can spin it and it can,
it can randomly come up on any color.
So I, I can't predict which color it's
going to come up.
If it's truly random, and we spin this
wheel over and over and over again.
And we just.
Count out how many times I get yellow, how
many times I get green,
how many times I get blue, then we should
have what's called a uniform distribution.
In other words it should look
like this.
This would be a random distribution of
spins.
So what's plotted here is on the x-axis.
We have the different colors that were in
the color wheel.
And, on the y-axis, is frequency.
And this is a
histogram, which you're going to cover in
the first lab later this week.
And what happens
is, you don't get them to be perfectly
equal, but what you see is They're
all about the same height.
So on average you would get
it would fall on the yellow pie, piece of
the pie just as often as
it would fall on the red piece of the pie
if it were truly random.
What would a non random sample look like?
Well, it might look something like this.
Say the wheel was biased so that it was
sort of heavier on the yellow and
green portion of it, so that it would fall
there more often than not.
Then, we might get lots and lots of cases
where it falls.
On the green slice of the pie, or on the
yellow slice of the pie,
and very, very rarely might it fall on the
red or the purple slices.
Now if you were you know, running sort of,
an illegal
[LAUGH]
gambling shop, this is how you would set
it up, right?
So you would put the sort of high value
prizes on red and purple.
And put the low value prices on green and
yellow and then you would always win as
the house,
and that's actually how a lot of gambling
houses work
is they're, they're not random they're
sort of non-random to
favor the house the owners of the gambling
facility.
so don't gamble.
That's is the worst thing a statistician
can do.
so this is what a non random distribution
would look like.
So, that was random selection from the
population.
Experiments also depend on random
assignment to conditions.
So we want there to be a 50, 50 chance,
for example that a child gets, either the
vaccine or the placebo.
Or, for example, that a subject coming in
to
do memory training, we want there to be a
50, 50 chance that they get assigned to
either
the true memory training condition or a
control condition.
So.
There's random assignment to conditions.
And if we successfully assign subjects to
conditions
then we should get something that looks
like this.
And with respect to this color wheel
example
so group one and group two not only
should they have this sort of uniform
distribution
of colors but they should also look
similar.
So group one should have a similar
distribution to group two.
So this is an example of random assignment
to, two groups or two conditions in an
experiment.
So to
recap, experimental research requires and
critically depends on this
idea of randomness.
One, random selection from the population
so that our sample is, is randomly
selected, and two, random
assignment to conditions so that we have
similar types of samples.
Across the conditions in the experiment.
[BLANK_AUDIO]