Hi, welcome to Statistics One lab one.
As you can see
we're in the R console and we could type
functions into the R console
right at the command prompt.
So, I could ask R what is 1 plus 2?
And R will return the result, 3.
But you'll see the way these labs will
work, is we prefer to write our functions
and write our code in scripts.
So, I'm just going to walk you through a
script in every lab.
And that script will prepare you for each
week's assignment.
So let me open up the script that I
prepared for
this first lab, which will prepare you for
the first homework.
And the purpose of this first lab and the
goal of the first
homework is basically to just show you how
R works, its basic functions.
talk about objects R functions and what
packages are.
So let's start at the top here, I'm just
going to highlight the first
few rows of code and show you that you
know R, one way
to think of R at the beginning, especially
if you're new to this,
is it's like a fancy calculator so we can
just do basic mathematical operations.
So I'm just going to execute
this little bit of code.
And if I now go back to the console.
You'll see that R executed 3 plus 4,
giving the result of 7.
5 times 5, 25.
12 divided by 3 is 4.
And 5 to the fifth power is 3,125.
So we can do basic mathematical functions.
Okay?
Now we go back to the script.
A basic distinction
in R is between, what I call R objects and
R functions.
So let's look at some R objects.
The most basic object in R is a vector.
So, let's create a vector.
I'm just going to exe, again, I'm just
going to execute this little bit of code.
Go back to the console.
And now you see we created a vector called
v
using the c command which stands for
combine or concatenate.
We just combine these four numbers into a
vector and that's a numeric vector.
And now let's go back to the script and
now let's create a list.
A list is slightly different from a
vector.
a list can contain.
Elements of different classes.
So a vector has to have all of the same
class.
So that last one we created was a numeric
vector.
We could have created a character vector.
but now
I want to create a list of items, some
character strings, some integers.
So let's execute that.
[SOUND]
Now we create a list called l and you see
It has,
the word blue and then it has the integer
two and so on.
Now, we can also create matrices and we'll
be working with,
mainly, we'll be working with matrices, in
future assignments in future labs.
So it's important that you understand what
a matrix is and how to access.
elements in a matrix.
So let's create a matrix, call it M.
Now we have this matrix M, it's just the
integers one to six and
I gave it the dimensions, two rows and
three columns.
And you'll see my comment here, matrix
creation is column wise.
What that means is, R took the integers
one, two and
three, four it went down the columns
instead of across the rows.
That's what I mean by matrix creation is
column wise.
Okay, back to the script.
We could also create a matrix from a
vector
and then add the dimensionality using the
dim function.
So execute that.
Back to the Console.
You see that, we created another matrix,
M2, it's the same as M, and
we added dimensionality just by using the
dim function, and again, that c function.
As we go forward in the, in the
course, we're going to be using matrices a
lot, so let me show you one more
way of.
Creating a matrix here we're
going to create it by binding columns and
rows so we have
x is just a vector of one to six y vector
of five
to ten.
And then we can use the functions cbind
and rbind.
And then we have a two by six matrix.
Finally, you can always check the
attributes of a matrix by using.
A function called attributes.
[SOUND]
And the attributes for M, remember that
was back
up here that's just a two by three matrix.
And if you want to call a particular cell
in a matrix Then, you just use the open
brackets and then which row and which
column you would like to access.
So, M open bracket one comma two, will
give me the integer three.
Because in my M matrix it's the first row
second column is the number three.
Finally let's talk about data frames.
This is what we're going to be working on.
At the beginning I said, think of R as
a fancy calculator where you can do
mathematical operations.
So, you're used to doing, probably
mathematical operations
on simple variables like we did at the
beginning, but what we'll be doing in
statistics
is, we'll be doing statistical analyses on
data frames.
It's analagous
to doing mathematical operations on
variables.
So what is a data frame, well a data
frame.
Is a matrix but it's a matrix that can
store different
classes of objects and typically what I'll
do is I'll just provide
you with, a data frame or data set, on the
course
web site and you'll just read that data
set into R using.
The read.table function.
Which is right here.
but in this lab, we'll just create a data
frame, so you can see what it looks like.
So, we can create a data frame in R.
There's a function called data.frame.
So let's do that.
So we created a data frame using the
data.frame, function.
And I called it d.
And then I just printed it by typing d
at the command prompt, or actually it's in
the script.
and there's the data frame.
You can ask R how many rows are in your
data frame, how many columns, again,
you could check the attributes, again, you
could
call a particular cell in the data frame.
So let's do all of those in one step since
we didn't, did most of this with matrices.
[NOISE]
Okay, so we ask number of rows with the n
row function,
there are five, we ask number of columns
with the n columns function.
There are three.
We check the attributes, it gives us the
names of the variables, or column headers.
It gives us the row names, and it gives us
the class.
this is a data frame.
And then we called particular cells in the
data frame, again, the same way
we did when we were looking at matrices
because a data frame is just a fancy
matrix, and this is what we're going to
work with mostly in future labs.
We can also, whoops, don't want to move my
code.
we can also display up a data frame and
edit a data frame with the view and edit
functions.
I'm not actually not going to run those
because
I want to move down to the last piece
Also you can get help on a function just
by typing in question function name.
So anytime you want to ask R what does
this function do?
Like if you want to know what the Edit
function does, just type in?
Edit .
Finally, an important thing that you, that
we all need to do before
the next lab and the next assignment, is
you need to know how install
packages, because R consists of lots and
lots of packages.
And a package Just is a bunch of functions
that people have created.
And there are lots of them.
If you go the R home page you can see
there are lots and lots of packages.
One that we'll work with in the beginning
is called Psych.
So, install the Psych package.
By typing in the function install dot
packages and then putting psych
in parenthesis and in quotes.
Let's do that.
And, you'll see what R does is it asks you
to select a CRAN mirror.
CRAN just stands for comprehensive R
archive network.
And you just have to pick a location
that's close to you.
so I'm going to pick Maryland, there
actually isn't
a New Jersey one, I'm in New Jersey.
but Maryland's close, so, I'll pick that.
This may take a second.
Oh, it's there, so now, after you've
installed the site package, you have to
load the package and you just do that with
the library command, so just libraries.
Let's go back to the console, it doesn't
return anything so let me just make sure
that it's there.
To make sure, I can just type search and
at the R command, prompt and then look
through
my output from search and I should see.
That I have the site package, yep,
there it is.
Okay, so now I've installed the site
package, that has a bunch of
functions that we're going to use,
especially in the first couple of weeks.
Throughout the, the, this course, we'll
download
and install lots of packages but for now.
all we need is the site package and the
basic packages that come with
the initial install and download of R like
stats and graphics and so on.
So that's
it, that's all you'll need to complete the
first assignment.
So, I'm going to end this first lab and
I'm going to quit out of R.
And I can do that several ways.
I'm just going to go up to, the R, menu,
and quit R.
It will of-, it will ask you if you
want to save changes.
I actually made a couple changes to my
script.
So I'm going to
save that.
It will also ask you if you want to save
your workspace image.
This is everything that came up in the R
console.
Since I saved the script, I don't need to
save that and I rarely ever do.
So I'm not going to save that.
And that's the end of Lab One.
See you next week.