Hi, welcome back to statistics one.
We're up to lecture eleven and the topic
today is multiple regression.
So, this lecture is divided into three
segments, in the first segment
I'll just introduce you to some basic
concepts in multiple regression, we've
already covered simple regression on a,
and you saw a glimpse of
multiple regression but we will get into
it a little bit more
deeply in this first section.
In the second segment we'll sort of take a
detour basically just into pure math
and I will introduce you to matrix algebra
if you haven't done matrix algebra before,
and the reason I am doing that is To
understand how the regression coefficients
are estimated in a multiple regression you
sort of have to have at least a basic
understanding of ma, of matrix algebra to
see how these are estimated all at once.
So we'll do a little bit of matrix algebra
in the second segment, and then in the
third
segment we'll walk through how the
regression coefficients are estimated in
this larger regression equation that
includes multiple predictors.
So first, Segment one.
let's look at multiple
regression, just sort of an overview.
And again, the important things to take
away here
are, the, the components of the multiple
regression equation.
and sort of, most importantly for this
segment, how to interpret
regression coefficients when there are
multiple coefficients in the model.
And this is a difficult topic, that even
advanced
researchers sometimes mix up and make
mistakes on.
so I'm going to, take my time and, and
really try and reinforce how to interpret
these coefficients.
So again just to make this distinction
between simple
regression and multiple regression real
easy, so simple regression
just has one predictor in the model,
multiple regression
you can have as many predictors as you
want.
So, here is the multiple regression
equation.
You saw this when we first talked about
regression about a week ago.
I am just putting in more predictors.
We are going to estimate multiple betas.
So to be clear.
we're going to have a predicted value on
the outcome variable Y.
We still have a regression constant.
That's just the predicted score on Y when
all the Xs are zero.
we have a bunch of predictor variables now
which
means we're going to have a bunch of
unstandardized regression coefficients.
We still have residuals, so we're going to
get one
predicted score for each individual, and
each individual has one
observed score, so we just have one
residual per person.
And I'm using k here to denote just
the number of predictors in the multiple
regression equation.
We still can calculate a multiple
correlation coefficient, because remember
that's the correlation between the
predicted scores and the observed scores.
And this is a way of evaluating the
overall model.
And we
can square that multiple correlation
coefficient
to get R squared, and that tells
us the percentage of variance in the
outcome measure that's explained by the
model.
And again that's a way to evaluate the
overall model.
It's a way to compare competing models.
The example I'm going to use for multiple
regression.
Is one in which we predict faculty salary
from a series of predictors.
So, what are some things that might
predict a faculty member's salary?
Well, one obvious one, and it, it is is
the strongest predictor in this example,
is just time since the person's PhD.
So people who have been out of school
longer, been working longer, they tend to
make more money.
But another predictor is, how many
publications,
particularly peer review publication an
individual has.
So, if a faculty member is really prolific
and publishes a lot.
That means they tend to be very marketable
and their salary is probably much higher.
So we could expect probably
a positive correlation between number of
publications and salary and, possibly,
gender.
Unfortunately particularly in the past but
even
to this day, there's some slight gender
inequity.
you might see a difference between men and
women.
so we could look at that in this
regression equation.
So first I'm just going to show you some
summary statistics.
because when, you'll see when we interpret
coefficients.
you can sometimes lose sight of the actual
summary statistics because you will see
some discrepancies.
So first let's just, just look at some
summary statistics.
I'm borrowing this example from
a previous example which is now a little
outdated.
these are U.S. dollars.
so if you are in the U.S. and you are
envisioning a career
in academia don't worry it gets, it gets a
little better than this.
This is an older example.
so the average salary for professors
in this example was 64,000 with a standard
deviation of 17,000.
time since the PhD was about eight years.
So these are relatively young faculty
members.
It's funny when I used this example years
ago I,
I didn't think eight years out was young,
now I do.
eight years out is young.
with a standard deviation of, of about
five years.
And they have on average about 15
publications with the standard deviation
about 7.5.
also because gender is a nominal variable
remember we
haven't really dealt with this situation
yet in regression we can't just throw in a
nominal variable into regression equation
without giving it some code because R
when it, when it runs that LM function it
needs a numeric value.
So, we need to code
male and female somehow.
So I just coded male as zero, female as
one.
Those are just arbitrary you can do it the
other way it doesn't matter.
So if we ran this in R we would use the LM
function.
Same thing as regular regression we just
add in more predictors.
So I did LM, salary is the outcome
measure,
so it's salary tilde and then all your
predictors.
Time plus Pubs plus Gender.
Notice it's, see, see the GLM in there, we
covered the GLM it's right there.
It's Y is a function of these
predictors time, publications and gender.
I ran that in R and, and here's my output.
so I get 46,911 plus and those are the
slopes relating each individual predictor
to the outcome measure, salary.
But let's really think about what these
numbers mean and I'm
going to ask some questions to get you
think about this.
oops sorry before I do I did summarize all
those coefficients
in a table of coefficients so you'll see
this in your R-output,
actually you've seen this when you did
simple regression, but when you
do multiple regression in R you'll, it'll
look a lot like this.
you'll see first, the unstandardized
coefficients.
So that's, in the first column, those are
unstandardized coefficients.
So to be clear, like 46,911, that's the
predicted score on Y when all Xx
are zero and these are the individual
slopes for each predictor.
you have a standard error associated with
each
one of those, remember, cause each one of
those is just a point estimate.
Now that we've talked about confidence
intervals, T is just the un-standardized
regression coefficient over standard
error, I'm
using beta here to reflect the
standardized coefficient, and
I just put that in so you can compare
them.
And then you get a P value associated with
each one.
And then down here again at the bottom, is
just the overall regression equation.
Now let's get to those questions that I
talked about.
And I'm asking these just to get you to
think carefully about this
output, and, and this outcome, and what
these coefficients really mean.
So what is 46,911?
What is 502?
If you look back at the table, you could
ask who makes more money, men or women.
according to the model,
is that difference between men and women,
is it statistically significant, according
to this model?
What's the strongest predictor of salary
well let's, let's answer those.
So 46,911 was the regression constant.
What is that?
It's the predicted score on Y when all the
X's are zero.
So it's when someone has no time since
their PhD so they just graduated.
They have no publications, and what was
coded as zero, well I coded men as zero.
So 46,911.
If you think back to the summary
statistics, that's a really low salary.
Why is it so low?
Well, because it's the predicted salary
for someone who just graduated and
has no publications and is male.
because I coded male as zero.
Okay.
So that's how to interpret the regression
constant in this example.
What's 502?
Well, 502 was
the regression coefficient for
publications.
So, you might say, well, okay, that's,
that's for a one unit increase in
publications,
that's the predicted change in salary.
And that's almost right.
Because that's what we learned in simple
regression, right.
The regression coefficient is for a one
unit
increase in X, it's the predicted change
in Y.
It's the slope relating X to Y.
But, what you have to remember in a
multiple regression.
Is that there are other variables floating
around
in this model.
So, it's the slope relating publications
to salary, yes.
But it's the slope at the average level of
time since PHD and averaging across men
and women.
So it's taking into account those other
variables in
your model which can get tricky and fool
you if
you're not careful in interpreting a
regression coefficient.
So example, who makes more money, men or
women?
Well if you look at the P value it's not
significant.
And it's negative.
So, if you go back and look at the table
of coefficients, it was at negative 3000
something, I coded men
as zero, women as one.
So, a one unit in increase in
X means we are going from male to female.
And the predicted change is negative.
What that means is, who makes more money,
men or women?
Well, women and, I'm sorry, who makes
more?
Men.
but, there are other variables floating
around in the model.
Right, it's, that's the difference between
men and women for an average
number of years since the PhD, and an
average number of publications.
So who makes more money, men or women?
I don't know, actually.
Because I didn't look at just.
Average salary for men and just average
salary for women, I looked at it in the
context of these other variables.
What if all the female faculty members in
this sample were just
hired and their times since their PhD is
very low.
Then, we might get this relationship
between men and
women just because of other
characteristics of the sample.
That is, other values on the other
variables
that are used as predictors in the model.
That's where this gets tricky.
then according to this model is that
difference statistically significant?
If you go back to the table of
coefficients, the p
value's not less than 0.05, so no it's not
significantly different.
Does that mean there's not a significant
difference in salary between
men and women in the sample?
No, because
again, this is the difference between men
and women when taking into
account these other variables.
It's very likely, that, there are more
men, that have, that are at the higher end
of the distribution in terms of
years since PhD, alright?
Because in academia, there are more
men than women, especially years ago.
So, if we took that variable out
and just looked at the difference between
men and women, it might be significant.
So that's where this gets really tricky.
The final question, what's the strongest
predictor of salary?
Well, time since Ph.D, I sort of gave that
away at the beginning.
But how do we know for sure?
You have to
look at the standardized regression
coefficient.
Now, the unstandardized, because the
unstandardized is
linked to the scale of each predictor
right, so to compare different predictors
you
have to look at the standardized
regression coefficient.
That's why I added that column so we could
answer this question.
That had the highest standardized.
The regression coefficient.
So that's why time is the strongest
predictor.
So to wrap up this segment again just
understand the components of the, the
regression equation.
Which I think, should be clear by now.
but more importantly.
Maybe walk through this lecture a couple
times, to make sure you understand
how to interpret the regression
coefficients when
there are multiple predictors in the
model.
Because it can get tricky.
And we'll do more examples of this in lab.
And next week, in the context of
moderation and mediation.