Hi, and welcome to statistics one, lab
two.
The goal of this week's lab, or goals of
this weeks lab, are one to read a
data file and r, then we're going to learn
a little bit more about object types.
Then, since the topic of this weeks
lectures was mainly distributions,
histograms, and summary statistics,
what we'll do is we'll print some summary
statistics in
R and we'll examine distributions using
histograms and the hist function.
So you can see that I'm in the R editor
already.
So this script will be available on the
course website.
So you can follow along.
And this'll be how I'll start each lab.
So we have a script and
as I did with lab one, I'll just walk
you through this script, I'll execute just
lines of
code at a time and then we'll go to
the R console, we'll see what, what output
we get.
And this week we're going to look at some
graphics, so
we'll, we'll move to exploring the
graphics output as well.
just a couple of notes before we start.
you've noticed that as
particularly in the discussion forums that
there's always, almost always more than
one way to do thing, do something in R.
So, be patient.
and if you come up with a more efficient
way to do something than, than I've
demonstrated here
in, in my script in lab, then feel free to
share that with the rest of the students.
You've already done that in the discussion
forums, and that's wonderful.
But again just be patient and, and be
polite as you're sharing that information.
It's, it's a wonderful opportunity that we
have here in these discussion forums.
Okay, so let's launch into lab two.
As I said here are the lab goals
[NOISE]
and each week what I'll do is I'll pick a
particular example.
and this week I'm going to go back to the
example of a
study that investigates the effects of
sports-related concussion on memory and
attention.
And one of the reasons I'm picking this as
an example is well one we talked about it
in lecture, but two you can actually go
look
at this test its available online at the
following
website impacttest.com.
So you can learn more about it if you
like.
And impact or impacttest.com, provides six
main measures.
And those six main measures are verbal
memory,
visual memory, visual motor speed, a
general reaction time
measure, a measure of impulse control and
then just
a, a total symptom score, just how many
symptoms
are you experiencing related to a
concussion.
The way this research works typically is
athletic directors or coaches in sports
they administer this impact test to their
athletes both before
and after a concussion, so they get a
baseline measure and
that's what we're calling some of our
variables in, in today's lab.
and then, after a concussion,
they measure them again.
So having that baseline is very helpful
because you can
see if an athlete has changed from
baseline to post injury.
Without the baseline measures, it would be
harder to detect.
Okay, so let's get started.
Another thing I didn't mention in the
first
lab, is this notion of a working
directory.
[LAUGH]
and I must admit I, I purposefully avoided
it because the working directory, setting
the working
directory, is different depending on what
kind of
computer you're using, what kind of
operating system.
but one universal is that there's a
function in R called
get wd and that will tell you what your
working directory is.
So let me execute that just one line of
code.
And again,
I wasn't clear in lab one how I'm doing
this.
And again, it's because it's slightly
different
on different computers and different
operating systems.
But I'm working on an Apple machine with
the OS10 operation system.
So what I'm doing is I'm hitting Cmnd
Return or Cmnd Enter and I believe in
most.
Windows machines, it's just Ctrl Enter.
So I'm just going to execute that and then
to go
to the R console, I just do Cmnd 1
on an Apple machine.
If you're on a Windows machine it's just
Ctrl 1.
So I just flipped over to the console by
hitting Cmnd 1.
And I executed get WD and
here is my working directory.
And I can go back, by doing
Cmnd 2, again if you're on Windows or
perhaps another system.
Perhaps, it's, it's Ctrl 2.
And I'm back in my in my script in the R
Editor.
So I commented out the, these lines
because
I don't need to reset my working
directory.
And again, if it isn't clear by now,
anything that follows
this pound sign, or if you're on Twitter,
a hashtag sign.
anything that follows that is a comment in
our sorry if I didn't
make that explicit in lab 1, but it should
be clear by now.
Up here, like, these, these are all I'll
just comments because they follow
this pound sign.
Okay another thing you will need to do,
most of you, most likely need to do is
install one more package.
You should've already installed the site
package, if not, no problem, do it now.
again I've commented out, it out because
I've already installed the site package
and this new package, SM, is a package
that we'll use just for this lab.
And you'll see really just for the last
couple lines of code.
But go ahead and install those.
I'm not going to do it in lab, and going
forward this is
going to be how the lab, how I'll do this
in lab.
I'll install them ahead of time so that
I'm not
wasting time here in this lab waiting for
things to download,
so I,I already did that but you can maybe
pause and
go ahead and install those packages if you
don't have them.
Okay, so the next step usually the first
step at the beginning
of a script, is to load the packages that
you'll need to execute this script.
So, I'm going to go ahead and load Psych
and SM using the library
function and R doesn't really return
anything for that.
It may just tell you what version
these packages are consistent with.
but now I know they're loaded.
and again I asked, how can you check to
see how your, your which packages you have
loaded.
The way I demonstrated that was just by
doing search.
That shows you what packages you have
loaded, so you can see here, I, indeed,
have, the Psych package loaded.
I do, indeed, have the SM package loaded.
and I did it that way because it just
returns a little bit of stuff.
It gives me some other things.
Just things that are in my working
directory.
as a couple of students pointed out in the
discussion forums, you could also use the
function installed.packages.
And that gives you a list of all the
installed packages.
I purposely didn't use that function
because look, I have so many
[LAUGH]
loaded here.
And I'm, I'm actually not on my own
desktop computer.
I record these in a recording studio for
sound purposes.
if I, if I did this in my office it would
be, it would be too loud.
but there they are.
So we do know that it's there.
So again, there's, there's typically more
than one
way to do things in R and that's fine.
that's actually one of the, one of the
great things about it.
oops, I don't want to end, I don't want to
exit.
let me just go back to the script.
Okay, so now we have the necessary
packages loaded.
Now what we want to do is read in the data
for this week's lab into a data frame.
And I'm going to call this data frame
Impact.
The data live in, live in is a phrase
maybe
common only in the US.
the data exist in a file called
statsonedatafilesstatsone13labtwo.text.
I know that's sort of a long name, but
this is our internal name for our data
files.
We're calling things stats one for
statistics one, 13
for 2013, because I did this course last
year.
Perhaps I'll do it again next year and
this
is lap two.
And we tend to just save the data files as
text files and then read
them in using the read table function, but
there are other ways to do this.
You could save datafiles as.
csv, for example, and there's a read.csv
function.
There are many ways to do this.
But, for this course, I'm just typically
going to save things as.
txt post them on the course website as.
txt and use the read table function.
There's also this argument header equals
true.
I could write out true but you don't have
to, you can just write Header = T.
what that means is the top row of this
file,
stats1-datafiles-Stats1.13.Lab.02.txt,
the top row of that data file, it consists
of
variable names.
It doesn't actually consist of the data or
it doesn't contain data per se.
It's just the variable names.
So, by setting header = true, I'm telling
R that the first row contains the variable
names and then every subsequent row will
contain the data.
And so if I execute this line of code,
again, I'm going to do Cmnd 1 to go back
to the R console.
it seems to have worked.
It seems, it doesn't return anything.
But it didn't give me an error.
[LAUGH]
So that's good.
so how do we know, if it's there?
And this is one of the things that's
difficult as
you transition from something like Excel
or SPSS or Stata.
And, and I, I know the frustration that's
out there,
because I did this myself just a couple
years ago.
I transitioned from SPSS.
And I used SPSS for almost 20 years.
so, it was difficult.
So, one of the difficult things is you
don't, you can't see your data.
Right, like where, where is the data?
So, one thing you can do is just say,
well,
I want to know the dimensions of this data
frame.
That's always helpful to me, someone who's
used
to thinking about data frames, data
structures, and matrices.
So I can just ask are, well what
are the dimensions, how many rows, how
many columns?
So I'm going to use the functions DIM,
NROW, and NCOL.
Execute that, go to the console.
DIM, impact, gives me 40 and 14.
What that means is there's 40 rows and 14
columns.
And typically there's in, in physiological
research or medical research, which I, I
would call this more medical research a
row represents an individual person.
So there's 40 athletes,
in, represented in this data set and there
are 14 columns worth of data.
So if I ask just N row, of course I'll get
40 and col 14.
Okay, let's go back to the script.
But what if you just, what if you really
want to see your data?
I understand that I, I like to see my
data.
So, one way to do that is to just use the
Edit function.
So, if I execute Edit Impact, then it
brings up
the R data editor.
And now you can see your data, but be
careful it's in editor so you could edit
your data in here, meaning you
could accidentally make a mistake in here
and change one of your values.
And so you have to be careful when you do
open up R data editor.
And let me also say if you're working with
R studio, then you might already see your
data.
So I'm not working with R studio.
If you are working with R studio, that's
fine.
so what you see here is the first column
is just a subject ID.
So this is typical in,
in any kind of research we give these sort
of anonymous ID numbers we don't use
people's name, right?
So that we want it to be confidential.
then what condition are they in?
So we have some con, some athletes who are
just in
a control group and then we have some
athletes who are concussed.
And then we have all these measures from
the Impact Assessment tool.
verbal memory, visual memory, motor speed,
reaction time, and
pulse control, and symptom score.
And we have them at baseline, so these are
all baseline.
And then we have them at retest.
And I call it retest, not post injury or
post test, because remember this control
group, they're not concussed.
So they're getting all of these things at
baseline and then
just months later to match the concussed
group in time so
it's, we're just calling that retest.
Okay.
So, we close the editor and now we're back
in the script.
Let's talk a little bit more about object
types, we covered
this a little bit in lab one but let's
just reinforce this.
So if I just do class impact and names
impact, then
it's just going to tell me well impact is
a data frame.
We, hopefully you should know that by now.
So I've read the data
into impact, R interpreted that as a data
frame because it's a matrix consisting
of of, of all sorts of variables of
different types.
If I type in names, it just gives me the
names of all the variables in the data
frame impact.
So back to
the script.
This is an important piece of code right
here because, you often want to access one
variable in your data frame.
And the way to do that is by naming
the data frame then Dollar sign and the
variable name.
So if I ask what class is verbal memory
baseline or reaction
time baseline and so on what will R
return?
So for class impact verbal memory baseline
well, it says, well that's an integer.
Reaction time, that's numeric.
you'll see, if you go back to, it's
actually on the screen up here, that's
convenient, or
you could go back to the editor you'll see
verbal memory baseline, I believe that's
this column here.
these are integers.
reaction time is typically measured more
precisely.
typically, on the, level of milliseconds.
so you'll see we have these things like
37.46.
So, R interprets that differently, and
calls that numeric.
notice, here, that subject is interpreted
as an integer.
And we don't really want that to be
interpreted
as an integer because we just, we just use
numbers, but it's really a nominal
variable if you
think back to the, the lecture on variable
types.
It's nominal.
We, ideally would put the subject's name
in there
but for confidentiality reasons we often
just assign a number.
So we want, might want to change that, so
let's go back
into the script and it is a very easy way
to change that.
I can use this function factor to change
the class of that variable.
So let me execute that line.
Or two lines.
And now what you see, if I ask R, what is
the class of the variable subject in
the data frame impact, now it's a factor,
because I used this factor function.
And that's better,
because subject is, is, it's not numeric,
it's, you
know, subject 40 is not greater than
subject 39.
Those are just arbitrary numbers that we
assigned to our subjects.
So let's go back to the script.
Okay.
So now, let's switch gears a bit and go to
summary statistics.
And this was one of the main topics
of lecture this week is getting summary
statistics.
So there are functions in R like mean and
standard deviations.
So mean and SD, so and I could do that for
one variable, like verbal memory baseline.
So I'm going to execute that, go to the R
console, and it gives me the mean of
verbal memory baseline.
It was 89, 89.75.
This was out of a 100, so these athletes
at baseline are doing very
well on this, on this task.
But that's to be expected, it's not that
difficult of a task if you look at the
website Impact and they're not concussed.
They're healthy college athletes, so
they're doing well.
the standard deviation is about 6.4.
In the next assignment we are going to ask
you
some questions where you have to, the
answer will
be a numeric value like this and what we'd
like you to do is
respond just with two significant digits.
What do I mean by significant digits?
Well in this case the answer we're looking
for is 6.44.
You can stop right here is my point, you
don't have to type in 6.444039.
That gets a little tedious.
We'll, we'll coat it so that if you do
you'll get it correct
[LAUGH].
but, but all we're asking for is 2
significant digits.
So if this were 6.447, then you should
round up to 6.45.
That's what we mean by two significant
digits.
Okay, let's go back to the script.
So that's a way of getting the mean and
the standard deviation.
You could get the median, the variance,
and so on.
but R has this
really nice handy describe function that
does all of that
for us, for all the variables in the data
frame impact.
So there we go.
This is a really nice function that we'll
use a lot.
Just gives us an overall summary of what's
going on in our data.
So it shows us all of our variables going
down these rows,
so verbal memory at baseline, visual
memory at baseline, and so on.
and then it retests.
There are 40 athletes in this data frame.
It gives me mean.
It gives me standard deviation.
It gives me median.
R gives a trimmed mean, which trims some
of the outliers or extreme scores.
it gives you this other measure of
variability
called MAD which stands for mean absolute
deviation score.
So remember when we calculated standard
deviation, we first
got the mean, then we got deviation scores
and
then to get rid of sign we squared all the
deviation
scores and then we summed them to get sum
the squares.
A different approach, which is sort of
unusual, and R is one of
the only software packages I know that
includes MAD as a default summary
statistic.
What we could do is instead of squaring to
get rid of sine, you
could just take the absolute value of the
deviation scores and then average those.
That's what MAD is.
But we're not actually going to use it
very much
but I just wanted to point that out to
you.
R also just tells you what the minimum
value on this measure is
and the maximum value and the range,
that's the difference between min and max.
And then it gives us the skew and the
kirtosis, the actual values.
SE stands for standard error, which I'm
just going to leave out there for now.
We're going to
talk a lot about standard error in I'd say
two more weeks in lecture.
but it's very easy to calculate.
it's just the standard deviation over the
square root of N.
Okay, but back to the script.
You might also want to look at those
summary statistics by some categorical
condition or by an independent variable.
Or, in this case, a quasi-independent
variable, right?
Because this is the sports related
concussion example.
So, if we want to do that, we can use a
function called Describe By.
So, I use the Describe By function.
I want to look at the Impact data frame.
And I want to split it by Condition.
Condition was the name of the column that
tells me whether an athlete is in the
control
group or in the concussed group.
So if I execute that and go to the art
console, now I have, I have my summary
statistics, first for the concussed group,
and then for the control group.
And it orders them that way just because
it does it alphabetically.
So con, concussed comes before control
alphabetically.
and then, all the same summary statistics.
So now let's go back to the code.
or to the script.
You can also subset your data frame.
And I know if you're coming from something
like Excel
or SPSS or Stata you probably know how to
do that
very well and it's,it's typically like in
a drop down
menu, like in SPSS you can just do data
split file.
it's, it's just as easy in R once you know
the functions.
So, again, let me just run this Edit
function one more
time to make clear what I'm, what I'm
about to do.
So, let's bring back up the data frame so
we're looking at it.
What I want to do is, I want to just
look at the, the athletes that are in the
control group.
So just these athletes.
And I want to do some statistical analyses
just on them.
So I just want to subset that group, and
likewise, then I want to subset just this
concuss group.
So how do we do that in R?
Again, there are many ways to do this in
R.
So I'm just going to show you one.
this is the way my lab tends to do it.
so I'm going to create
a new data frame called Control for the
control subjects.
And, I'm going to use a function
called Subset, I'm going to subset the
original data frame impact.
And I only want athletes who are in the
control
condition.
Well how do I tell R to pick out just
those athletes?
Well, I'm going to use this this system,
which looks a little
may look little intimidating at first but
remember, the way to
access a cell in a matrix is by typing the
name
of the matrix, or the data frame in this
case Impact.
Then open bracket and then row comma
column.
So,
I'm, it doesn't really matter what row
they're in but if they're, or,
I want to know what column.
contains
the, the string control.
So whenever column two, which
is the condition column, whenever column
two says
control, I want to take those athletes and
put them in this subsetted
data frame called Control.
Sorry, that was a little clunky.
So let me just show you how it works.
So what I did is I, I did that, ran that
subset and then I just said let me
see the control athletes and what it does
is it just gives me one through 20.
Let me go back to the script and just do
it again for concussed.
again, I know that might have been a
little confusing.
So, I'm just going to do it again for the
concussed.
We're going to say, I'm going to use this
function subset.
Subset the original data frame impact, go
into that data frame impact.
I'm not worried about row right now, I
just
want to look at column two because that's
condition.
If column two equals concussed, then I
want to take
them out and put them in this concussed
data frame.
A couple other things about this line of
code that, that's illustrative of how
R works, is from now on, you'll see
in lab one, I didn't use this assignment
function.
basically because I just wanted to get
some of the basic points across.
But whenever we assign like a new data
frame or
a new vector of things we should be using
this
arrow and dash, this is saying assign this
sub set of the impact data frame
to this new data frame called Concussed.
So that's a way to do assignment.
You could put equals here, but if you do
that, then it
starts to get confusing when you're
reading big scripts with lots of code.
because I've looked
down here in his hist function, we're
using the equal sign to assign
values to arguments.
So let's just use equals and to do
that, not to assign for example new data
frames.
Another thing is here, we're not saying
does this equal concuss.
We're using equal equal.
So we use a double equal if we're looking
for R to
[INAUDIBLE]
return a true false, or Boolean
expression.
so that's I know a little confusing when
you
start out, but there's just basically,
three ways of assigning.
One is this guy right here, we're going to
do that when we're
taking something and assigning it to a new
object or new data frame.
there's equals.
We're typically going to use that like
down
here, which I'll show you in a second.
As assigning
options to arguments in a function, and
then equals equals
when we want R to return a true false or a
Boolean expression.
Okay.
So did I run this line of code?
I can't remember.
Let's just run it.
There we go.
So now we have two new data frames one
called Control, one called Concussed.
So let's go back to the script.
Now the last thing I want to do in
this script is just show you how to do
histograms.
So, it's real easy.
There's just the function called Hist.
And again this may look sort of confusing,
but what we're doing is I want
to do histograms of all the control
athletes at baseline.
And remember there were six measures, so
I'm
going to do all six measures on one page.
I want to do verbal memory, visual memory,
motor
speed, reaction time, impulse control and
symptom score.
I want to look at all the histograms on
one page so I can just get a glimpse.
So the way to do that is to execute this
one line of code right here.
And what this says is set a parameter,
that's what PAR stands for.
And MFRO is matrix formation by row equals
combine
2 3 or you can get concatenate 2 3.
So basically what this is going to do is
this going to set up
two rows and three columns to give me six
histograms per page.
This is like in Microsoft Word
or, or Adobe Acrodat, Acrobat.
When you want to print multiple
sheets per page, that's all this line of
code is allowing us to do.
So let me just, I'm just going to do all
this in one fell swoop and boom.
We've got six histograms on one page.
So the first one here is verbal memory.
The second one is visual memory,
then motor speed, then down here is
reaction time, down
here is impulse control, and then here is
symptom scorer.
And remember, these are control athletes
at baseline so look.
Most of the athletes have a score of zero
or less than zero.
there's one athlete out here who maybe
exhibited one symptom.
maybe they just weren't feeling well that,
that
day.
so these are healthy athletes because
they're
in the control condition, and this is
baseline.
One other thing I want to point out is,
this, this first
histogram, verbal memory, it doesn't have
anything at the top, notice.
The second one and all the rest, for that
matter, have, at the top histogram of
control bracket colon four, because that's
how we were calling visual
memory in this data frame.
I, I prefer this, it's cleaner.
I have verbal memory right down here.
I don't, I don't need anything at the top,
really.
So, that's why I put in this one histogram
in this line, I
wrote main equals just open quote close
quote so I put nothing there.
That way, there's nothing at the top.
It just
makes it cleaner.
So, again, to
reinforce this point that there's, there's
almost always more than one way to do
stuff in R I'm going to just show you that
we could
use this sort of fancy code of Control
open bracket, blank, comma, three, just to
get the
third column in this, in this data frame.
that might be confusing if you're starting
out in R.
So a more intuitive way, probably, would
be to just name it by its variable name.
Right?
So, I could just say do a histogram for
the control subjects of this variable,
Verbal Memory Baseline.
And put the X label, the X, label the X
axis Verbal Memory.
These are equivalent.
So just to demonstrate that, I'm going to
run this.
And if you look at these two histograms,
they're exactly the same thing.
So that's just demonstrating there's two
ways to call this variable.
and what I mean by call is, is to access
that variable and R.
Okay so these two histograms are exactly
the same in my lab we we like to use this
system right.
Because it requires less lines of code,
and it's just more
efficient and I I like doing it at the
beginning of
this course because it's sort of forcing
you to start thinking
in terms of matrices and data frames which
is really important
going forward in the class.
Okay?
So the next thing we can do is look
at histograms of the concussed group at
base line.
So let me just run all of that.
And, there we are.
Again this is the concuss group, but at
base line.
So let's zero in here on symptom score.
Again, it's just everybody's down here at
zero because it's baseline.
Almost done with this lab.
Hang with me.
if I now look at the control group at
retest,
none of the histograms change very much.
Again, I want to attract your attention
here.
Again, symptom score is very low.
Of course what's going to happen, you'll
see now
if we look at the concuss group at retest.
So this is after an injury.
Now what you see again, let's just go
right over
here to symptoms, now you see symptoms all
over the place.
So,
these are the injured athletes after a
concussion.
And, if you want, you can inspect these
other histograms, or look at some recent
statistics.
You can see that their performance drops
on a lot of these measures.
indeed there, there are effects of
concussion.
of course we simulated this data to make
it up,
but this reflects actual research that
we're doing here at Princeton.
One final thing I want to show you, I know
this lab
is running long, but one more thing
because it's sort of cool.
and this is what we needed that SM package
for.
So, instead of just doing a histogram.
We could do what's called a density
plot, and that's basically just a smooth
histogram.
Let me show you what I mean by that.
and I'm just going to use the symptoms
score from the injured athletes to show
you how, what this looks like.
so here's that histogram I just mentioned.
These are the injured athletes at retest.
So you see, now you see symptom scores are
all over the place.
And on the right, this guy is a density
plot.
What that's doing is just, is it's, it's
smoothing this histogram.
It's sort of best fit to this
distribution.
So it's nice, particularly for this kind
of of, I was going to say experimental
design.
But I should say quasi-experimental design
right.
you can compare density plots using a
function called SM Density
Compare, and that function only exists in
the SM package.
That's why we needed to install that.
So this is the last thing I'm going to
do in this lab.
Let me run that one, and this really, I
think, illustrates the effect of
concussion, right.
So in the green dotted line here, these
are the control subjects at retests.
So they're still hovering right around
zero symptoms, they're not exhibiting any
symptoms.
But, look at the red line.
These are
the concussed athletes at retests, they're
exhibiting lots of symptoms.
And there's a lot of variability in
the number of symptoms that they're
exhibiting.
And this is true of the research that I've
seen
on concussions, so, you know, athletes out
here are exhibiting
lots and lots of symptoms, so these
athletes must have
suffered a really serious injury whereas,
maybe these athletes down here.
maybe they experienced certainly they
experienced an injury,
but maybe less serious and then, then out
here.
So there's some variability in the
symptoms within that group.
so that's sort of a cool graph you can do
using this SM, SM Density Compare function
and it, that lives in the SM package.
And that's it for lab two.
That's everything you'll need to do and,
and to know to complete assignment two.
so good luck with that and I look
forward to hearing from you in the
discussion forums.