Hi, Welcome to Statistics One Lab 6.
In this week's lab, we'll do a lot of the
same things we've done in previous labs.
So we'll read a datafile into R, we'll
start with summary statistics and we'll do
some correlations.
But, the emphasis again this week will be
on regression analysis
and in particular, we will look at
regression analysis that include
a categorical predictor variable.
Because we haven't done that yet, and that
was one
of the things that was covered in the
lectures this week.
Is how to deal with categorical
predictors, and how to use dummy coding.
That is how to take a nominal variable.
And convert it into a series of numeric
codes that we can insert into the LM
function.
So that's the novel piece of this lab.
I'm using an example that's similar to the
one I used in lecture.
So the outcome variable will be annual
salary of faculty members.
but note that this is a different dataset.
I made up a new dataset to illustrate here
in R so
[LAUGH]
you'll see, the salaries are much higher
now.
I sort of did this to reflect more current
annual salaries among the faculty members.
And these are more experienced faculty
members.
You'll see they're, their ages are higher.
so the predictors are age, number
of years as a faculty member.
Number of publications and which academic
department the faculty member comes from.
So history, psychology or sociology.
And that's the categorical predictor,
right?
because that's a, that's a nominal
variable, it's just, there's different
categories.
so we need to represent that somehow via
dummy codes
and I'll show you how to do that in R.
And the sample size in this example is
just a
100 I, I just, I just made up the data.
Okay?
So again at the outset I want to do these
basic things,
check your working directory, if you need
to, set your working directory.
and so on, and load packages, so let me do
those things.
I haven't done that today.
That all worked fine, okay.
Okay, so now we're ready to read the data
in, and I want to.
Actually look at this data and show you
wha, what we're dealing with.
So let's do that.
So you see we have salary it starts on the
lower
end of 60,000 goes up to a higher end of
like 130.
Actually it goes well beyond that almost
up to 200,000.
so you'll see in a minute when we
look at summary statistics these are these
faculty members
are on average about 50 years old with
a lot of experience and a lot of
publications.
but what I want to point out here as
we look at the data file is this
department variable.
it's just, it's just a
[INAUDIBLE]
a character vector.
So P stands for psychology, S for
sociology, H for history.
So obviously, we can't enter that into the
LM function.
R needs a numeric value to put into the LM
function.
So we'll use dummy codes.
And there's an easy way to do that in R.
So let's go back to the script.
First thing I want to do is just look at
some summary statistics and correlations
among the main variables.
So first, let's look at the summary
statistics.
And you see that, as I mentioned these
faculty members are a little bit older
than in the example I used in lecture.
So the average age is about 50.
they've been faculty members for quite a
while they are publishing at
a pretty high rate so an average of 67
publications that's pretty good.
and the average
salary is 133,000.
So this is this is a sample of 100 faculty
members that
are, that are doing pretty well and are a
little bit more established.
so let's go back to the script.
I can do correlation analysis on the main
measures.
I'm just doing.
The data frame FS 1 to 4 because the fifth
column was department, which is a factor.
That wouldn't enter into the correl,
correlation analysis.
And
you see that everything is highly.
Correlated and positive correlated.
And that makes sense, right?
Because if, especially for age, and years,
which I'm
going to show you, are basically redundant
in many ways.
so age and years are highly correlated.
the more years you've been a faculty
member, the higher your salary, right?
Hopefully you're getting annual raises.
but also the more you publish, and
this is true in, in academia, the more you
publish the more marketable you are.
The more
[INAUDIBLE],
the more well known you are you typically
make
more money if you're more productive in
terms of research.
So there's a positive correlation there as
well.
Okay, so let's go back to the script and
start doing some regressions.
I call this first model just model 0
because I just want to show that
years as a faculty member and age of the
faculty member are largely redundant.
Right, their representing almost the same
thing.
their slightly different.
You know, people get their Phds at
different times, they join faculty at
different times but for most part not by
very much.
So, this is an important lesson for
multiple regression is.
We don't want to just throw in all the
predictor variables that we have at our
disposal.
We want to throw in, we want to
include variables that are theoretically
meaningful.
And we don't want to include variables
that are redundant.
So that, the purpose of this first model.
And so why I'm
calling it model 0, is just to illustrate
that point.
So if I run this model,
what you see is years as a faculty member.
That is a significant predictor of salary.
but age isn't.
because they're largely redundant.
One of them is not going to have a signif,
is not going to
explain a significant amount of variants
in the outcome when the other one is
in the model.
Because they're both sort of explaining
the same variants.
And years as a faculty member is the more
meaningful variable here.
So when the model's going forward.
As I said here in my comment.
We're just going to use years as a faculty
member, and leave age out.
Just want to include that to show that
multiple regression it,
it's a bad practice to just throw every
variable at your disposal
in it, in your disposal.
In the model.
You don't want to do that.
Okay, so now let's look at the models.
First, we're going to do model 1,
predicting salary from years.
Then model 2, we'll predict salary from
publications,
and then in model 3, we'll put them
together, and we'll see if putting them
together
does better than, than having them by
themselves.
So first, let's look at model 1.
So in model 1, we, we see that we get a
significant slope.
We could have predicted that based on the
nice, strong, positive correlations.
Right, so for every one unit increase in
years, you, the predicted change in Y,
the salary, the predicted change in salary
is $2,689, or $2,690.
and the T value is 8.4, 8.5.
It's a low P value, so we, we would
reject the null hypothesis that the slope
is zero.
there's a significant relationship between
years as a faculty member and salary.
Makes sense.
And it's explaining a good chunk of
variance in
salary so it's, it's explaining 42% of the
variance.
Just by itself.
Okay.
Let's compare
that to publications.
And again, we know from that strong
positive correlation,
that we're going to get a significant
regression coefficient here, so.
Here's the regression coefficient.
Here's the T value.
It's a very low P value, again, we're
going to reject the null
hypothesis that this slope is zero and
claim that it's statistically significant.
notice the T value here is 9.68 to 9.7.
whereas the T value was around 8.5.
So for publications, the T value is
slightly
higher than it was for years, despite that
the fact that the slope for publications
is
not nearly as steep as the slope for
years.
And the reason for that is the standard
error
is lower in perhaps than it is in years.
So that's why you get a higher T value
despite the fact that the slope isn't
quite as steep.
So that can happen because remember T is.
The slope over standard error, just want
to point that out, okay.
And publication is also explaining
slightly more variance, it's about 49%
versus years.
As faculty member which is 42%,
not a lot more, but slightly more.
The bigger question is how do these two
models compare two model where both
predictors are included in the model.
So let's look at that model.
And what we see, if we look at the table
of coefficients, is both years and
publications remain sig, significant.
So unlike years and age, these two
variables are
not redundant, they're each accounting for
unique variance and salary.
And our prediction of salary should get
better
by including both of these in the model.
over including just one alone.
But to test that, we have to compare this
model to models 1 and model 2.
So that's the final step in this part of
the script.
Let's compare model 3 to first model 1,
and then model 2.
So, does model 3 do a better job?
Well, the way this, we test that is
through this anova function that does
model comparison.
It returns an F statistic, which is sort
of like a T statisic.
We'll cover this more when we talk about
analysis of variance.
it's just a ratio of variances.
So it's a ratio of variance explained in
the two models.
And it gives you a P value, which is based
on a sampling distribution which is based
on degrees of freedom.
and it's significant.
So what it's telling us is model 3 is
significantly better than model 1.
And likewise, it's telling us that model 3
is significantly better than model 2.
Okay, so including both years and
publications in
the model, seems to be the best approach.
Okay, now let's move to the new piece.
Adding a categorical predictor
into this type of progression ananlysis.
So we already have.
Years in publications, but now we
want to look at salary differences across
departments.
so the way I'm going to do that.
And as I noted in this comment here
remember
in R there's almost always more than one
way to solve a problem.
And that's true here.
In dummy coding or doing contrasts.
So I'm just going to show you one way.
when we get to moderation analysis next
week, we'll actually try this another way.
but for now, this is the simplest.
We can use this function C, which stands
for contrast.
And don't confuse this with little c,
which was combined or concatenate, right?
This is big C, capital C for contrast.
What is does is, it takes a categorical
variable and this argument
treatment will just take the first
department, and by first,
I mean the first one alphabetically.
And make that the reference.
So, the first one is history.
So in this, in this example, in this
analysis, history is going
to be our reference group and then we will
create dummy codes automatically.
We don't have to create new columns or
anything.
it will just create dummy code for
psychology and for sociology.
So, I can just run that little piece of
code.
And, it's not going to return anything,
but
it didn't return an error, that's good.
so now I can enter it into a new model,
let's
call it model 4, where we have years, we
have publications.
And now I'm just going to put in this
department code.
And you'll see that this represents our
dummy codes.
Let me show you what it looks like.
So now we have our slope for years.
Which is not that different from what we
saw before.
Our slope for publications, not that
different from what we saw before.
They're still both significant.
But now we have these two new
coefficients, and
this is the new piece that we need to
learn
this week and I covered in lecture, and
it's
sometimes a little bit confusing for
people when they first
do this.
So remember, that by setting up this
department code,
and using this argument treatment, what R
did is
it took the first group alphabetically
which is history
in this case, and it made that the
reference group.
So what that means is, across the dummy
codes
that are automatically generated, history
just had zeros across that.
So, this value right here, 62,000 is the
predicted salary for a faculty member in
the history
department with an average number of years
as
a faculty member and an average number of
publications.
So what are these values here.
Well, this is the predicted difference
between history and
psychology, taking into account average
number
of years and average number of
publications.
So what this is telling us is the
predicted salary
for psychology is slightly lower than it
is for history.
It's not a significant difference, but
it's slightly lower.
But look at sociology.
That's a big difference.
It's $18,000 less, and
it's a significant difference.
So what this is telling us is that the
sociology faculty group is making less
money than the history group.
And it's a significant difference.
but, that's while we're considering years
and publications.
And we're now explaining 58% of the
variance and salary.
I also want to point out that for each of
these models, I
didn't, I didn't note them earlier,
I've been printing the confidence
intervals, okay.
So just one thing to notice is for years
and for publications these confidence
intervals don't cross zero.
Other words they don't include zero.
so that's an indication that they're
going to be significant.
here comparing
history to psychology it does cross zero.
So, the interval includes zero.
So, that's most likely not significant and
that's illustrated here with this P value.
Okay.
So, let's do
[UNKNOWN]
model comparison to see if adding
department improve the fit of the model.
you should be able to predict this that it
does because there was a significant
difference between history and sociology,
all right, but
let's formally test it with a model
comparison.
And sure enough there's the F value,
there's the P value, all right, so yes.
This model did get better by adding
department and
we knew that because one of our predictors
here is significant.
Okay.
so let's examine this mean salary
difference a little bit more closely.
so, if you want to just look at the actual
mean salaries for the departments?
You can use this function called tapply,
which gives us a table
of, for this data, for this, sorry, for
this variable,
for this categorical variable, it'll give
us the mean
salaries.
because the predictions in the model are
not the actual mean salaries.
So let's just look at the mean salaries.
So,
[INAUDIBLE]
I left out my comment.
But, this still worked.
So, if we look at the actual means, right,
these are not predicted means.
These are just the means of the salaries
for history professors, psychology
professors, and sociology professors.
And here we see something that's sort of
puzzling
giving what we just saw in the multiple
regression.
All right, they're not that different.
So 137,000, 129,000, 135,000.
So particularly between history and
sociology.
They're not that different it's only 2000.
Yet the predicted difference was 18,000.
So what's going on?
Well, as I say in my comments here, the
actual means are not that different.
So, there must be differences across
departments in years, and or in
publications.
Because remember the model assumes an
average value of those.
So let's check that out.
We can use this again, this tapply
function.
And we'll do it for both years and
for publications.
So here it is for years.
You see history an average of
22, psychology also 22, but sociology
27.5.
So, the sociology professors have been
working much longer.
Also look a publications for history 63
for psychology about
60, for sociology 76.
So the sociology professors
have been working longer.
And they've published more.
Yet, if you look at their actual salary,
they're just on par with history.
So that's why when we predict salary based
on average number of years and
average number of publications, it appears
that sociology is underpaid.
Right?
That's what the multiple regression model
is showing.
So if we had only considered just average
salary across departments, we wouldn't
have detected this sort of discrepancy
that's happening across these academic
departments, right?
Sociology.
Has been on the job more.
They publish more, yet they're not being
paid more.
The multiple regression analysis that we
conducted reveals that discrepancy
across departments.
And that's one of the sort of powerful
things you can do with a multiple
regression analysis.
but it also illustrates the care that
you have to take when interpreting
regression coefficients.
Especially when inclu, including
categorical predictors.
So let me just go back to the script.
I'm basically done with this lab, I just
added a summary statement at the end
because
I know this can be a little confusing the
first time you go through it.
So there's the, the conclusion and the
lesson at the end.
So if you want to run this script again
for yourself you can try it.
And this will be this example is a good
one
for what you will have to do to complete
assignment six.
So that' s it for this week good luck on
assignment six, good luck on the mid-term
and I will see
you in lab seven.