Hi and welcome back.
We're up to lecture 5, segment 2.
In this segment, we're going to walk
through the
mathematical calculations of the
correlation coefficient little r.
So, when it comes to the important topics
for this segment, that's about it.
Just knowing how to do this calculation,
I'm
going to show you two different ways to do
it.
One I refer to as the raw score formula,
and the
other I refer to as the Z score formula.
But in the end I'll show you that they're
equivalent.
There's actually just one new concept
here.
There's a lot of math that's going to come
at you in this segment.
The one new concept is sum of cross
products and covariance.
And I'll illustrate that through the
calculations.
So first this is more of a conceptual
presentation of the formula, not a
mathematical presentation.
But just conceptually what little r is,
what the correleation is.
Is it's the degree to which X and Y vary
together, relative to the degree
to which X and Y vary independently.
So, we could rewrite that down below as
the covarience of X and Y.
And again, I'll get to that when we do the
calculations.
Over the variance of X and the variance of
Y.
Now as I mentioned there's two ways,
there's more than two ways.
We're just going to show, I'm just
going to show you
two; the raw score formula and the Z-score
formula.
We'll start with the raw score formula.
To illustrate this, it's actually really
easy.
If you followed along in Lecture 4 and the
calculation of summary statistics.
Particularly the calculation of variance.
So remember, variance is equal to standard
deviation squared.
Another way that we write that is mean
squares.
Because it's the sum of squares over N or
the average sum of squares mean squares is
variance.
It's also standard deviation squared.
Let's review the calculation of variance
from that lecture 4, remember
I used the example of Jeremy Lin, this was
to Linsanity.
thing that swept New York during the NBA
season, not this year, the year prior.
and I use this to illustrate not only how
many points per game
was Jeremy Lin averaging during those ten
games, but what was his variability?
So remember we calculated the mean, we
calculated the standard deviation,
we calculated the variance.
The way we did that is, I listed out the
points per game across ten games, and then
that first column, points per game.
To get the mean, we just sum that column,
and divide by the number of games.
So it's the sum of X divided by N, that's
just the average.
So during those ten games Jeremy Lin was
averaging 22.7 points per game.
To calculate variance, we then have to
look at each individual
game and see how much is he differing from
his average.
So this middle column is what we call
deviation scores.
We just take points per game for that one
row, and subtract out his mean.
So the first
one is 28 minus the mean, 22.7, which is
5.3.
We go down, do that for each row.
We can't sum and take the average of the
deviation scores,
because they sum to zero, so the average
would be zero.
So, to fix that problem, we just square
all
the deviation scores, and that's the third
column, right?
So, then, we square every deviation
score, sum those, and that's that.
That phrase, sums of squares.
It's going to be a really important
concept going forward throughout the
course.
This number down here, sums of squares, is
922, divided by ten because there are ten
games.
That gives me means squares; that's
variance.
So, to summarize the results, his mean, or
average points per game during that time
was 22.7.
His variance or mean squares was 92.21.
That's not that meaningful of a number.
So let's take the square root of that to
get us
back into the units of points per game,
that's the standard deviation.
He was deviating on average about 9.6.
Remember that's a little inflated because
I included
that one game where he scored just two
points.
He didn't start.
remember back in lecture 4 we eliminated
that
and the standard deviation was a little
lower.
But that's the calculation of variance.
And sum the squares.
To calculate a correlation coefficient,
all we have to do is
add that one new concept, sum of cross
products, and then covariance.
So to review, how do we get sum of the
squares?
For each row in that data frame.
We calculated the deviation score, then we
squared each deviation score, then we
summed them.
Sums of squares.
To calculate sums of cross products.
Remember now we have two variables,
because we're
looking at the correlation between X and
Y.
So we're going to calculate the deviation
score on x, the deviation score on y.
And take the product of those, and sum
those products.
That's the sum of cross products, or SP.
So written out mathematically, for each
row I'm going to multiply the deviation
score on X by the deviation score on Y.
And then I'm going to sum them.
So here is the formula for sums of cross
products.
Sum of cross products, excuse me.
This is something that you should know and
be
able to calculate off the top of your
head.
So now, let's look at the formula for the
correlation coefficient, again I'm
going to do this two ways.
First, the raw score formula.
So the raw score formula written in its
simplest form, is just the sum of cross
products over the square root of sum to
the squares X times sum to the squares Y.
Remember, go back to the conceptual
definition of the correlation
coefficient, it's the degree to which X
and Y vary together.
That sum of cross products.
Relative to the degree to which they vary
independently, and that's captured
by sum of the squares x, and sum of the
squares y.
So, hopefully you can see the concept
there, now that we're moving into the
math.
If I unpack that, and write it in longer
form, here's the sum.
Of cross products which we just saw, it's
just the deviation score on
X times the deviation score on Y, sum them
all.
Likewise, we've summed the scores x,
summed the scores y.
Those are just the same old sums of
squares that we
did when we're calculating variance by in
the summary statistics lecture.
So now I can open up this formula, here is
the raw score formula again,
and it's simple form, but now it's written
out in long form.
And I am doing that because I want to show
you.
That it's going to wind up being exactly
the same as the Z score formula.
But this is just the same formula written
out in longhand.
So this top part here.
That's the sum of cross products.
This part here, that's sums of squares x.
This part here.
That sum of the square is Y.
Right?
So these two are just equivalent.
Now let's look at the Z-score formula.
I'm going to do the same thing.
Start with it in a simple form, unpack it,
and then
show you how it's the same thing as the
raw score formula.
So if we start with Z scores, remember
any, any scale, any
score can, can be converted to the Z scale
and Z scores.
So if we have everything in Z score
form, then this is the formula for
correlation coefficient.
It's just the sum of the product of the Z
scores.
Divided by N.
So again, now, what I'm doing is unpacking
that, writing things out in longer form.
Remember, how do we get a Z score?
Well, it's the raw score minus the mean
divided by the standard deviation.
So, that's just these first two.
Minds and then how do we get standard
deviation?
Well, first we can get variants, that's
these guys,
right?
It's the sum of squares divided by N or
mean
squares, then take the square root of
that, that's standard deviation.
So here's the final proof of equivalence.
If I write the Z score formula out in
really long form, then what I have is X
minus M of X.
So, X minus the mean of X, over standard
deviation, written in long form.
So this whole piece is just standard
deviation of x.
This whole piece is just standard
deviation of y.
Now, let's write it in its really tedious
long form.
Again, this is just sort of packing and
unpacking algebra.
So if it's been a while since you've done
this, maybe just review these slides.
A few times.
for those of you who have, who are really
familiar
with just basic algebraic manipulations,
this is, this is review.
But if, if it's been a while, or if it's
just new to you, just review these slides.
I, I promise you, they work out
[LAUGH]
that they're equivalent.
so now, what I've done is this is the
really long form.
So what we have in the numerator is this
whole piece is just Z of x.
I'm going to multiply it by Z of y and
just divide by n.
That was the original formula in short
form, right, is Z
of X times Z of Y, divided by N.
So here it is again at the top.
So this top part is exactly what you saw
in the last slide.
Now, to go from this first piece here To
this second formula.
All I've done is, again, I've reduced some
of
the terms just by applying basic rules of
algebra.
So if you see,
in this top formula, we have n in both the
numerator and the denominator.
So those can cancel out.
So we can reduce that formula at the top
to this formula in the middle.
And if you take a close look at
that formula in the middle, it's sort of
cool, right?
Because it's sums of squares, excuse me.
It's sum of cross products
[LAUGH]
in the numerator.
And then sums of squares for X and sums of
squares for Y in the denominator.
Which, remember is
the raw score formula, so sum as, sum of
cross products is right
here, sum as square as X is right here
and sum as square as Y is right here.
Remember, go back to the very beginning of
the math segment, that was the raw score
formula.
So we started with the raw score formula
in simple
form, unpacked it, went to the Z score
formula, unpacked it.
And brought it all the way back to the
raw score formula, to show they're the
same thing.
They're going to give you the same exact
number.
The correlation coefficent.
So finally, this concept of covariance is
really important.
And one that we'll use throughout his
course.
and something that you just need to
have fundamental understanding of, to
understand basic statistics.
So just as in summary statistics I, I, I
emphasize moving beyond just measures
of central tendency like the mean.
And embracing measures of variability,
like variance.
Here too, you need to sort of push
yourself to another level
and say, Okay, well, I know what variance
is, but what is covariance?
You need to be able to just look at these
formulas and, 1, conceptually get them
and, 2, mathematically unpack them.
So to recap, variance is mean squares
because
it's the sum of the squares divided by n.
It's a very simply analogy to covariance,
right?
Covariance, I'm just going to use COV for
covariance
is the sum of cross products divided by n.
Just instead of sum of squares it's sum of
cross products.
And then, correlation is just standardized
covariance.
So that the correlation coefficient fits
between positive one
and negative one, in the same way that
standard deviation
is standardized variance.
Okay?
So variance to standard deviation is
analogous to covariance to correlation.
And finally you might of noticed if you've
been really sharp.
We still have this issue of when to divide
by N, when to divide by N minus 1.
Again this came up in the summary
statistics lecture.
If you're just doing descriptive
statistics,
technically the rule is divide by n.
As we launch in to inferential statistics,
which will be
next week, as we look into, as we start
multiple regression.
When you do inferential statistics, we're
going to divide by n minus 1.
And when we start inferential statistics
in, in the regression
lecture, I, I'll discuss that issue a
little bit more.
But for now, just, if you are doing
descriptive divide
by n, if you are doing inferential, divide
by n-1.
So the summarize, just know how to
calculate this
correlation coefficient, its really
important to know that math
just like you know how to calculate an
average.
It should be clear.
Hopefully, the concepts come through as
you do the math I've been teaching
Intro Stats a long time, and a lot of
students tell me that.
As they actually walk through the
calculations
for correlation and for even more advanced
analyses.
The concepts start to come through as they
crunch the numbers.
So, if this is new to, or if it's been
awhile, challenge yourself and
do it, and review those slides.
and again, the most important new concept
is sum of cross products.
And covariance.