Hi, welcome back.
We're in lecture nine, segment two.
The topic of lecture nine is the Central
Limit Theorem, which is a really
important concept that underlies
everything we've been
talking about in the last few lectures.
Especially with respect to null hypothesis
significance testing, obtaining p
values, and deciding whether something is
statistically significant or not.
In this last segment I'll walk
through the formal definition of the
central limit theorem.
And hopefully this will all come together
so that
you'll see how we get from say a
regression coefficient
to a T value, to a P value, to
making that decision to reject or retain
in null hypothesis.
So let's look at the Central Limit Theorem
formally stated it has three principles.
So first the mean of a sampling
distribution
is the same as the mean of the population.
Second the standard deviation of the
sampling distribution is
the square root of the variance of the
sampling distribution.
That's just saying standard deviation is
the square root of variance.
And finally this is a very important
piece, is the shape of
a sampling distribution is approximately
normal, either if we
have sample sizes that are greater than or
equal to about
thirty, or if the shape of the population
distribution is normal.
So note that if we have big enough samples
and some people might quaver with that N
of 30.
Some people might make it a little higher,
and some people might
make it a little lower depends on the
statistician your talking to.
but the point here is that the population
itself doesn't have to be normally
distributed, as long as we get multiple
samples of large enough
size, say n greater than 30, then the
sampling distribution will
take on a normal distribution.
It's a critical point.
So now let's put the central limit theorem
together with NHST.
In the context of multiple regression.
So this is what we did when we did the
regression examples,
and what we do in lab when we do the
regression examples.
If we're doing NHST, then we start with
this assumption, that the null hypothesis
is true.
Right?
That's the game of NHST.
You start with that assumption.
You then conduct your study.
You can then calculate your regression
coefficient, B.
You can calculate the standard error of
that,
and then you can calculate a t value.
And you saw that in the R output, and the
t value is simply the regression
coefficient over the standard error.
Conceptually, what the t value is, and
you'll see this throughout the course in
null hypothesis significance tests.
The t value is essentially a ratio.
It's a ratio of what we observed the
actual regression coefficient, the slope
relating x to y.
The slope that we observed relative to
what we would expect just due to chance.
So, if I get a T value of one, then, I
didn't find much of anything at all.
I know that's not going
to be statistically significant.
I know that P is not going to be less
than.
05, because what I've observed, my slope,
is
exactly what I would expect just due to
chance.
Typically, I want to get a t value of at
least two or more to show that I've
observed a slope twice as large as what I
would have expected, just due to chance.
But, it's this
conversion from the t value to the p value
that we need to
solidify in this last segment here.
So each t value has
a corresponding p value, but it depends on
the sample size.
So we start out with this assumption, if
the null hypothesis is true, that would
mean that in the population the slope is
zero.
Then no one sample should have a very high
or very low slope.
Let's say I obtained a very high
slope, therefore I would reject the null
hypothesis.
But what I want to do now is get more
specific about this very low, very high.
What exactly constitutes very low, very
high?
Well, it depends on this normal
distribution.
Remember that third principle from the
central limit theorem.
It states that a sampling distribution
will take on
a normal distribution, or it will
approximate a normal distribution.
If we have sample sizes large enough.
Right?
So if we get multiple samples and sample
size is large enough, then we'll
approximate normal distribution.
That means I can make probability
judgments about my outcome.
Now it didn't say in the Central Limit
Theorem that
third principle, it didn't say you get
exactly a normal distribution.
It says it approximates
a normal distribution.
So you don't get that actual perfect
normal distribution.
What you get instead is called a t
distribution, and it's actually what
statisticians refer to as a family of t
distributions depending on sample size.
So, if you have a really large sample,
then
your t distribution that you can use for
your
probability judgments to obtain your
p-values, will
look much like the perfect normal
distribution.
But as your sample size gets smaller your
t distribution gets a little wider, which
means you need a larger t value to get out
into the extremes to get a low p value.
But that's where the p value comes from.
We do our study,
we calculate our regression coefficient,
we calculate standard error, we calculate
t, it's simply b over standard error.
Then
I have a certain t value.
Then based on my sample
size, I pick a certain t distribution, and
I find where
is that t value in the t distribution that
I need to use?
And if it's way out here in the extreme.
Then I'll obtain a low P value, because
the P value says its the probability
of obtaining these data, or more extreme
given the assumption that the null is
true.
Well the null being true
would give me a T of zero.
So if I get an
extreme score way out here, I'm going to
get a low P value, and I'll
be able to reject the null hypothesis.
So where does the P value come from?
It comes from the T value and its
corresponding C distribution.
Which depends on sample size.
And the
p value, to be specific, is just the area
under the curve at that particular t value
and beyond.
So if you're way out in the extremes
you're going to have a low p-value.
You'll reject the null.
If you fall around the middle then you'll
have a high p value, you'll retain the
null.
So to recap, we assume the null hypothesis
is true.
We conduct the study, calculate our
statistics,
get our t value.
And then, we can get our p value based on
t, and the sample size, and the
appropriate t distribution.
Again, if the null hypothesis is true, no
one
sample should have a very high, very low
slope.
I obtained a very high slope, therefore
rejecting the null.
Very high and very low simply means p less
than.
05 .
So less than 5% of the distribution in the
extreme positive tail
of the t distribution, or in the extreme
negative tail of the t distribution.
Now remember, I want to reiterate at the
end of the segment, I'm wrapping up here
sampling error therefore standard error is
largely determined by sample size.
Alright we, we went over this when we
talked about sampling, way back when I
introduced
the, the notion of sampling error, and
defined
standard error as the average amount of
sampling error.
Right?
And this should just
be conceptually easy to wrap your head
around.
If I have small samples relative to large
populations,
I'm going to have a large degree of
sampling error.
It's also right there in the math, so
again, sampling error is largely
determined by sample size.
Back when we talked about sampling and
the idea of sampling error, we illustrated
this
by showing you what the distribution look
like for six
different samples of different sizes.
So the first one on the upper left
is a sample size of 10, then 20, then 50,
then 100, then 200.
Then a 1000 and the thing to notice in
these different samples and this is what
we covered when we talked about the, the
idea of sampling error and standard error
is
the smooth function here.
This normal distribution when sample size
is only 10 is much, much wider Then the
function when we
have a really large sample, say a 1,000.
That's
because standard error is the standard
deviation
of this sampling distribution and
as samples get larger.
They're going to squeeze in around the
mean,
and the standard errors going to get very
low.
This goes back to the problem of NHST
being bias by N.
Right?
That's like this example here, let's take
it even further, imagine we had a million
subjects in our sample, then the standard
error would get really, really small and
that
distribution would get really really
tight.
But remember t equals B over standard
error.
If standard error gets so small then it
won't really matter what my slope is.
I'll get a pretty high t value.
And a pretty high t value will give me a
low p value.
And I'll get something that's
statistically significant.
Okay?
So it's important to try and obtain large
samples to give yourself a chance to
obtain
the significant effect, but always
remember, that, NHST's
in this whole process is biased by sample
size.
Which is why I advocate following up
NHST's with estimatyes of effect size.
Another way to look at this is to drive
home this point that, that sample
size really drives and determines sampling
error and
influences the t value and the p value.
Is here, again we've taken six different
sample sizes,
again same sizes 10, 20, 50, 100, 200, and
1000.
And we standardized each of
these samples so they would have a mean of
zero.
And then we just looked at the standard
error associated with that mean.
And the first thing to notice is in this
first sample with an
n of 10, the mean is plotted right here in
this bar plot.
It's not even zero, because there's such a
large degree of sampling error.
Right?
And this
bar here reflects the amount of sampling
error.
That's the standard error bar.
So what you see as sample size increases,
the actual mean approximates zero.
And the standard error bar shrinks,
because standard
error shrinks as a function of sample
size.
Again, it's a critical
point which is useful when you're
designing experiments
or studies, if you can get large samples.
But it can also be misleading when you
have obtained statistically significant
results with really large samples.
Again that's why we follow up NHST's with
estimates of effect size.
So to rap up this segment and hopefully
bring the last few lectures
all together and rap it up, the Central
Limit Theorem has these three principles.
The mean of a sampling distribution is the
same as the mean of the population,
and if we're assuming the Noel hypothesis
to be true that means going to be zero.
The standard deviation is just the square
root of the variance.
And then third most importantly,
is that the shape will approximate a
normal
distribution if we have a large enough
samples.
Even if the shape of the population isn't
normal the
shape of the sampling distribution will
approximate that normal distribution.
It won't get perfectly normal and we will
get a
family of tea distributions instead that
depend on sample size.