Hey, welcome back.
We're up to Lecture Three.
In lecture three, we'll be talking about
Variables, Distribution and Scales.
And as you can tell from the title of
the lecture, this lecture is divided into
three segments.
In this first segment we'll talk about
types of variables.
It's very important at the outset of the
course, to understand what type
of variable that you're dealing with
when you're conducting a particular
statistical analysis.
So we'll be careful here to explicitly
define different types of variables.
So first, what is a variable?
Well, a variable is anything
that can take on multiple values, in
contrast to a constant that
only takes on one value.
So comparing variables and
constants you might say, is like comparing
apples and gravity.
So, there's apples and gravity, apples,
the size, the
shape, the weight even the type of apple,
those are all variables.
There are lots of different types of
apples, they
take different sizes, different shapes,
different weights and so on.
Those are all variable.
In contrast, gravity or gravitational
force is a constant on Earth.
In statistics, it's common to classify
variables into four distinct kinds.
And I'm going to follow suit with that
tradition.
And the four kinds are nominal, ordinal,
interval, and ratio.
You might think, where did these four
kinds come from?
They come from, classic cognitive
psychologist, S.S. Stevens.
And this is a classic
paper published in Science in 1946, where
he outlay, outlined
these four types of variables are four
types of measurements.
So lets start with the simplest type of
variable, a nominal variable.
A nominal variable and it, it literally
means to name types, of,
of, instances of, of variables, is to just
assign individual
cases, two categories.
So for example the Coursera students that
are out there that are watching
statistic one, statistics one they come
from countries all over the world.
So your country of origin is a nominal
variable.
It's just assigning individuals to
categories.
So country of origin, is a nominal
variable.
It just allows me to distinguish some
students from others.
So there are some students from Brazil,
some students from
Argentina, some from Australia, India, the
US and so on.
The next type of variable is an ordinal
variable.
Ordinal variables are used to rank order
cases in a data structure.
So, again, if we think about the countries
where all of
our students are coming from in this
Statistics one course on Coursera.
I might rank the, the countries according
to population.
So some countries like
China, India have much larger populations
than smaller countries say like France
or a really small country say like
Luxembourg, have smaller populations.
And if I just wanted to rank order them,
in terms of who has the highest
population, they get a number one, who has
the second highest population they get a
number two.
Then, ranking would
be an ordinal variable.
Interval variables are
also used to rank order cases, so we can,
we can order cases from top to bottom.
but, in this case, the distance, or
interval, between each value is equal.
That's why it's called an interval
variable.
So again, sticking with this theme of
countries
of origin for Coursera students each
country, if we
look at the globe, has a longitude and a
latitude.
And I can compare the longitude and
latitude of each country.
And the distance from, say zero longitude
to a hundred longitude is
the same as the distance from 100
longitude to 200 longitude.
They're equal intervals.
They're equal spaces.
So longitude, and latitude, those are
equal interval variables.
And in case you're not familiar with
longitude, latitude, here's an image of
the globe.
so, longitude just refers to the
East-West, where are
you on, on the globe.
And latitude just refers to North-South,
where are you on the globe.
And again, the point of this interval
variable is the distance
between, say, zero degrees latitude, which
is the equator,
which is right here.
The distance between zero degrees
latitude and, say, 30 degrees latitude is
the same as the
distance between 30 degrees latitude and
60 degrees latitude.
So this distance is equal to this
distance.
That's the point of an interval variable,
is the
intervals between each unit are equal, so
we call them equal
interval variables.
Okay, the final type of variable is a
ratio, variable.
This is the same as interval, but they
also have a true zero point.
So, what I mean by a true zero point, so
let's take population.
When I talked about ranking the different
countries, all I was doing is ranking
them.
I wasn't talking about the actual
population.
If I wanted
to look at the actual population,
population is a ratio variable,
and it's a ratio variable because it has a
zero point.
So if the population of a country is zero,
that's meaningful.
That's, that means that it's, humans are
extinct in that country, right?
So it's a true, what we call a true zero,
another example is age.
If your age is zero, you could really
have no age.
another good example, and an example we're
going to
use a lot in the next segment, is
Temperature.
So temperature on the Kelvin scale, we're
not used to temperature on the Kelvin
scale unless you've taken a lot of
chemistry courses, you might be used to
that.
But temperature on the Kelvin scale is a
ratio
variable, because, zero Kelvin is absolute
zero, no temperature,
it's absolute zero.
The temperature on a Kelvin scale is a
good example of ratio variables.
So in this classic, paper by Stevens in
1946, he came
up with these four distinct categories or
types of variables.
because there are different types of
things
we can do with these kinds of variables.
I know this font is a little fuzzy and
hard to see.
I purposely cut and paste this table from
Stevens 1946, because I think it's an
important paper.
everyone should read it.
If you can get your hands on Stevens,
1946,
or, maybe we should post it to the
website.
it's a classic paper for statistics, and
also a classic
paper, paper for cognitive psychology and
for psychometrics in general.
I won't go through the whole, whole slide.
You can look at this at your leisure.
The point is that, a variable of type,
say,
nominal only allows us to do certain
things.
It only allows me to say, are two entities
equal or not equal?
So are you from the same country or
different countries?
So if I take two students at random from
this
course, and I just know this nominal
variable country of origin.
All I can do is say are you from
the same country or are you from a
different country.
I can't say anything about greater than or
less than.
I can just say are you from the same or
different.
That's all, that's all nominal variables
allow us to do.
As you go down this, this list, you'll see
as you go from nominal to ordinal to
interval to ratio you are allowed to ask
more and more questions of your variables.
So for ordinal, I can ask not only are you
the same or different but I can ask.
Are you ranked higher or lower?
So, do you come from the same or different
countries?
And does your country have a greater than
or
less than population than the other
student, and so on.
With interval, I can ask questions about
by how much are you different, alright?
If I just have rank orderings.
So if your just, if, all I know is
you come from the country that has the
greatest population.
And then I know that you come from
the country that has the second greatest
population.
I can't ask, well, what's the difference
in population?
That's what interval and ratio variables
allow us to ask.
Just, another example, perhaps a little
more intuitive.
Think about the, the people
who are running a race or swimming against
each other in a swim meet.
You know, you can get first place, second
place, third place.
Like in the Olympics, you get the gold
medal,
you get the silver medal, you get the
bronze medal.
If all I know is the rank ordering, that's
the ordinal variable.
Just first place, second place, third
place, who
got gold, who got silver, who got bronze.
If that's all I know then I can't ask,
well, by how much did the winner win?
So was it as really close race between
first
place and second, rr, was it just a
blowout?
So the person who won was way ahead of the
person in second.
If all I know are the rankings, if all I
know are the ordinal variable, then I
can't answer that question about distance.
But if I have their time,
say it's a running race, or a swimming
competition, if
I have time, that's a ratio variable,
there's a true zero.
Then I can ask questions about, well, by
how much did
the winner come in first place over the
second place finisher?
And by how much did the second place
finisher
come ahead of the third place finisher,
and so on.
So, as you go down this list.
You're able
to ask more detailed questions.
And so, in statistics and in this course,
we're going to strive for variables, that
give us that interval or ratio scale.
We can't always do that, but ideally we'll
use interval
or ratio variables because they're the
richest in terms of information.
They allow us to ask the most in-depth
questions of our data.
So just to quickly preview the variables
that we're going to use in this course.
In experimental research, I talked about
independent variables.
So, for example, in the Polio vaccine
trials, the independent variable was the
treatment.
Whether the child received the vaccine, or
the placebo, that's a nominal variable.
They either got vaccine or placebo.
like, the memory
training experiment.
They either got training, or they didn't
get training.
That's just the nominal variable.
Subjects are randomly assigned to one of
those two conditions.
the quasi-independent variables are also
an
example, so the sports related concussion.
Here was concussion, no concussion.
Those are just nominal groups.
another good or popular quasi-independent
variable is genders female, male.
we'll typically use interval and ratio
variables as our dependent
variables, or as our measured variables in
correlational
research.
So, for example, the rate of polio in a
community, like how many kids out of a
thousand, acquire
polio after the vaccine, that was our
dependent variable.
Or we could look at score on an
intelligence test, or
score on a personality survey, those are
in the interval ratio type.
And finally it's important to keep track
of whether your variable are discreet or
continuous.
So, what I mean by discreet variables are
examples like nominal variables.
They are discrete categories, separate
categories.
Whereas continuous variables are like the
interval and
the ratio type, where there's just a
continuum.
So, we have this scale on,
in, say, like, an intelligence test, and
it's just a continuum.
ordinal variables are a little tricky.
They're technically categories, right?
If they're, if I only have, say, first,
second, and third, gold, silver, bronze.
those are like categories, but they're
ordered and in some
cases we might want to take averages of
ordinal variables.
And then they'd
look more like interval or ratio.
So we'll talk more about that later as we
get into some actual analysis.
So, to sum up this segment, the main point
is that there
are different types of variables that
we're going to use throughout the course.
And that statisticians use to do their
research.
And it's really important at the outset
that you
always know what types of variable you're
dealing with.
Because you can only apply certain
statistical procedures, to, variables of
certain types.
So just remember that there are four
different types,
Nominal, Ordinal, Interval and Ratio.
And know that as you go from nominal to
ratio, you're
allowed to ask more and more interesting
questions of your data.
And that's the end of this segment.