Hi, welcome back to Statistics One, we're
up
to lecture eight, and the topic of lecture
eight,
is Null Hypothesis Significance Testing,
which is a, a
fundamental topic in statistics and a
somewhat controversial topic.
so we will talk about the basic logic of
null
hypothesis significance testing in the
first segment in this lecture.
And then in the second segment,
I'll talk about why it's controversial,
why there
are some problems with it, and then we'll
talk about some of the remedies that you
can apply, to deal with some of those
problems.
So this lecture we'll just have two
segments.
As I said, we, the first segment,I'll
just give an overview, introduce the, the
process
of NHST and then in the second segment,
we'll talk about why it's such a
controversy
and, we'll talk about the problems and
then ,how you can address those problems.
So first an overview.
Null Hypothesis Significance Testing, when
I, when I teach undergrads statistics
I refer to as a game, it's a game we play,
as scientists who do research.
not all of us play this game, there are
many scientists out there, especially in
the last decade
or so, who have argued very vehemently
that we
should stop playing this game and that we
should ban
null hy-, null hypothesis significance
testing, from all
of scientific research, because they argue
it's very misleading.
I don't take that position, I'm, I'm not,
I, I
don't describe myself as pro NHST, but I'm
also not anti-NHST.
I think if it's taught appropriately,
which hopefully we can
do in this lecture and you understand what
it can
do, and what it can't do then you'll be
fine.
so let's talk about how it works.
And again, it's nice to think of it as, as
a game.
This is a game we're playing, as we're
conducting our research.
So before we conduct a study or an
experiment, we set up two hypotheses.
One I'll call the null hypothesis, and
that's just H sub zero.
So if were doing say a cor-relational
analysis,
the null hypothesis will just be R equal
0.
The alternative hypothesis would be say,
I'm
expecting or predicting a positive
correlation, so R
is going to be greater than zero, that's
the
alternative, so this is how the game
starts.
Step one, Identify the null hypothesis and
the alternative hypothesis.
We could do this in
regression as well, so here the null
hypothesis is
that, the regression coefficient, the
slope between x and
y, is 0, and the alternative is that, it's
positive our hypothesis is, we're
predicting a positive relationship.
if the alternative hypothesis is, it
predicts
the direction of the relationship in a
correlation
or regression analysis, as I just showed
you
there, then those are known as directional
tests.
We could be more agnostic about, what
might happen in a study or an
experiment, and not predict the direction,
so that's known as a non-directional test.
you might have heard
of these before, the directional test is
sometimes referred to
as a one-tailed test, and the
non-directional, a two tailed test.
We'll talk about why that is in the next
lecture.
So, again, here would be the setup for a
non-directional test in regression.
So the null is still that, the
regression coefficient is zero, but now,
the alternative
is that it's just not equal to zero.
It could be positive, it could be a
negative, and that exclamation point
equals, remember, that's how we that's the
notation for not equal to, in R.
So I'm going to use that, I'm going to
start to sneak R
notation into the lectures, now that
you're getting familiar with, with R.
So step one of the game, is we
just state the null hypothesis, state the
alternative hypothesis.
Then going in to our study, this is the
weird part, one of the weird parts
[LAUGH]
we have to assume that the null is true,
then do our study,
calculate all our statistics and then,
reassess that assumption.
That's sort of odd and backwards and this
is why critics of
null hypothesis significance testing, say
it's
just that, a weird approach to science.
because very rarely are we predicting
nothing, right?
Very rarely do we develop theories
that predict no relationship between two
variables.
you know, Jonas Salk didn't predict that
his vaccine wouldn't work, so it's rare
that we're looking for no relationship, so
it's a little bit weird and backwards.
but, anyway, that's how it's going to
work.
We're going to assume the null is true,
through our study,
calculate some statistics and then, we can
estimate the probability of observing
the data that we did observe, given that
initial assumption that the null is true.
That gives us a p value at the end, and if
you're, if you've had any
exposure to research, or, or just reading,
about
research studies online, or in the news,
you'll often
hear this phrase, the relationship was
statistically significant, p less than
0.05.
That's where that this is where that comes
from.
So if we get a very low p value for
example less than point 05.
So if the probability of obtaining the
data we obtained, given
the assumption that nothing was going to
happen, if that probability is so
low like less than 5% chance, then we
reject the
null, and we say, hey it looks like the
null
hypothesis is, was wrong, looks like there
is an effect
here, there is a relationship between X
and Y, for example.
So that's how the game works.
And if you play this game, you have to be
prepared for
one of these four outcomes.
So strictly speaking,
if you're doing an NHST, you're going to
wind up in one of these four boxes.
So the way I demonstrate this in, in my
undergrad
class is At Princeton, is think of these
two rows
in this table which I've labeled" Truth,"
sort of like the truth is out there.
We don't know what the truth is.
That's why we're doing the research.
We don't know if the null is true or if
the null is false.
We don't know.
so that's why we're doing this.
So the truth is out there.
so we have to, so think of these two rows,
as alternate universes.
They can't coexist, so either the null is
true or it's false.
So, we we either live in the world that's
represented by row
one, or we live in the world that, that
represented by row two.
Those, those are mutually exclusive
different worlds, okay?
Think, think about the columns sort of
differently, the
columns are, are what we do, as the
experiment
or as the researcher we have to make a
decision based on that P value, based on
our data.
We are either going to decide to retain
the null or reject the null.
We have to make one, we have to make this
binary decision.
Again, that's one of the things that
people don't like about
this, is that sort of strict decision
rule, you have to
reject or retain, that's it, but, that's
how the game works.
So, you retain or you reject.
So, you're going to wind up in one of
these four outcomes.
So, if you retain when the null is true,
great you made the correct decision.
Likewise, if you reject when the null
is false, great you made the correct
decision.
But there's always
the possibility of an error, and there are
two types of errors.
The first is a type one error, or, or
false alarm.
That's where you've rejected the Null
Hypothesis, when in fact, there
wasn't a relationship there, that's why
its called a false alarm.
That's like doing a, a vaccination study
and claiming
that the vaccine works, when in fact, it
really doesn't,
sometimes that happens.
Sometimes there are fluke results or if
you do a, a, test a new drug to see if it,
it's effective in treating, say, HIV.
And you might get an initial result that
looks good, and say, hey, this drug works.
But then, as you do more
research, get more representative samples,
better assessments.
You might found out, hey it doesn't work,
so that will be a type one error.
There is also the possibility of a type
two error, and that's called the miss.
So, there's really an effect out there,
and you just missed it, for whatever
reason.
Maybe you've had poor assessment, maybe
you didn't have
enough subjects you, you didn't have a
random representative sample.
For whatever reason, you may have missed
it.
So there's always the possibility of a
type one error or
a type two error, and we have to live with
that.
Because research
is messy a lot of the time, and we're
doing
this inference process where we're getting
a sample from a population.
So we're engaged in this est, these
estimation procedures.
there's a lot of probabilistic outcomes.
So, we just have to be comfortable with
the fact that, we might make mistakes
in individual studies, but that's okay
because we do lots
of studies.
Alright, you don't do one experiment and
then, say hey, you know,
this vaccine works, or this drug works, it
takes multiple studies, replications.
So, if you're uneasy with this, and the
fact that
we're going to make errors sometimes,
remember that, we're going to to
do lots of experiments, or lots of
studies, or if
you're a consumer of statistics and
research look for replications.
never base a, a conclusion on one
individual study, because they're prone to
these errors.
So to be clear and this is one of the most
important
things I, I, I tell my undergraduate
students to walk away from
my course with is, knowing that the p
value that you see
In the news or in a research paper, or in
your our output.
What is it mean really, it's the
probability
of obtaining the data you obtain given,
the,
the assumption the null hypothesis is
true.
Okay, it is not the flip of that, which is
what a lot of students do and actually,
even PhD's, not my colleagues here at
Princeton they wouldn't make that mistake.
but I've seen people do it.
They often get this outcome and then they
just mistakenly flip it around and say Oh,
well then, it's the probability of this
hypothesis given the data.
So the probability that the null is true
is very low.
That's not true.
You can't make that reverse inference.
So, again, this top line here is one of
the most important things I want
you to take away from this course, even if
you only watch this one lecture.
Please know that, when someone says that
something's statistically significant, p
less than .05
.
What it means is, it's the probability of
obtaining those data, given the
assumption that, there was no effect, or
no relationship in the study or
experiment.
So far in this course, we've only done two
procedures,
that we can apply NHST to.
so we've done correlation and regression.
We're going to apply NHST to lots and lots
of statistical procedures, going forward.
So far, we've only done two.
So when we do correlation analyses, we can
say, well, is the correlation
between these two variables, is it
significantly different from zero?
Again that's that phrase statistically
significant.
That's where it comes from.
And we could ask in a regression analysis,
is the slope of
the regression line for X relating to why
significantly different from zero?
And if so, then we would conclude and we
would
write up in our paper, and perhaps, the
newspaper would
pick it up.
They would say, well, researchers found a
significant correlation between,
a statistically significant correlation
between
working memory and intelligence, right?
That's, that's something that we found
before, that's a, that's a
significant correlation when you do the
NHST procedure and a correlational study.
so, so far, that's all we've, we've been
able to do with NHST.
So in the regression example I want
to point this out to you because you'll
see this in the lab where you start to do
multiple regression, you'll see lots of T
tests and lots of p values.
So it's important that you start to
understand
what these are because you're going to be
seeing
this in a lot of your R output in lab, and
as you do the next assignment.
So the way to get to this p value that
we've been talking about, is to first
calculate a t value.
And I'm going to cover all of this in more
detail, in the lecture on the central
limit theorem.
We'll get into the nitty gritty of these
T values and P values, and their
relationship.
But for now, I just want to show this to
you
because you're going to see it on your R
output.
So the T value is
just the regression coefficient relative
to
the standard error of the regression
coefficient.
And, it's a ratio.
And most NHSTs are, essentially just
ratios.
And they're basically, what did you
observe relative
to, what do you expect just due to chance?
Alright, that was standard error.
Standard error
was "how much sampling error are we going
to get, just due to chance?"
The regression coefficient is what we
actually observed.
So, if what we actually observed is a lot
stronger than what we expected due to
chance, then
we'll get a high T-value and that's
going to result
in a low P value and a statistically
significant result.
In contrast, if my regression
coefficient is the same as what I would
expect, just do to chance error.
So if B is equal to SE, then we have a T
of one.
That's not going to give me a low p value.
That's not going to result in a
statistically significant result.
we would have to retain the null
hypothesis in that case.
and you'll see this in the R output, and
we're going to cover the, the underlying
math of this
in much more detail when we cover multiple
regression
So, to summarize this segment NHST is,
is simply a procedure for hypothesis
testing and it's just one procedure.
There are other ways to engage in
hypothesis
testing, which I'll talk about in the next
segment.
and I said, I like to just think of it as
a
game, we're playing a game, NHST makes it
a little less controversial
if I think of it as a game.
it requires this binary decision, so you
either reject the null hypothesis,
or you retain it and what that means is,
there's always going to be
four possible outcomes, two are great
correct,correct retention, correct
rejection and two are errors, the type one
error False alarm, type two error, a miss.