Hi, welcome back.
We're up to lecture 6 segment 3.
The topic of this lecture is measurement.
And the topic of this specific segment, is
the importance of sampling.
So, in this segment, we're going to talk
about, the importance of random and
representative sampling.
We talk about this back in the first week,
when we talked about descriptive
statistics but I want to
emphasize this again in relationship to
measurement
issues and with respect to evaluating
co-relation.
So, the important concepts and topics to
take away from this segment.
Are first, is this idea of random and
representative sampling.
The concept of sampling error.
And the concept of standard error.
Which is a
measurement that we're going to use
throughout the rest of the course.
And its critical for understanding
inferential statistics, which is
what we'll start launching into in the
next lecture.
So first lets go back to the color wheel
illustration
from lecture one where I demonstrated this
idea of randomness.
So again, assume we have this color wheel
and we can spin it, we can play, play a
game, we can make bets on, on certain, on
the wheel landing on certain colors.
If it's a fair game, we're assuming that
the
likelihood that the wheel lands on any
color is equal.
So the likelihood of landing on the blue
slice is, is equal
to the likelihood of landing on the red
slice and so on.
So if I spin the wheel many, many times,
then I should get the
same number, approximately the same number
of blues, as reds, as yellows and so on.
So we, we demonstrated this in lecture
one.
if we plotted the outcomes on the
histogram, then if it was truly random.
So if it was a fair game.
Right?
If it wasn't rigged.
we should get a histogram that looks
something like this.
It should be approximately the same number
for each color.
And, again from lecture 1 we saw an
example of a rigged wheel.
So, this wheel, this wheel was rigged to
land
on green much more often than say red.
Okay.
So this is an illustration of a non random
process in that color wheel example.
Now let's apply that to sampling.
Remember sampling is the idea that we
want to do research and we want
to do research that makes generalizations
or tests hypotheses about a large
population.
But typically can't get our hands on.
Everyone in the population, so we try to
get a random and representative sample.
Of course we can't get the entire
population, so were always going to be
dealing with this issue of sampling error.
And sampling error defined is simply the
difference between the population and the
sample.
So, if you look back, if we go back just
two slides,
this was a truly random process.
we generated this in r and it was truly
random.
Yet, you notice it's not perfectly equal
in terms of, how
often we landed on yellow, or how often we
landed on green.
There's still some sampling error.
So even our random process isn't perfectly
random.
There's some fluctuation just due to
chance.
That's sampling error.
In statistics, in, in inferential
statistics which is
what we'll be doing going forward for the
rest of the course, the main problem here
is that we don't know the population
parameters, right.
That's why we're getting the sample and
trying to do this inference.
So if, if sampling error is defined as the
difference between the sample statistics
and the population parameters.
How can we calculate that if we don't know
the population parameters.
Well, we, we can't calculate it exactly
but we can estimate sampling error.
So how do we estimate sampling error?
Sampling error mainly depends on the size
of
the sample and that should just be
intuitive, alright?
If I'm trying to make a generalization
about all healthy young
adults or all healthy children and I only
sample, say, ten from the
Princeton community, that's not a very
random or representative sample.
There's likely to be very large sampling
error.
In contrast, if I go out and I get a, a, a
global
sample, say I do this online and I get a
global sample of
10,000 people, then I'm much more likely
to approximate the population parameters.
And I'll have a very small sampling error.
So very simple idea.
The biggest thing that influences sampling
error is sample size.
And that should be, that should be
intuitive conceptually and mathematically,
you'll see it's very easy.
also though, note down below that sampling
error also depends on the variance in the
population.
Again, we typically don't know what the
variance in the population is.
The, the exact value.
but if there's a lot of variance in my
population then I'm likely to have more
sampling error.
If there's very little, variance in the
population
then it doesn't really matter who I
sample.
Right?
So, as variance in the population
increases.
The sampling error is also going to
increase.
So, to illustrate this again, using the
color wheel illustration assume we have
six different samples and these six
samples
just differ in terms of sample size.
So, we'll go from a small sample of just
ten individuals.
Up to a large sample of 1,000 individuals.
So, if we did that
and we plotted them in terms of this color
wheel illustration,
what you see is the distributions get more
and more representative.
As we increase the sample size.
Again, this should be intuitive.
But I really like this illustration.
Because you can just see it right here in
these six graphs.
And again, this was just generated
randomly
in R.
so if you look at the first one, which has
a very small.
sample there's only ten individuals in
that sample.
We get a lot more purple or maroon if you
will then we
do say yellow.
There's actually no yellow represented
in that sample.
but as you go to this very large.
sample of a 1,000, we have almost equal
frequencies of all colors.
So it's a truly random and representative
sample.
I can also illustrate this in histograms.
So, what will be important for us going
forward, is as we get larger samples, and
we minimize that sampling error.
We're going to get more and more normal
distributions, which is great because a
normal distribution
is one of the underlying assumptions of a
lot of the statistical procedures that
we'll be covering.
Moving forward in
this course.
So, here what I've done is just plotted
these again, these six different samples.
But I've plotted them to see how closely
they approximate a normal distribution.
And if you look closely you'll see this
move curve here.
that's the normal distribution and it's
very easy to see that with the sample
of just ten subjects, I'm not getting a
very normal distribution.
it works like you know, there's a slight
negative skewing there the mode.
it looks much higher than the mean.
but then if we go again to
this really large sample, it's almost
perfectly normal.
Okay?
And that's just that's going to happen as
sample size increases.
We're going to get reduced sampling error
and we're
going to get a more normal distribution in
our sample.
So, big sample sizes are great.
So sampling error, again, is just
estimated from the
size of the sample and the variance in the
sample.
The way we do that is we actually
calculate a value and that's called
standard error.
So Standard error is an estimate of the
average amount of sampling error.
And here is the formula for that.
This is a really important formula.
Going forward for inferential statistics.
It will be repeated over and over.
standard error is simply the standard
deviation in the sample divided by the
square root of n.
So, again, you can see the influences on
sampling
error and standard error right there in
the formula.
Alright.
So I said, as sample size increases,
standard error should decrease.
Alright.
So sample size, n, is there in the
denominator, so if that goes really large,
then standard error's going to go really
low.
Alright.
And standard deviation sample should
reflect standard deviation in the
population, so if that goes up, standard
error will go up.
So, to wrap up this segment, the important
concepts and topics, were this idea
of random and representative sampling,
again I used the color wheel illustration.
to demonstrate that and how we can apply
it to samples.
And the discrepancy between samples and
populations.
Which is this idea of sampling error.
And then I showed you the formula for
standard error.
Which is the
average amount sf sampling error.