Hi, welcome back.
We're in lecture ten, and the topic of the
lecture today is, Confidence Intervals.
In the first segment, I introduce the idea
of Confidence Intervals, in the context of
sample means.
In this section, we'll look at Confidence
Intervals, around regression coefficients.
So, again, a Confidence interval can be
applied to any sample statistic.
So this segment, is actually very
repetitive of the last segment.
A lot of the concepts are the same, I'm
just going to
apply those concepts, to a regression
coefficient, rather than a sample mean.
For some reason, in actual reporting of
statistics a lot,
as I said in the last segment, a lot
of researchers are sort of uneasy about
reporting Confidence intervals.
Partly because they're so large.
but worse than that, is there rarely
applied to things like correlation or
regression coefficients.
For some reason people understand that
there's a, there's
variability around a mean, but they there,
there less prone
to apply that same logic to a correlation
or regression coefficient.
So remember, a correlation coefficient or
regression coefficient, they too are
sample statistics.
So they too are just point estimates, and
it
would be better if we were reporting
interval estimates.
So again, this all is the same as what I
said for a sample mean.
we have a
regression coefficient.
iI that's just from one sample, it's a
point estimate.
what that means, is it represent just
one point in this possible sampling
distribution.
So remember, from regression, we can get a
t value, and r gives you that,
because it gives you a t value and then a
p value associated with it.
and the t value was the,
just the unstandardized regression
coefficient, B over
the standard error.
And again, that's just going to fall some
where in a sampling distribution.
So again, it's going to be some point in a
sampling distribution.
If it was there, we would say it's not
significant.
Right?
Cause its not very extreme, but if it was
like way out here,
or way out here, then the probability of
landing there, is very low,
under the assumption that the mean is
zero, then we would reject the null.
Again, this is the same as I said in the
last segment, the
logic here is to report a range of values,
rather than a single value.
Report an interval estimate, rather than a
point estimate.
And again the argument for this, is the
reality of sampling error.
If we know that we have a large
population, and we're only getting a very
small
[SOUND],
even if it's representative, we're getting
a small sample, then we're going
have some degree of sampling error, and we
have to acknowledge that.
And one way to acknowledge that, is rather
than report a point
estimate, just report the interval
estimate,
that takes into account standard error.
Again, this is the main point from the
last segment,
and it's the take home message from the
entire lecture.
The confidence intervals are going to be
influenced by, the width of them, will be
influenced by standard error, which is
influenced
by sample size, and variance in the
population.
So again, let's go to the, back to this
impact example.
what I'm going to do, is run a regression
predicting visual memory score, from
verbal memory score.
And I use these two variables, because
they showed a really
nice degree of correlation, if you
remember in our overall sample.
I think the correlation was in the range
of like, point 4 something.
so we should
get a nice prediction, and a significant
regression
coefficient, if we were doing Null
hypothesis significance testing.
what we can do is get an interval around
that.
And again, just like I did in the last
segment, we'll do it for two different
sample sizes, so we see how the interval
gets wider, as we decrease the sample
size.
So we'll start with a sample size of 40.
And here's what the the regression looks
like.
So I'm just plotting the scatter plot with
the
regression lines, so that's the actual
slope that I got.
That's the point estimate, is the blue
line.
That's the slope relating verbal memory,
to visual memory.
So that's B in the regression coefficient.
But that's just one number, that's a point
estimate.
If I want to get the confidence interval,
well I got that out of r.
And then what I did, is I just plugged it
into the scatter plot.
And that's what you see in the shadow,
around the regression coefficient.
So what this shows me,
is the possible range of regression lines,
that I could expect due to chance.
So how this works, is I could get one, let
me erase that.
So the regression line could be as steep
as if I start at the very bottom
of this shaded area, it could be as steep,
as this.
So that's the upper bound of the
Confidence interval, so
that slope would be the upper bound in our
Confidence interval.
Or it could be a shallow, if I start form
here and go to here, it could be
as shallow as that.
Notice that, that's still a positive
slope.
So in this shaded region, I don't have
a flat line, and I don't have any negative
slopes.
So you can interpret from this visual,
this graphic, with this regression
line, and this 95% Confidence interval
around it, you could interpret this to be
a significant relationship between verbal
memory, and visual memory.
Again, hardcore statisticians would argue,
you're reporting Confidence
intervals to get away from the idea of
statistical significance and NHST.
but those of us who are so prone, and it's
such a habit to think, is it significant
or not?
Would look at this and see well, I can't
get
a flat regression line in there, in this
shadowed region.
That means it's a significant effect.
so that's sort of a, a, an argument
against Confidence intervals,
is when you report them like this, and you
report a
visual even if you report the interval,
and if zero is
not in the interval, then you can assume
or you can infer.
Excuse me.
you can infer that it's statistically
significant.
so even with Confidence intervals, you can
still sort
of run into this problem of the idea of
significance.
But let's look at the interval and the
width
of the shaded region, as we decrease
sample size.
So now, again, I use the impact data, but
now I just got a random sample
of 20.
Same exact variables, same exact
regression, so
it's still LM, visual memory tilde verbal
memory.
and now look what it looks like.
We have a, a regression line that's
similar
to the last example, because that's my
point estimate.
But the shaded region around it is
much larger, because the standard error
went up.
Why did the standard
error go up?
Because n went down.
So now, you see that I can put a flat line
in there.
I could just go
[SOUND].
So, it's possible that the true population
parameter for B,
is 0.
If that's possible, then you would get a
non significant p value if you were doing
NHST.
but the bigger point here, is to show how
wide that
interval is in the scatter plot, when
sample size went down.
The other point to take away, is you
really should be doing this
any time you report a scatter plot,
correlation or a regression.
If you, If you're showing a scatter plot,
it's really nice to
put that that confidence interval, or at
least the standard error around it.
Again, to indicate and to acknowledge,
that you
have just a point estimate, you have just
one sample, and you have some degree of
sampling error.
How much sampling error?
Well that's reflected in the width of the
shaded region, which is driven again, by
standard error.
So it's really nice to put those in there,
we'll do that in the lab.
And we'll, we'll give you script, that
shows you how to generate a
scatter plot with this shaded region
in reflecting standard error, or
Confidence interval.
So again, to wrap up this segment, it's
the same summary as the first segment.
It's, this very important point that all
sample statistics.
Not just means, but correlation
coefficients, regression coefficients.
Anything else you take away from one
sample.
They're just point estimates.
And that means, they just reflect one
point on this idea of a sampling
distribution.
So the logic of Confidence intervals, is
to report
a range of values rather than just a
point.
So we report an interval estimate, not a
point estimate.
And finally, the width of the Confidence
interval, is just going to depend on
standard error.
And standard error depends on sample size,
and variance in the population.