Hi welcome back.
We're up to lecture seven segment three.
The topic here in lecture 7 is an
Introduction to Regression.
And we've already given you an overview of
regression and talked about how to
calculate the coefficients.
I now just want to review some
of the assumptions underlying a basic
linear regression.
Now it turns out that the assumptions
underlying a simple linear regression are
almost identical to the assumptions
underlying the
correlation analyses that we did last
week.
So this segment will be quick and, and
pretty easy.
and basically a review of
last week's assumptions underlying
correlation analysis.
So the first
three assumptions are one, that we have a
normal distribution in Y, the outcome
measure, the second is that we're looking
for a linear relationship between X and Y.
Again, later in the course we'll deal with
non-linear
relationships and there are certainly ways
to handle that.
But for now, as we're starting out, we're
just going to deal with normal
distributions and
linear relationships.
And then again, remember we have this
assumption of homoscedasticity.
Which I'll show you again in the scatter
plots.
Let's not forget as well, just like with
the correlation analysis,
we assume that we have reliable measures
of X and Y.
Remember if we don't have reliability in X
and Y, if
they don't coorelate with themselves then
they can't correlate with anything else.
So, we need to have reliable measures.
We need to have valid measures for our
arguments to make
any sense and we need to have random and
representative samples,
but I covered all that in the context of
correlation.
So, let me go back to these first three.
Normal distribution and why the linear
relationship and homoscedasticity.
When we covered these in the context
of correlations analysis, all we did was
basically
eyeball histograms and scatter plots we
looked
at the histograms for normal
distributions, we looked
at the scatter plots for relatively
linear, linear relationships but
we can do better than that, we can
actually do some statistical analyses to
evaluate these assumptions.
And the way to do that is to save the
residuals from a regression analysis and
then start to investigate those residuals.
And this is a really important exercise
that we'll do over and over again
especially as we go into multiple
regression.
So I am going to bring back this classic
example of Anscombe's quartet.
Because it's just such a pretty and
elegant example, so remember the
correlation between X and Y and each of
these four data sets was exactly
the same, well of course it turns out then
that the regression
equation, if we predict Y from X, is going
to
be exactly the same for all four examples
in Anscombe's quartet.
It's one of the reasons why he created it,
was to show that you could
get the same exact outcome in a regression
analysis, from those four very
different-looking data sets.
So here's the output of a regression
analysis.
The regression constant is three and the
slope is about 0.5.
If you go back and look at the look at the
scatter plots, you see the
intercept indeed is about three and the
slope indeed is about 0.5.
For each one of those.
But clearly only the first one on the
upper left satisfies the assumptions
underlying a linear
regression analysis.
So how can we do a more
sophisticated statistical analysis to test
those assumptions?
Well, to test them, we can save the
residuals and this is easily done in R.
We're going to do it in lab this week.
but remember, for each individual, we're
going to have
a predicted score and we'll have their
actual score.
So it's a very simple step, to just save
the residual.
We can then look at those residuals as a
function of the x productive variable.
So, we can construct new scatter plots,
were x remains on the X axis.
But now let's put the residuals on the Y
axis.
And here's what it looks like.
With
Anscombe's quarts, quartet.
The first model on the upper left, the
first dataset, this is ideal.
This is the kind of thing we want to see
when
we save residuals and plot them as a
function of x.
There's virtually no relationship between
x and the residuals.
They're independent and the residuals some
of them are above zero, some of
them are below zero, that indicates
homoscedasticity.
So this looks great, that's exactly what
you want to see.
Otherwise if you see that there is a
relationship between X and the residual,
as is the
case in all the other examples then you
know
that you have some sort of measurement
error in
x, or some sort of confound in your study
or in your model because x is somehow
related to
the residual and you'll see that if you
plot the
residuals as a function of x as we've done
here.
So you see they're not linear
relationships across the board.
But they're clearly relationships.
So each of these other data sets indicate
violations
of the assumptions of a linear regression
analysis.
It's only this first one that satisfies
the assumptions
because the residuals are not a function
of x.
So if I took the correlation in this, it
would most likely be right about zero.
Flat line, some are positive,
some are negative, again indicating
homoscedasticity.
So, to wrap up this very short segment,
again it's pretty much
a recap of the assumptions that we looked
at when doing correlation analysis.
Most importantly normal distribution in Y,
linear relationship between
X and Y, homoscedasticity, and the best
way most of
us get a way to test those assumptions,
see
if we violated them, is to run a
regression analysis,
save the residuals and then start to
examine the residuals as we did here, for
example plotting them as a function of
your
predictors, in this case just the 1x
variable.
And what you're looking for is no
relationship at all, they should be
independent.
If they're not, that indicates you have
some sort
of dependency between your systematic
predictor, and your unsystematic error
which indicates a problem and a violation
of one of the assumptions.