Hi, welcome back.
We're up to Lecture 4, Segment 2.
And in this lecture, we're talking about
summary statistics.
And in this segment, in particular,
we're going to talk about measures of
variability.
So what do I mean by variability and
measures of variability.
Well, in the last segment, we talked about
measures of
central tendency, like the mean, the
median or the mode.
What those measures do is they try to
capture
the center point of a distribution.
What measures of variability
do is they try to capture how much spread,
or how much of a dis, how wide is
the distribution.
So, the two main measures
that we'll look at are standard deviation
and variance.
And variance is simply standard deviation
squared.
So standard deviation
is just the average deviation from the
mean in a distribution.
And we'll see that mathematically in a
moment.
And again, variance is standard deviation
squared.
So this is an important formula to know.
I'm assuming that most of you already knew
the formula for a mean.
And if you didn't know it already, it's
all right.
It's easy to remember.
Remember, it's just the sum of the scores
divided
by the number of scores.
So sum of x divided by n.
This formula is just in, just as important
to know.
You should know this off, off the top of
your head.
the formula for standard deviation and for
variance.
It's very similar.
It's just now we're going to get the sum
of deviation scores squared.
That's known as the sum of squared
deviance scores, or for short sum of
squares.
And divide that by n.
And I'll walk you through the math, so you
get familiar with
this, because this is a really important
concept going forward in statistics.
Just knowing how to calculate standard
deviation and variance, and understanding
them conceptually.
Okay.
So, if this is new to you, please spend a
lot of time reviewing this
segment, so that you get this, this, the
math down and you get the concept down.
And just a word about variance before I
dive into the math and an example,
is that sometimes, especially in
psychology and sociology
or political science, variance gets a bad
wrap.
So, like I study individual differences in
intelligence, for example.
And a lot of times, people think, oh,
well, it's so horrible
that this child has scored so, so poorly
on this intelligence test, or
so on.
but it's always important in statistics to
remember that variation is natural and
it's good, it's information in statistics.
So, look at variance with a very positive
view if
you can, because it's, it's, as I said,
it's natural.
And the way to think of it in statistics
is variance is information.
It's going to allow for us to investigate
co-variants and correlation and so on.
So, and if, if you don't trust me or if
I'm not convincing you
enough that variance is natural and
variance is good check out the guy named
[UNKNOWN].
He, he thought that he's pretty good.
so, onto an example.
There is one of my favorite examples I
developed last year
because this happened in New York city,
which is where I live.
and it happened in professional basketball
in the US in the MBA.
this is a guy called Jeremy Lin, who was
not
that big of a star, not a star at all
actually.
He's not really a top basketball player in
the US.
but all of a sudden, he got the chance to
play for the New York Knicks.
so there's Jeremy Lin in Madison Square
Garden.
That's right there in the middle of
Manhattan,
just a couple of blocks from where I live.
so, I got caught up in what the media
called Linsanity.
Jeremy Lin suddenly took the NBA by storm,
because he started scoring a lot of
points.
so what
we're going to do is we're going to look
at
Jeremy Lin's points per game over that
time.
it was during the winter of 2012.
so what I can do is, I can look at Jeremy
Lin's points per game across, let's just
pick out a 10 game stretch of that season
in 2012.
And if you start at the bottom, actually,
you'll see there's just 2 points per game
in that one game.
And that was typical of what Jeremy
Lin was doing before one of the star
players on the Knicks was hurt, and Jeremy
Lin had the opportunity to play.
So Carmelo Anthony, who is one of the
stars of the
New York Knicks, he was hurt, Jeremy Lin
got the opportunity to start.
In his first opportunity to start, he
scored 25 points.
And then the next time he, he, he started,
he scored 28 points, and so on.
He scored 23.
And I think it was around here when he
scored 38, that
Linsanity totally set in in New York City
and we got all excited.
We thought the Knicks were going to win
the NBA championship, it never happened.
not happening again.
Today as I filmed this the NBA game
seven championship is happening tonight
here in the US.
and the Knicks aren't in it
[LAUGH].
that is the topic of this lecture.
we have Jeremy Lin's points per game
across 10 games.
We can get summary statistics from this.
Right?
So we can get, what was his average across
this, this segment, or this section of the
season.
So what was his average across these 10
games?
And that's a common statistic in a lot of
sports.
So,
points per game, or say goals per season
if you're looking at football
internationally, or hockey here in the US
is also big right now.
so we could get just average points per
game.
But I also might want to know, and, and
it, it's an important statistic to look at
if you're looking at sort of the quality
of players, is how variable are these
players across
a certain stretch of games.
So, was Jeremy Lin consistent across these
10 games, or was he sort of all
over the place, having a good night one
night, a bad night the next night?
So first, let's calculate the mean.
That's just the sum of all the scores
divided by n.
And I did that down at the bottom of the
screen here.
To get
the mean, I just sum that column of points
per game.
The sum of that column is 227, or
averaging over 10 games.
So it's 227 over 10, or 22.7.
So during that 10 game stretch, Jeremy Lin
is averaging 22.7 points per game.
That's the mean, that's a measure of
central tendency.
But we want to know
about his variability over those 10 games.
So, the way to calculate variability is
variance and standard deviation.
The first thing we want to do is for each
game, we want to calculate what's known as
a deviation score.
And that's this column.
These are deviation scores.
So to get a deviation score, I just
take how many points did Jeremy Lin score
in one game and compare it to his
average.
So, in this first row, I can take 28 and
subtract his average 22.7 and I get 5.3.
So he was deviating from his average about
5.3.
He was 5.3 above average that night.
And so on, I can calculate
each deviation score.
The whole point of variability is getting
sort of an average deviation.
Now, I can't take the average of this
column because it sums to zero.
So, if I sum that column, I would get zero
and divide by 10, I'd have zero.
So, instead what we'll do is we'll square
each deviation score,
that's this last column, is the deviation
scores squared.
That gets rid of sign.
So then when I sum the squared deviation
scores, I can divide by n and that gives
me variance.
So, this last column, I've just taken each
deviations score,
squared it and then sum all this squared
deviation scores
to get 922.1.
If divide
by 10, that gives me 92.21.
So, to summarize those results, his
average points per game or mean
was 22.7.
The variance standard deviation squared
was that 92.21, it was the sum of squared
deviations divided by n.
For short, we're going to call that sum of
squares divided by n.
If we take the square root of that, then
we get the standard deviation, 9.6.
By taking the square root, that brings us
back to the units that we started in.
Remember, we had to square everything to
get rid of sine,
when we went from deviation scores to
square of deviation scores.
So this last step, we take the square
root,
that brings us back to the units we we
in, which is points per game.
What this is saying is on average, he was
fluctuating about 10 points per game.
Is that really accurate?
Not really.
He wasn't really fluctuating about ten
points per
game, once he had the opportunity to
start.
Right?
The standard deviation is 9.6, because I
included
that one game where he only scored 2
points.
He didn't start that game.
If we don't include that, then his
standard deviation will go down.
before I do that, I just want to point out
some notation.
Again, I'm going to use M for mean,
SD for standard deviation, SD squared for
variance.
It's also known as mean squares for the
mean sum of squares, er, mean squared
deviations.
so mean squares, sum of squares, these are
important definitions to know
going forward.
but again, let's look at Lin, and compare
him to one of the top stars in the NBA,
Kobe Bryant.
I guess after this year, I might have to
do LeBron James.
But I just can't, I don't like him.
I'm not really a big fan of Kobe either,
but I'm sticking with Kobe.
let's compare Jeremy Lin during that time
in the winter of 2012 to what Kobe Bryant
was doing during that time in the winter
of 2012.
Kobe Bryant was the leading scorer at the
time in the League.
So, if we take the 10 games that I just
looked at for Jeremy Lin and we compare 10
games from Kobe Bryant during that same
stretch of time.
This is R output.
You're now familiar with this after going
through the
first lab, and hopefully you're working on
the first homework.
what you see is, here's the mean for Lin,
and here's the mean for Bryant.
so Jeremy Lin was averaging 22.7.
We just showed you how to calculate that
by hand.
You won't have to do that, just plug it
into R.
R will give you the mean.
It's 22.7.
he wasn't really doing quite as well as
Kobe Bryant.
Kobe Bryant was averaging 26.4 points per
game.
but if we look at a measure of variation.
So, let's
look at the measure of standard deviation.
as we saw in our hand calculations,
Jeremy Lin's standard deviation's about 10
points per game, whereas Kobe
Bryant's is only about 7 and a half points
per game.
But again, that's because I included that
one game where he had
just two points in that game, and he
didn't start that game.
So, let's compare Kobe Bryant and Jeremy
Lin if I drop that one out.
So here's the R output if we just look
at 9 games during that stretch.
And in these 9 games, Jeremy Lin started
all 9 games.
Now, he's doing almost as well as Kobe
Bryant, 25 points per games versus 26.6.
And his variability is about the same.
So now,
it's about 7 and a half to about 7.8.
He's actually more consistent than Kobe
Bryant across those 9 games,
in that one little stretch of time in the
winter of 2012.
It was wonderful back then for us, us
Knicks fans it didn't last long.
but that's the point of, of this
little illustration, is to look summary
statistics.
We can get something that's very common we
know about,
is the average or mean, but we can also
look at variability.
How consistent are the scores in a
distribution, or how variable are
the scores in a distribution.
And that's the point
of calculating standard deviation and
variance.
so to review this entire lecture.
the point of summary
statistics is, we can't always show our
audience.
Or when we're writing things, writing up
research for a, a publication in a
journal or an article in a newspaper, or
on a website.
we can't show all of those histograms for
all our variables.
It just become too much information for
the audience to digest.
So, we often
want to just give some talking points,
some summary statistics.
And the most common summary statistics are
measures of central tendency.
And the most common one of those is the
mean or average,
but you might want to do median in the
case of extremely skewed distributions.
but it's also really important as you
start getting into statistics and really
important for
the rest of this course, to think beyond
just the mean or measures of central
tendency and think about measures of
variability.
Variance is going to be a really important
concept as we move forward.
So it's important that you understand
how to calculate standard deviation and
variance.
And it's important that you understand
conceptually what standard, deviation
and mean, and what they convey.
Finally, it's important
that you know the following formulas and
that you can just do these by hand.
Of course, we're going to do all our
calculations using the R software.
it's less error-prone and a lot faster
and, and convenient.
Right?
But you should just know how to do these
off the top of your head.
So, again, hopefully this one was review.
If it's not, just give yourselves some
practice on it.
so the mean is just the sum of all the
scores divided by the number of scores.
And then, I gave you this one formula for
standard deviation and variance.
this first one is used for descriptive
statistics.
And that's still all we're dealing with is
descriptive statistics.
We're just describing what's going on in a
sample.
Next week, when we move to inferential
statistics, we're going to use a slightly
different
formula for variance and standard
deviation,
where we'll divide by n minus 1.
And we'll talk about that when we go into
inferential statistics.
And if you are very sharp, you will notice
that the standard deviation I calculated
by hand for Jeremy
Lin's points for gain was not exactly the
same as
the standard deviation that we saw in the
R output.
And that's because I used the formula for
descriptive
statistics, I divided by n because that's
all I was doing, was descriptive.
But the default in R is to use
the inferential formula, dividing by n
minus 1.
And that's why there's that slight
discrepancy, if you picked up on it.
and that's the end of that segment.