Hi, welcome back, we're up to lecture 6,
segment 2.
This lecture is all about measurement
issues.
In the first segment we talked about
reliability, in
the second segment, we're going to talk
about validity.
So there's a lot to talk about when
talking about the validity of a construct.
First of all we have to talk about what is
a construct?
How do we operationalize it?
That sounds like a mouthful.
And then they're a lot of ways to access
validity and I'll
walk you through each one of these just
with one quick example.
there are actually entire courses on
measurement
theory that cover reliability and
validity.
So to cover all of this in just one
lecture is a bit difficult.
But again, I think it's critical to expose
you to these issues in an introductory
statistics course.
So, what is a construct?
Again, I'm coming at statistics
from the social sciences, rather than say,
like from mathematics,
where they would worry less about, issues
like this.
the construct, a simple way to define it,
is it's an
ideal object that's not directly
observable, as opposed to real objects.
So, Remember back when I talked about
variables and constants.
It's like comparing apples and gravity.
[LAUGH]
apples are real objects we can measure the
size, the weight, the type and so on.
They're, they're very easy to measure.
we don't eat a construct, an abstract
construct of apple.
but in the social sciences, we do
Deal with very fuzzy and abstract
constructs all
the time, perhaps the most famous one
is intelligence; for over a 100 years
researchers
have been arguing about what intelligence
really
means, how should we really access it.
That construct intelligence Is one of the
most famous
and one of the most controversial, but
that's a construct.
The personality traits are also a
construct.
One of the most important things for
statistics
and to do empirical research is to
operationalize a construct.
So, first define the construct but then
come
up of some way to quantify that construct.
So that's the process of opera,
operationalization.
How do we operationalize a const, a
construct.
You define it to make it observable
and quantifiable so, for example,
intelligence tests.
So we have this idea that
there's something called intelligence and
that came of observations
of children in classroom, some tended to,
to do better across the board than others.
and then intelligence tests were
developed to operationalize that construct
intelligence.
Again there's a lot of controversy around
how that's done but
that's the process of defining a construct
and then operationalizing it.
So then we can do empirical research.
We can can data and do our statistics.
So how do we evaluate the validity of a
construct.
Turns out there are sort of four main
categories
to look at when you are looking at
construct validity.
First is content validity.
Then the next two sort of go hand in
hand, convergent and divergent validity,
and then finally nomological validity.
So to illustrate those four types of
validity, I'm going to take a very
simple example that's not very
controversial
and move away from the intelligence test.
But related.
let's look at verbal ability in young
children.
This is a construct.
It's a very important construct for
academic achievement.
as you're raising your children, you want
them to learn how to read.
You want them to build their vocabulary.
This leads to their verbal ability, a
construct
that cognitive psychologists And
educational psychologists
and developmental psychologists use quite
often.
So there's our construct, verbal ability.
How might we operationalize that?
Well, one way is just to develop a
vocabulary test.
We could come up with a vocabulary test,
administer it
to a bunch of children, and see how they
do.
Does it assess Their verbal ability in a
valid way.
Well, how will we determine if it's valid.
Well first, look at content validity.
Content validity is very simple.
It's just
[INAUDIBLE]
.
Look at the test.
Does this look like It's a vocabulary test
that's appropriate for this population,
this sample of children.
So is it a collection of words that these
children should know, some of them, not
all of them.
We wouldn't give a vocabulary test in
German to students in Brazil.
Alright, that wouldn't have content
validity.
and we wouldn't give a vocabulary test
that's
appropriate for say, you know, 12 year old
children to four year old children because
they
wouldn't get any of them right most
likely.
So that would be lacking in just face
validity or content validity.
So that's a really simple one.
The next two go hand in hand, convergent
and divergent validity.
So the idea of convergent validity is
scores on this test,
however I've operationalized the construct
this
vocabulary test, scores on the vocabulary
test Should correlate well with other
established measures of the same
construct.
So, for example, if we have a measure of
reading comprehension, that
we know is reliable and valid and well
accepted by educators, teachers, parents.
And then we administer our new vocabulary
test.
And scores on the vocabulary test are
correlated with scores on the
reading comprehension test, then that
indicates
to us some level of convergent validity.
The scores are converging on other
measures of this construct, verbal
ability.
But it's not enough to just have
convergent validity.
And sadly, a lot of researchers just stop
there.
They try to get their convergent validity,
and then they stop.
What's critical is to show the flip side.
You gotta have divergent validity along
with your convergent validity so
you also have to show that your measure
of, of verbal ability.
Say, your vocabulary test.
You also have to show that it correlates
less well with some other ability.
Or correlates less well with things that
it just shouldn't correlate with.
Say, height, right?
just any, just, if, if there's any
assessment that
you can look at, that it should be
correlated
at 0 with, then you should test that, and
that would give you some evidence for
divergent validating.
So if you see a stronger correlation
between the vocabulary test and reading
comprehension
than you do between the vocabulary test
and some measure of spatial ability, for
example,
that would illustrate some divergent
validity.
So it's correlating with the things it
should
and not correlating with the things that
it shouldn't.
Convergent validity and divergent
validity.
Finally, there's nomological validity
which is
more like, meta validity if you will.
[LAUGH]
the scores on the test, say this
vocabulary test say they should be
consistent with more general theories that
exist in related fields of research.
So, for example, if we're looking at
verbal ability in children.
Then scores on the test should be
consistent with
what we know about developmental
psychology, cognitive psychology and
neuroscience.
For example
a child with neural damage or a disease to
a particular
brain region that is known to be important
for the development of
verbal ability Those children should score
less well on this test
of vocabulary if it is indeed a valid
measure of that construct.
That fits in with broader theories and its
consistent with convergent.
Evidence,
so it fits with normological concepts or
theories and that's why it's called
normological validity.
Sort of a broader approach to validity.
Again, which sadly in the realm of Social
Sciences is not addressed enough in in my
opinion.
so, I want to sum up the first two
segments
here, reliability and validity, because
they go hand in hand.
And, as I said, there are actually entire
courses devoted to measurement theory.
When I was a graduate student, I took an
entire semester course, just on
measurement and reliability and validity.
It's very common in cognitive psychology.
It's even more common in developmental
psychology, and particularly
educational psychology.
It's really important to know that you
have reliable and valid measurements and
valid constructs.
so the important things to take away are
this
broad theory of classical tests theory, or
true score theory.
Then the different ways to get reliability
estimates.
And then the different ways to assess
validity
of a construct.