Hi, and welcome to Statistics one: Lab
three.
The goals for this week's lab, are, first,
we'll
read a data file into R, and print summary
statistics.
Just as we did last week in lab two.
But since one of the main topics this
weeks is corr-, this week, is correlation.
We will run a bunch of correlation
analysis in
R and we'll examine relationships among
variables using scatter
plots and scatter plot matrices.
So, you'll see for this lab that I'm using
the same data set that I used for lab two.
That will keep things simple and Hopefully
this lab will
be a little shorter than last week as a
result.
So again it's the example investigating
the effects of sports related concussion.
using this online assessment tool called
Impact.
The one change I made to the data set is I
gave the variable
name sort of Shorter labels.
You'll see that comes in handy when we're
looking
at the correlation matrices, and the
scatter, scatter plot matrices.
So again, at the beginning, you should
always
make sure you, you're in the right working
directory.
So you can use get WD for get your working
Or set WD for set.
Your working directory.
I have all these commented out.
Because I, I have that done already.
And,
again, you might have to install some new
packages for this lab.
particularly G Clus and RGL.
So I already did that.
I don't want to waste the time in lab to
do that.
But you might want to pause and install
those packages.
G Clus and RGL.
Okay.
of course, you still need to load those
packages so, I still need to do that.
I'll load the packages and
I'll read the data into a data frame
called Impact.
And, I didn't get any errors, so that
looks good.
I might want to view the data or edit the
data, just to make sure it's there.
you can use this view function but, I
know that it doesn't work on all operating
systems.
So, try it but if it doesn't work you,
you can use edit, that should work in any
operating.
any machine, any operating system.
[NOISE]
So, here you see the data, it looks just
like last week,
we have a bunch a athletes who are in a
control condition.
A bump, a bunch of athletes who are in
concussed condition.
We have verbal memory and this is at time
on our baseline, visual memory,
visual motor speed, reaction time, impulse
control, total symptom score.
And then, all those measures, again, at
time two or retest.
Again, for the
controls, that's just test retest.
So, you'll see that we can use those
as sort of est-, to get estimates of
reliability.
and of course, the main purpose of this
type
of research would be to look in the
concuss group.
And see what happens as you go from.
Time one baseline to the test after an
injury.
Okay.
So let's go back to the script.
Just as we did last week.
We could just print some summary
statistics just to make sure
we have the data we think we have and,
there we go.
I print, do the desrcibe function on the
impact data frame and I have
40 subjects or 40 athletes in this data
file and there's all my variables.
And summary statistics, okay, this is sort
of we
covered last week, but again we will do
this probably
every lab just to or reinforce these,
these basic concepts.
And again we could look at the summary
statistics by conditions, so if I use the
function describe by the data frame impact
then impact By condition.
[NOISE]
Then I'll get on my summary statistics for
the concussed group and a control group
separately.
Okay, now let's get to the main topic of
this week- correlation analysis.
So the main function is just COR core and
what I'm doing this
first analysis is just Look at
the correlations among all the baseline
measures.
So what I'm going to put in to R
is cor(impact[3:8]).
And that's because the base line measures
are
in columns three to eight in the data
frame.
Remember, columns one and two were subject
number and condition.
So, the, the actual variables that we
want to correlate don't start until column
three.
So let's just do that.
And here we go.
We have.
A correlation matrix.
And this first number here, this shows us
the correlation
or little r, which we talked about in the
lecture.
between verbal memory at baseline and
visual memory at baseline.
So it's about.
.
38 .
it's, so it's a little bit low.
I, I would expect it to be a little
higher than that, but it's positive so
that That suggests
that verbal memory and visual memory, as
assessed online via Impact has some
reliability.
Right?
Because, if it didn't have any
reliability,
it would be able to correlate with
anything.
And two, it has some validity because
it's, it's showing convergence with
another memory measure.
Of course, could be a little better.
and again the sample size here is a little
low.
We would, we would probably want a some
more athletes,
but I just want to use the same data set
we used last week.
So let's go back to the script.
That correlation matrix looked a little
noisy because there's so
many Decimal places, so let me just use
this round function.
It's sort of standard to look at
correlations just to two
decimal places, so I'm just going to round
to two decimal places.
And now, let me bring that up a little
here's my correlation matrix.
Now it's a little bit easier to read.
There's that.
.
38 .
And, notice that visual motor speed
doesn't really correlate
with verbal memory, but it does with
visual memory.
So that makes sense cause it's visual
motor speed.
Also notice that it's negative.
And that's because this, this speed
measure
was measured in reaction time.
So, if you have better memory, you're
scoring
higher on the memory test, but if you're
faster, meaning that you're better at that
task
then you have a lower value cause it's
speed.
That's why there's a negative corrolation
there.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Okay.
Now, we're going to create two subsets.
One for the control group, and one for the
concussed group.
So that we can do correlation analyses
within those groups.
So, again, I'm going to use the subset
function on impact.
And if impact if the second column.
If the value in there equals control I'll
set that, that athlete
or that row into the control data frame,
and same with concussed.
And there they are.
Okay.
So now let's do a correlation analysis of
the control group.
All of the measures, so this is both
baseline and retest.
So, here's this nice big correlation
matrix, it's a 12 by 12.
And again, one thing that I maybe should
have pointed out to you if you're new
to correlation matrices, the diagonal is
always going to be ones, right?
Because that's each variable correlated
with itself.
and, and this matrix every correlation
matrix
is symmetrical so the values below the
diagonal
are same as the values above the
diagonal.so here is he correlation between
verbal memory and visual memory now we are
getting nice strong positive correlation.
but what I mean by symmetrical is you see.
69 here.
It's also up here.
And negative 27 is here, negative 27 is
here.
so you only have to look really below the
diagonal to look at all the correlations.
But what's interesting in, in this data
frame
in particular is these are the control
subjects.
So they just perform this assessment tool.
At baseline and then sometime later at
retest.
So if we look at the correlation between
verbal memory at time one and verbal
memory at time two we could think of
that as a test, retest reliability of
precedent.
So it's.
67 .
Which is okay,
it's not bad.
The visual memory is a little bit better.
visual, visual motor speed is not as
great.
And then look at this one the reaction
time measure, it's remarkable.
It's rare that you get exactly zero.
The reaction time measure does not look
reliable at all.
Alright, impulse control really good.
And total symptom score not bad.
So these reliability estimates are for
the most part good except for this guy.
but remember, the, there is only 20
athletes in the
control group so there might be some
sampling error so don't,
I don't want to making these strong claims
about that
website impact based on these 20,
subjects, or 20 athletes, right.
this is just to illustrate the idea of
correlations and
the idea of tests, retests reliability.
So now let's look at the concussed
athletes.
Look at the concussed athletes.
All the measures again, I get a 12 by 12
matrix.
All the diagonals are ones.
It's symmetrical.
now we can't really think of these as test
retest reliability estimates.
Because they were concussed in between.
so some of them are still high.
but it's hard to know you know what those
correlations mean.
I just wanted to run it so we could see
the same
thing that we saw for the control group.
So lets go back to the script so beyond
correlations of just the
main measures I thought we could do
something a little bit more then that.
and this will also prepare you for the
next assignment because
we'll ask you to do things like this in
the next assignment.
So let's let's propose a question Say,
does the
baseline impulse control of an athlete
predict their memory impairment after a
concussion?
So maybe athletes who are more impulsive
are going to engage
in a more aggressive style of play, make
themselves more susceptible.
To sort of more dangerous plays and sort
of maybe more severe concussions which
might then result in a worse overall
memory apparent, impairment.
Again, I'm, I'm sort of making this up
just for the lab.
so that we can do some more with the data
than just look at correlations along the
measures that were provided.
So the first thing we need to do is
let's just get a composite measure of
memory impairement.
So we'll
combine verbal and visual.
So first what I am going to do is in the
concussed group I am going to
create a new variable called verbal impair
for verbal memory impairment, and I am
just
going to get that by taking their verbal
memory score at base line and subtracting
their
verbal memory score after an injury Then
I'll do the same thing for visual memory.
And then I'll combine those
by averaging them.
To get an overall measure of memory
impairment, called memory impair.
By adding those two impairment measures
and dividing by two.
That just give me the average Or composite
measure of memory impairment.
Then what I'll do is I'll correlate that
measure, that
new variable that we created, with impulse
control at timeline.
And let's see what happens
[SOUND]
we get a correlation of about 0.229 or
0.23 So there's
a slight positive correlation, it's not
that strong.
but it does look like there's some
relationship perhaps.
again the, the sample size is a little
small.
but it does suggest that those with sort
of higher scores on impulse control show
greater memory impairment.
Again, but that correlation's a little bit
low.
you might want to know, is
that correlation significant, like
statistically significant?
And that's exactly what we'll cover next
week.
So in next week's lectures you can, start
to
think about whether certain correlations
are statistically significant or not.
it depends on the sample size and it
depends
on the variability and you will see that
in next weeks lecture and next weeks lab.
o.k.
now lets go to scatterfox and this is the
way to visualize our correlations
or visualize relationships among variables
and I put in a note here.
There are a lot of scatter plot functions.
And they're in lots of different packages.
I tried to keep this simple, so that we
wouldn't have to download
too many packages.
but you'll see there's a lot of fun things
you can do with scatter plots.
And there's a lot of advanced options.
So feel free to explore around, and if you
find some
interesting things feel free to share them
in the discussion forums.
But let's start with the most basic plot,
it's just the plot function, and I'm just
going to plot verbal memory and visual
memory at
time one, because those showed that
positive correlation.
And, here's the scatter plot.
Let me make it a little bigger.
so here's visual memory on the x-axis, and
verbal memory on the y-axis.
And if you eyeball it, it looks like
overall, there's a slight positive.
Correlation.
but we can do better than eyeball it.
Let's put a line, on that scatter plot,
called the regression line.
Again, this is the topic for next week.
An that'll, characterize that
relationship.
Yep, I have to do the plot again.
There we go so now what the regression
line is and we'll talk about
this in detail in lecture next week and
you will do it again in lab
next week, what this line does is
it minimizes the distance between each dot
and
the line and that's called ordinary lease
squares regression which we'll get into
next week.
It also allows me to predict
scores, based, predict scores on the y
access based on scores on the x access.
So if you get a really high score of
visual memory then say around 90 here.
I can go up to the regression line and
then over.
Then I would predict you to get about you
know almost to 95 on the verbal memory.
task.
So that's what the regression line is used
for.
If you
see it like this.
This nice positive slope.
that means there's a positive correlation.
If it was completely flat, that means
there'd be a correlation of zero.
And if it was going the other way, a
negative slope.
That means there'd be a negative
correlation.
Okay, let's move on to scatter plot
matrices.
So, we have a lot of measures in this data
set, so I might want to
visualize all the relationships at once in
a matrix, just like
we did with the correlation matrix, but
now with scatter plots.
So let me run this.
And now I have what's called a scatter
plot matrix.
So you can see its all my measures, let me
make it a little bigger.
okay so I have verbal memory at time one,
visual memory at time one visual motor
speed, reaction time and symptoms.
so here's that, that one scatter plot that
we looked at between verbal verbal
memory and visual memory but this shows me
all of the relationships at baseline.
One thing to notice is down here symptom
score, why are all
these dots just sitting right on the
bottom of the graph, well that's
because it's symptom score at baseline,
most athletes are scoring zero, they're
not showing any symptoms of a concussion
because it's baseline and they're healthy.
Okay, we can do, as I said there's a lot
of things
we could do, I'll show you one, or two
more fancy things.
So, I'm going to run this whole chunk of
code and then I'll walk you through it.
but what this will do is give us a scatter
plot matrix that's colored and it will
order the the variables in the scatter
plot by magnitude so lets take
a look, check that out, its very cool I am
going to make
it big, okay so again this is just a
baseline so you
saw that verbal memory and visual memory
those are the two strongest
ones, so puts those together with the sort
of A purple color.
Because that's a stronger correlation.
And then, symptoms is way out here on the
periphery, because it
doesn't correlate with anything at time
one.
because there's, there's no variance.
Again, if you don't have variance, you
can't get covariance.
Alright?
So that's just sort of a neat thing you
can do.
Again, there are many other options.
feel free to play with her.
Or search around the internet for
different options for scatter plot
matrices.
one more thing I want to do.
Is show you scatter plots in 3D.
So,
we could look at just, you know, the
relationship
between two variables, like verbal memory
and visual memory.
And.
In a two dimensional scatter plot and
that's standard, but R has lots
of advanced graphics so why not
take advantage of these three dimensional
plots.
So let's look at visual memory, verbal
memory and symptom score
all at baseline but in a three dimensional
plot And you
will see that this one is interactive, so
you see it opens up if I click
on it and hold my mouse down, then I can
move it around and we can visualize three
dimensional relationships, so if I hold it
just like this It looks just like the 2D
scatter plot we just did, so visual memory
on the X axis, verbal memory on the Y but
I can spin it, alright and if I spin it
this way, we can spin a little more what
you can
see is now we are going left to right here
You don't see any dots right their all
along the left.
That's because remember symptom score all
the
athletes are scoring around zero at
baseline.
So that's why I started with this one so
you can sort of get a feel for it.
and again what I am doing is I am just
holding down my mouse and
I am sort of dragging it around, so lets
just do one more and that
it will be the end of this lab so now lets
do this same three measures but
at time two so that we don't have just all
zeros for symptom score.
So now again let me just here it is that
visual memory, verbal memory in 2D.
But if I can sort of drag it around, drag
it this way,
now you see In this other dimension you
see there are symptom scores
sort of all over the place, so because
this is after concussion, so
its pretty cool you can play around with
that, you can add color
again you can add regression lines if you
like
so feel free to play with that more But
this is about all you'll need, for now to
understand correlations and scatter plots
and to do assignment three.
So, good luck on that and I will talk to
you next week in lab four.