Hi, and welcome to Statistics One lab
four.
The goals of today's lab are to read
a data file into R, which we've done
already.
Again, print summary statistics, which
we've done.
We'll do correlation analyses which we
covered last week but then we'll
also do regression analyses, which is the
main topic of this week.
And you'll see that we'll do, first
we'll do a regression analyses yielding
unstandardized
regression coefficients.
And then we'll do a regression
analysis giving us the standardized
regression coefficients.
And you'll see it's really simple
manipulation to go from unstandardized to
standardized.
And the example this week is a little
different it's actually much simpler,
there's just three variables.
So, the example is, a correlational study
investigating predictors of physical
endurance in healthy adults.
So, the outcome variable, y, is physical
endurance.
And you'll see that it's just on an
arbitrary scale, it's measured from zero
to 60.
And the predictors, the x variables, are
age and number of years
that the person has active, has been
actively engaged in exercise or sports.
You'll see that the sample, which consists
of 200 people, consists of people who are
pretty active.
So we'll see that when we look at the
summary statistics.
Again I've commented, commented out these,
these lines of code because I know I'm
in the right working directory but just
make sure you're in the right working
directory.
Make sure your data file is spelled
correctly, there's
been a lot of problems just downloading
data files.
just make sure you're,
you're, you're spelling your data file
correctly.
Make sure you're downloading it into your
working directory.
the only package we'll need for this lab
is the psych package.
So, most of you should have that installed
already.
but if you don't, if you're joining the
class late you need to install the psych
package.
Again, I've commented that out because
I've already done it.
Okay, so let's go.
I start by loading
the psych library and then I'm going to
read in the data
file from that text file into a data frame
called PE.
I'm hitting Cmd+Return, and then Cmd+1 to
go back to the console
and good, it looks like there's no errors.
So let me just,
let me just look at it.
I'll use the view, sorry, I'll use
the edit function edit PE, you can use the
view function if you like.
let me execute that, and the R Editor
comes up.
if you're working in R studio you would
have already seen this.
this is just a participant ID number which
is common
just give people an arbitrary
identification number their age in years.
Active years refers to the number of years
that they've
been actively engaged in sports or in
exercise.
And endurance again, is the score on an
arbitrary scale
zero to 60 where higher scores indi,
indicate greater endurance.
So now, let's move down through the code
for
this lab and let's look at some summary
statistics.
Give us an idea of what's in these
variables.
So here are the summary statistics.
You see that we have 200 subjects in, or
participants if you like, in this in this
sample.
And notice I didn't change participant ID
to a factor, I left
it in there as integer, so R's reading
that in as an integer.
if you don't want that in your summary
statistics table you
could change that to a factor which we did
last week.
so technically
I should, I should get that out of there.
but let's look at age, the mean age in
this sample's about 49 and a half years
old.
as I said, notice that this, this
sample they're pretty healthy, athletic
physically fit bunch.
There, they've been on average, actively
engaged in sports or
physical fitness for 10.6 years, ten and a
half years.
[LAUGH]
at least in the US that's, that's pretty
atypical for a group of 200, 200 adults.
so that will also help to explain some of
the odd correlations
that you're about to see which is why I am
pointing it out.
and they're average endurance score again,
the scale you'll
see the minimum is three and the maximum
is 55.
the scale's
an arbitrary scale that we picked again,
we just made up data for this.
it's from zero to 60 with higher scores
indicating greater endurance.
So, let's go back to the script and let's
run a correlation analysis just on those
three variables.
So I'm doing core(PE that's the data frame
where the data are now.
And I'm doing [2:4
because I don't want to put participant ID
in there, I just want the three main
variables.
So I'll execute that.
And here are the correlations.
so the correlation between age and
active years is positive, it's 0.33,
approximately.
so the older you are, the more opportunity
you've had to
be engaged in to be actively engaged in
sports, so that's why that's positive.
And you'll notice that physical endurance
is not
correlated with age, if anything it's
negatively correlated.
again, you might think that's a little
odd.
you would expect a, a sort of stronger
negative correlation, right.
Because, as you go up in age, you should
be going down in physical endurance.
But as I said, this is a sort of unique
sample because they're very active the
average again, for active years was over
ten,
it's like ten and a half, almost eleven.
and you'll see, that's, that's accounting
for this, this
lack of correlation here between age and
physical endurance.
so then we have a correlation between
active years and endurance, as you would
expect.
So, the more people are engaged in, in
active exercise or sports the better their
physical endurance.
So let's go back to the script.
as we run larger
correlation matrices, I think we did this
last week I like to use
the round function, makes it a little
cleaner, so, I just put round around
[LAUGH]
that line of code.
and then that'll just give me two decimal
places so just looks a little cleaner.
we could also run the function cor.test
now that you've
been exposed to this idea of null
hypothesis significance testing.
I didn't run this last week in lab because
we hadn't really encountered the idea of
significance testing yet.
we're going to cover this idea a lot more
next week
when we talk about the central limit
theorem in particular.
but we could, for each of these, we could
just run a null
hypothesis significance test.
So that correlation between age and active
years,
it was about 0.33, is it statistically
significant?
Well if I run core.test R will tell me.
So you can execute that one line of code,
go back to the console, and
you'll see that R gives me this output
it says, we're running a Pearson's
product-moment correlation,
that's what core.test gives as the
default.
it then gives me a t value of 4.9.
What's called degrees of
freedom is DF, it's 198, it's the number
of subjects minus 2.
and again, we'll talk a lot about why it's
that number
next week and, and how you get this exact
p value.
This p value is, this is stated in
significant digits, so this is like
0.000001 so
it's very, very low.
which means we would reject the null
hypothesis
that there's no relationship between age
and active
years, that says here the true correlation
is
not equal to zero is the alternative
hypothesis.
it also gives a confidence interval, which
we'll talk about next week.
So instead of reporting just the estimated
correlation,
remember this is an estimate of the true
population correlation based on this
sample, some statisticians suggest that we
should report confidence intervals.
so this is our 95% confidence interval for
this correlation, it's about 0.2 to 0.45.
you see that 0.33 sits right in the middle
of that interval.
So this, we'll cover next week.
the correlation coefficient is known
as a point estimate and this is known as
an interval estimate.
This is our best estimate of what the
true population correlation is between age
and active years.
Remember, there's always going to be some
error associated with just a
point estimate, this 0.33 because there's
always some degree of sampling error.
Well, how much sampling error do, can we,
can we expect?
Well, we try to estimate that
by calculating standard error.
And that's how this interval is
calculated, it's
based on how much standard error we have.
Remember, standard error is largely
determined by sample size.
but I'm getting ahead of myself, we'll
talk more about all of that next week.
Let's go back to the script.
we could do that cor.test for each of the
other correlations.
I'll do it for endurance and active years
and
endurance and age.
And what we see is
up here, this is for endurance and active
years, again we get this really
pretty high t value, 4.86, and a very low
p value.
that means that the probability of
obtaining this correlation given
the assumption that the null hypothesis is
true, is very low,
that's what that p value means.
Again, we're going to get into this more
next week.
again, it's about the same magnitude as
the, the one above it.
And then of course, this one's not going
to be significant, right.
So this one is negative 0.08, it's very
close to zero, so the
t value is, is pretty low, it's negative
now because we have a negative
correlation, so it's negative 1.12, say.
and the p value is 0.23, so, that's not a
very low p value.
to reject the null hypothesis we typically
want a p
value less than say, 0.05 is a typical cut
off value.
so here we would retain the null
hypothesis.
And we could, we don't claim here, or
we wouldn't claim here that there's a
significant correlation.
Obviously, in this case it's, it's so
close to zero.
Okay, let's go
back to the stri, script.
And just to be sure that we're not
violating any assumptions
here because you might look at those
correlations and say, well
that's weird why do we have, you know, no,
there's no
correlation between age and physical
endurance, that doesn't make much sense.
let's just look at our our distributions.
So we'll just run some histograms and look
at the distributions.
So here's age we have a, a large range
from
like early 20s all the way up to around
80.
These two, there's two people up here
right
around 80, who, they're, they're almost
like outliers.
We might want to consider dropping them
out of the sample
but they're not so extreme that I'd, that
I'll drop them out.
And they're not going to really affect
the, the outcome too much.
active years looks a little bit positively
skewed, right, which
is not, not unusual for that kind of a
measure.
Then the endurance looks like a really
nice normal distribution.
So there's nothing too unusual about these
distributions, they look
pretty normal, we've got a little bit of a
positive skew.
Maybe a couple of,
a couple of data points that are close
to being outliers here but nothing too
extreme.
so let's go ahead and run the regression
analyses, that's, those look good enough.
so let's run first, let's run a regression
analysis predicting endurance from age.
Remember there's no correlation between
endurance and
age, so we shouldn't get a significant
regression
coefficient, but let's run the model
anyway, just to be sure.
So, I'm going to call this Model One.
I'm using the function lm, that's for
linear model, because
right now we're assuming linear
relationship between invariance and age.
And we can check that in scatter plot.
I'm using the function summary, just to
give me the output that's associated with
that model, that'll give us the regression
constant and the regression coefficient
for age
when predicting endurance.
And you'll see it'll give us a bunch of
other things, like model r squared, and so
on.
So let me just run that.
So here's the output, I ran this Model One
and here's summary Model One.
it gives us a range of residuals, which
I'll
actually show you on a plot in a moment.
But this is the most important piece of
the output right
here and what you'll typically look to
when you do regression
analysis, which you'll do for the next
assignment and the next
couple weeks when we do multiple
regression when we put in more
than one predictor.
it gives us our estimates, these are the
coefficients.
So this right here is the intercept, or in
my lecture notes this was b sub zero in
the regression equation, it's just
the predicted score on y when x is zero.
So, if someone had
an age of zero we would predict they would
score
30.8 on this arbitrary scale.
Again, age doesn't really correlate with
endurance
so 30 should be around the average,
I can't remember what the average was, but
it should be somewhere near there.
and we see is the estimate for
the regression coefficient for age
predicting endurance
is negative 0.08.
it's standard error is 0.07 that's just
how
much of a relationship should we expect
just due
to chance, so it's about the same as, as,
you know, the actual coefficient, so it's
not significant.
Another thing to look for is this multiple
r squared.
So, in this case, it's just, literally, r
squared, the correlation squared.
but when we get into multiple regression,
you'll see that this is the, this is the
proportion of variance in y explained by x
or x's, all the predictors.
So, it's the proportion of variance of, in
y explained by the model.
So, you'll see that it's 0.01, only 1%
of the variance in endurance is explained
by age.
They're just not related
in this sample.
Let's look at another example.
let me just do the scatter plot to show
you what it looks like, so there's the
scatter plot.
y or, on the y axis I have endurance, on
the x axis I have age.
And you see it's almost a flat line, it's
just
a very slight negative slope, because the
correlation was negative 0.08.
but basically no relationship going on
there.
Now, let's look at two variables that
are correlated, so active years, predicted
endurance.
So let's, in model two, let's again use
that lm
function but now let's look at a variable
that predicts endurance.
So now when we look at the summary, now
let me go down
to the coefficients, this is really what
we want to look at, right?
now you'll see that the predicted score on
y
when x is zero, now is much lower, right?
Because if you have not, if you have zero
active years then
you're going to, I'm going to predict that
you
have a much lower score on the endurance
scale.
And here is the unstandardized regression
coefficient, okay.
Remember, this is unstandardized, so you
can't really
think of this in terms of like
correlation.
this is just the, for every one unit
change in
active years, so for every one more active
year, it's the
predicted change in the endurance scale,
so, it's almost a one to one.
So, for every one more active year I'm
going to put a 0.75 not quite one.
one more, one point higher on that
endurance scale.
And is that a statistically significant
relationship?
Well, yes because this t value,
which is just the unstandardized
regression coefficient,
0.7552 divided by the standard error,
0.1553, that's the t value
and it corresponds to a p value of like
0.000002,
[LAUGH]
so really, really low.
so, yes I would reject the null hypothesis
that there's no relationship.
and we could conclude that there's a
statistically significant
relationship between active years and
endurance, not very surprising.
The other thing I want to look at here is
the multiple r squared.
You see now we're explaining about 11% of
the variance and endurance just from
active years.
Okay, let's go back to the script.
we can visualize that in a plot.
And here’s the scatter plot.
Looking at endurance as
a function of active years and you see
there's this nice, positive slope, okay.
Okay.
Now in model three I'm actually going to
do technically a multiple regression.
I know we haven't really gotten into the
heart of multiple regression
yet but just to show you why this, this
example is interesting
and, and what can happen with multiple
regression, let's put both age and
active years in the regression equation
together and predict endurance from that.
And, you'll see
this is pretty interesting.
So now let me again, direct you to the
coefficients table.
Now if we look at age we get relationship
of negative,
a slope of negative 0.222 or 0.223.
And but notice now there is now the t
value is negative three and the p value is
0.002.
So now
again, using a cut off of 0.05 and, and
we'll talk next week when we talk about
central limit
theorem and sampling distributions, why we
use the cut-off
of 0.05 but it's, it's a very low p value.
So the probability of getting this slope
and this t value, the probability of
obtaining those values given the
assumption that
there's no relat, relationship between age
and endurance,
again that's the null hypothesis.
The probability of that happening, given
the assumption of the
null, is really really low, so I reject
the null.
And now we can claim that there
is a statistically significant
relationship between age and
endurance and it's because we've taken
into account
active years which is also a significant
predictor.
So now, both of them are significantly
predicting endurance.
And if we go down to the model, r squared,
you can see
we're doing a lot better now by putting in
age and the active
years together, we're accounting for about
15% of the variants in the outcome.
Whereas, if we go back up to our old
output, if we just used active years,
and we didn't put in age, we were only
accounting for about 11% of the variance.
So, the model gets better by putting in
both age and active years together.
And that's the power of multiple
regression, which we're going to talk
a lot about in the next next
two weeks we'll be talking about multiple
regression.
Okay, so let's go back to the script.
we can't visualize that in one scatter
plot if we had both age and physical
endurance, so what we're going to do to
visualize model three in just
one scatter plot, and I did this in the
lecture, we could save the
predicted scores.
Because another way to think of that, that
model r squared is it's the correlation
between the predicted scores and the
actual observed scores on y squared.
So a way to do that in R, and this is a
really handy function,
the fitted function, that will give me the
predicted scores from the model.
So I'm going to create
a new variable called predicted in my data
frame PE
and I'm going to just put the predicted
scores there.
Then, I'll plot the predicted scores
against endurance.
And now you see the slope is, it's
probably
hard to tell, I should have put them maybe
right
next to each other, this slope is even a
little bit stronger than the slope in the
previous plot.
just using active years to predict
endurance, right.
Because the r squared was a little higher,
so this is just
the predicted scores from model three
predicting endurance, and that's a little
bit better than just active years by
itself.
So it's a way to visualize in one scatter
plot this model three relationship.
Okay, we can also save the residuals,
which is a
very important lesson and something we'll
use a lot going forward.
So, we want to, if we save the residuals
into a variable just called e, for error,
then I could visualize the residuals.
So, we should see that I have a normal
distribution of residuals, centered at
zero and sure enough that's what we get.
So if I just do a histogram of
the residuals they're centered right
around zero because some
of my prediction errors are, are too high,
and some of them are too low, all right.
And this, this satisfies the assumption of
homoscedasticity, right.
The prediction errors are just sort of
randomly fluctuating across that, that x
variable
and some are negative, some are positive
and there's a normal distribution around
zero.
So that's nice to see.
if we save our residuals and plot it in
the
histogram, that's the sort of thing we
want to see.
I could then look
at the relationship between the actual,
the predicted scores
and the residuals and of course, those are
going to be orthogonal to one another.
And sure enough, if I look at the
residuals in relationship to the predicted
scores then there's no correlation there,
and that's, that
should be obvious.
Okay, so I'm almost done with this
lab but I just want to show you how to get
standardized regression coefficients.
It's real simple we're just going to run
the same exact models that we did up
above, except we're going to put this word
scale, not
just word but function scale, around each
one of our variables.
So if I just put scale in front of all the
variables in all of these models
then we'll get standardized regression
coefficients.
Just to remind you that the standardized
regression
coefficients in a simple regression, and
remember it's
only in a simple regression, the
standardized
regression coefficients will equal the
correlation coefficient.
So just to remind us what the correlation
coefficients are I'm going to run the
correlations again.
And then I'll run these two simple
regressions
to show you that those should be
equivalent.
So, this gave me a lot of outputs.
Let me go up.
so
[COUGH]
there we are.
here are the correlation coefficients, I
just got that by running the core function
again and I rounded it to make it clean.
so remember they're about 0.33 for, for
active years predicting endurance
but negative 0.08 for endurance, or sorry,
for age predicting endurance.
So, in this first model we, we use the
function scale to get standardized
coefficients, age predicting endurance,
what is the
progression coefficient?
Well, it's negative 0.08, exactly
the correlation coefficient, okay.
Then if we
go down and look at the coefficient
for active years it's 0.326 or 0.33.
Okay, so it's exactly the same as the
correlation coefficient
when we get the standardized regression
coefficient in a simple regression.
Now that's not going to be true when we go
to multiple regression.
So once we add in another predictor,
remember those
coefficients can change and it, it changes
a great deal in this example, that's
why I use this example, it's sort of a
nice one, those coefficients can change.
So now even with the standardized
regression coefficients,
they're not going to equal the correlation
coefficients anymore.
So I run that, and
now you see I have a, a standardized
regression coefficient for age of negative
0.22 and for active years it went up a
little bit which is sort of unusual.
This is a unique example that's why I used
this.
it went up to almost 0.4 so it's now in
multiple regression.
The standardized regression coefficients,
they're still going to range from
like negative one to positive one but
they're not
going to be equal to the Pearson
product-moment correlation.
So it's really important to know that in
multiple regression, the
standardized regression coefficients will
not
be equal to the correlation coefficient.
In simple regression, which is one
predictor in the equation, yes, the
standardized
regression coefficient will equal the
correlation
coefficient but not here in multiple
regression.
And that's what we are going to
do in the next couple of weeks we're going
to do more of these multiple regressions.
Just one last thing I want to point out
here, is notice that the r squared is
exactly
the same for the standard, the
standardized solution as
it is for the unstandardized and hopefully
that makes sense.
All we're doing with the standardized
solution is we're just changing
the scale of the variables, so the
relationships remain exactly the same.
If you wanted to visualize that you could
just
plot it.
but you can see the, the code, the p
values, the t values for these
coefficients are exactly the same as
before and this multiple r squared.
The proportion of variance explained in y
is
exactly the same as when we did it
unstandardized.
Okay so that's it for lab four.
That's everything you'll need for the next
assignment, good
luck on that and I'll talk to you next
week.