Hi, welcome back.
Rep to lecture 3, segment 3.
And this last segment of lecture three is
on scales of measurement.
Now, in lecture three, I have sort of been
em, emphasizing how
important it is to know what type of
variable you are dealing with.
And emphasizing how important it is to
look at your distributions in your
variables.
It's also really important to keep in mind
what scale
of measurement you're dealing with.
so this last segment, which will be a
slightly shorter segment, is just talking
about different scales.
We've already dealt with this in the last
segment by looking at the body temperature
example.
So, for all those histograms, I presented
the
histograms first in degrees Fahrenheit,
then in degrees Celsius.
Those are just two different scales of
measurement
to measure temperature.
Alright?
So, I think we're all used to dealing with
scales of measurement.
But in statistics, what's nice is there's
a
standard scale and it's called the Z
scale.
So, any score from any scale can be
converted into a Z scale with Z scores.
And this allows for a really efficient
communication across stataticians.
scientists can share data, different
researchers can share data.
If everything is
converted to a Z scale, it's very easy to
interpret.
And it's very simple calculation.
How do we convert a, what I'll call a raw
score to a Z score?
It's just this formula right here.
We just take the raw score, that's x,
subtract
the mean m, and divide by the standard
deviation.
Now, we haven't covered summary statistics
in detail yet.
We'll do that in the next lecture, so
you'll see exactly how
to calculate mean and standard deviation
if
you're not familiar that, with that
already.
but that's it.
It's that simple a calculation.
So we'll just take the raw score,
subtract the mean, divide by the standard
deviation.
That gives us a Z score.
And if we do that for every score in a
distribution, then
we can put our distribution on this common
metric, the Z scale.
So, what's also nice about a Z scale or Z
scores, is the
mean Z score in any one sample is always
going to be 0.
Right?
So I take the raw score, subtract the
mean.
If my raw score is the mean, so say
body temperature, the average body
temperature in Fahrenheit is 98.6.
So 98.6 minus the mean, assuming a normal
distribution,
98.6 minus 98.6 be 0, divided by whatever
the standard deviation is, would be 0.
So the mean in any Z score distribution is
going to be 0.
What's nice about that is if you have a
negative Z
score, then I know you have, your score is
below average.
And if you have a positive Z score, then I
know you're above average.
So again, let's look at this body
temperature distribution.
Here it is again in, in
degrees Fahrenheit, it's this nice normal
distribution.
Here it is again in Celsius, again nice
normal distribution.
Here it is in terms of z scores.
Again, we did this in r, and r sort of did
the breaks a little bit differently for
this graph, but it's still a nice
normal distribution.
And most importantly, the average is 0.
So the average body temperature in terms
of z scores is 0.
These are the same exact numbers from
histogram to histogram, to histogram.
It's just in degrees Fahrenheit, degrees
Celsius, or in Z-scores.
It's the same exact numbers.
We just converted them, direct conversion.
So, just to be clear, let's assume we have
a normal distribution of healthy
individuals, where the mean
body temperature is 98.6 degrees
Fahrenheit, and the standard
deviation is about a half a degree, so
0.5.
Suppose I pick one individual from that
distribution at random,
and that individual's body temperature is
99.6 degrees.
Now, I want to convert that raw score,
that X 99.6
to a Z score.
Well, all I have to do is apply this Z
formula.
I take the raw score, 99.6,
subtract out the mean, 98.6, divide by the
standard deviation,
which was 0.5.
So that's just one over 0.5, or 2.
So this individual's Z-score is positive
2.
There are two standard deviations above
the mean.
The other thing we can do once we convert
everything to Z scores and
look at histograms in a Z distribution, is
we can easily get percentile rank.
Which is a useful statistic to get when
we're looking at
descriptive statistics and where
individuals fall
relative to others within a distribution.
So the percentile rank is just the
percentage of scores
that fall at or below that score in a
distribution.
So, if we're dealing with a perfectly
normal distribution and we've converted
everything to Z scores, then I know that
the percentile rank for a Z of 0 is 50%.
Right?
If I have a nice normal distribution,
normal distribution,
I've converted it to Z, so the mean is 0.
Then below that score is going to be 50%
of the distribution.
In other words, the percentile rank of a Z
of 0 or 98.6 degrees Fahrenheit is 50%.
50% of the distribution falls below the
mean.
So, to sum up, the Z-scale is the standard
scale that we use in statistics.
It's very efficient.
It's very nice for communication.
I can take any raw score, convert it to a
Z-score.
And once I have a Z-score, I can get a
percentile rank.
So these conversions are very common in
statistics.
And at this point, you should
be comfortable doing those types of
conversions.
And we'll do those in lab and
perhaps on a, on the next homework.
And that's the end of this segment.