Hi, welcome back.
We're up to lecture three segment two, and
in this segment we're going to talk about
distributions, and we'll look at
distributions in graphs called histograms.
So a histogram is one of the simplest
graphs that
we use in statistics But they're very
useful, and very informative.
So it's just a type of graph, that's used
to display a distribution.
So you might think why start with
histograms, there
are lots of fancier graphics that we could
start with.
but a histogram is nice.
Because it helps us to overcome
our some natural tendency to rely on
summary statistics.
And this is just a natural thing.
As an analogy, think of just stereotyping.
It's very easy to stereotype individuals.
Who are part of a group, because you can
rely on your sort
of summary statistics, of that group to
make an inference about an individual.
But, as we know, we shouldn't do that, if
we want to get to know individuals
within a group.
We want to look at the entire
distribution.
We want to look at everybody within the
group before we calculate those Summary
statistics, or jump to those conclusions,
those summary conclusions about a group.
So here's a quick example of a
nice, normal distribution plotted in a
histogram.
So, we're going to look at a lot of
histograms in this segment, and throughout
the course.
They'll always take on the same form.
So on the X axis, I'm plotting whatever
variable it is that I'm looking at.
In this case, it's the, the example is
body temperature present measured in
degrees Fahrenheit.
And on the, Y
axis, all I have is frequencies just the
number of people in this
distribution, in this sample, that have
this particular body temperature.
So, in a second I'll do this in
Celsius because I know we have
international audience.
But in, in Fahrenheit,
normal body temperature is about 98.6
degrees.
That's what most people go with.
so if you look where 98.6 degrees is right
about here.
So, yeah.
It's right about at the average.
this group runs a little hot, you might
say.
so that's a nice, normal distribution.
A characteristic of a normal
distribution is, if I wanted to sort of
smooth this, I could draw a curve over it.
It has this nice, bell shaped curve to it.
And the way to spot a normal distribution,
is to look for that signature bell shaped
curve, and it's symmetrical around the
mean, around the average.
So you see there's just to,
the, the number of cases beyond the mean,
is
about equal to the number of cases below
the mean.
So it's symmetrical, and has this nice
normal bell shaped curve.
Here's the same exact data, just plotted,
in terms of Celsius, so now on the
X axis you see we're just plotting
temperature measured in degrees Celsius.
Again it's a normal distribution.
We did these graphics in R, and you're,
you've seen R a little bit, in the labs.
and R just bins these differently.
So you can see the width
of these bins, are, are different.
And again you can set that if you remember
using the R function hist.
And the argument breaks.
You can change that if you like.
But this is just the same exact
data, plotted in Celsius instead of in
Fahrenheit.
So those are nice, normal distributions.
but histograms can reveal a lot of
information captured that's not captured
by summary statistics.
so just for an example, let's run with
this body temperature example.
Assume a few kids in the class are sick,
just a, a, a couple.
They have the flu for example ,and they
have a really high body temperature.
We might not capture that just by getting
say the
average body temperature across the whole
group, especially if it's a really
large group, right, Those a couple of
kinds who are sick won't really show up.
But if we look at the histogram, then what
we'll see is, if like, here's
one kid out here, who has temperature of
like over 101.
I actually had a temperature of over 101
last week, it was nasty.
so here's this kid, this
one kid in the distribution, so, it's not
quite normal, it's more like this.
Alright?
If I had to smooth it out.
So that's what's called a skewed
distribution, and this is a positive skew.
And the way to remember that is,
the skew is where there's few.
So there are fewer scores at the positive,
or high end, of this distribution.
That's why it's a positive skew.
Okay, so the skew is where there's few.
This is a positively skewed distribution.
This is the same exact graphic, just
presented again in Celsius instead of in
Fahrenheit.
And again we don't get a nice normal
distribution.
We get something that looks more like
that.
It's not quite as skewed as I drew before,
but
[LAUGH]
you get the point.
It's a little bit positively skewed.
Now again, not all distributions are
normal.
We're going to assume normal
distributions, for a lot of
the statistical procedures that we do in
this course.
but, we need to examine that first.
So, a first step in a lot of our labs, and
in a lot of
the homework assignments, will be to plot
histograms, and determine if we have
normal distributions.
But there are lots of distributions that
are not normal.
So let's look at a couple that are not
normal.
So, again, I'm going to run with this body
temperature example, for a few more slides
and say, say we have 1 group of children.
The entire group had the flu.
Say a whole classroom full of children got
sick with the flu, and then they were
treated.
They were given, say, antibiotics (as I
was last week, than goodness for the
antibiotics
[LAUGH]
).
And one thing that can happen with
antibiotics, is
it can actually suppress your body
temperature a bit.
So, after getting the antibiotics, that
group of children, their body
temperatures might be a little bit below
average relative to normal.
and then, let's compare them to a second
group, a second classroom of
kids, who also got infected with the flu,
but maybe, say, a week later.
So, their body temperatures are still
high.
Okay.
Let's look at that in, in graphics.
Again, I'm going to do this first in
Fahrenheit, then in Celsius.
so here's a, a, on the left, a normal
distribution.
It's pretty normal.
but it's a little bit below average.
Remember I said it's, the average is 90,
98.6.
and in this case we're actually,
a little bit below 98, it looks like is
the average for that group.
And here, again, we've got a pretty
normal, not perfectly normal distribution.
and this group is
a little bit above average.
So we've got you know, the average looks
like it's approaching 100.
So this is the group of children who are,
are still sick.
They haven't have the antibiotics yet.
Imagine that, I didn't know that these are
two separate classrooms of children.
Imagine that I just looked at their body
temperatures, and plotted the histogram.
All of them together.
So let's put
them together.
So if we put those 2 distributions
together, the, the
group of children who are on the
antibiotics, and their, their
body temperatures' a little bit below
average, with the group
of children who are still sick, and
haven't received the antibiotics.
Their body temperature is still above
normal.
What you'll see is the distrubution that
looks like this.
It's actually bimodal.
It has 2 modes.
So, if I, if you look at it carefully, you
can see
there's sort of a normal distribution
there, and a normal distribution there.
It's the two distributions put together.
So if you didn't know that, it might be
harder to see, but the more practice you
get at looking at histograms, the more
you'll
start to see these, evidence of non normal
distributions.
So this is an example
of something that looks not normal.
Instead, I would describe this as bimodal.
Again, I'm just doing the same exact
thing.
Except here, I'm plotting everything in
degrees Celsius, instead of degrees
Fahrenheit.
So here, this group is a little, if you
look at the average, they're a little
below average.
If you look at the average for this
group on the right, they're a little above
average.
If we put them together.
Again, what we see
is something that looks a little bimodal.
You get these two peaks.
There's a peak here and a peak here.
Remember in a normal distribution there's
just one peak, in the center distribution.
Here we're seeing two peaks And, again,
it's evidence that we
have these two different samples of
children that were put together.
So the point of that exercise.
And the point of looking at all those
histograms, is to
just make this simple point that not all
distributions are normal.
Yes we are going to assume a lot of
normal distributions as we go forward in
this course.
Its easy especially for introductory
statistics to
assume a normal distribution, but we'll
make
that assumption, then we'll test it by
looking at histograms, by running the
scripted
statistics and r.
we'll see if we have normal distributions
or not.
So we'll assume normal distributions, but
just
keep in mind not all distributions are
normal.
so simply viewing a histogram often
reveals whether its not normal.
You might have a positive skew, you might
have a negative skew, you might have
something
that's bimodal, you might have something
that looks
completely out of whack not normal at all.
Sometimes it's hard to determine just by
looking at the historgram, and
it's a judgement call, there are no hard,
and fast rules about this.
So in that case, summary statistics will
help, and we'll
talk more about that in the next lecuture
on summary statistics.
so, the only way to really get a good
handle on what is a normal distribution
look like,
and what does a non normal distribution
is just to look at more and more
histograms.
The more experience you get with this, the
more you'll be
able to say, yeah, that's, that's normal
enough for our statistical procedure.
we'll go ahead.
Or that's that's too positively skewed,
that's too, negatively, negatively
skewed.
So the best way to do that is just get
experience.
So let's look at more distributions.
This can get a little tedious so while
we do it, we'll imagine that we're wine
tasting.
Or, you're at home.
You could start drinking wine, right now
if you haven't already
[LAUGH].
I haven't yet.
It's still.
In the morning here
[LAUGH]
in the US, on the East Coast.
so, let's go wine tasting.
So in this example, suppose that we have
100 wine experts.
And they're going to drink, and rate the
overall quality of eight different wines.
They're going to rate four red wines, and
four white wines.
And, in all the examples higher scores
indicate
higher quality.
So if they give it a score in the 90s that
means they really like it.
and let's say we had 4 countries submit 2
wines each, so I just picked 4 countries,
I actually
picked 4 countries where I know we have a
lot
of Korsera students in statistics 1 in
these 4 countries.
So it wasn't completely random, there were
4 countries with a
lot of students, and they're known for
producing lots of good wine.
So, Argentina, Australia, France, and the
US.
Each one submitted a red, and each one
submitted
a white, we again, just did this for fun,
my assistant on this, is, is from France,
so we had a lot of fun doing this example.
so let's say Argentina submitted a malbec,
they're
very known for their quality malbecs, and
a chardonnay.
Australia, let's say,
they submitted a Shiraz, and a Pinot
grigio.
France, let's say they submitted a
Bordeaux, and Sauvignon blanc.
And the US, let's say, they submitted a
Cabarnet, and a Reisling.
And you're going to say, Reisling from the
US?
Yes, upstate New York has really great
Reislings, which is where I'm from.
so that wasn't random.
I, I had to slip that in.
That was personal.
so the US submitted a Cabarnet, probably
from California
a Reisling from upstate New York, let's
say.
Okay.
To preview what we did, again we just made
up this example.
We had a lot of fun making this example
up.
and we made it up so that the red wines,
the distributions of the ratings, are
normal in the red wines.
But if you look at the ratings of the
white wines, those are all not normal.
So here are the distributions.
We just simulate a data in R.
It's very easy to do.
We'll show you how to do that in a later
lab.
and then we plotted them in histograms.
So again, what I'm looking at here on the
x axis
is just the wine rating, and then on the y
axis.
How many wine experts gave it that
particular rating?
So you can see, for the Argentenian red,
that's the Melbec, they had a nice, normal
distribution.
the Australian red was the Charaz, I
believe, right?
Un, that's a really nice, normal
distribution.
You can't get much more normal than that.
let's look at the
distributions for the French red, and the
US red.
the French not completely normal.
There's a little bit of skew there, down
there.
But it's pretty normal.
in the US again nice, normal distribution.
Let's compare that to some non normal
distributions.
So now let's look at the white wine, the
ratings for the white wine.
First if we look at the the ratings from
Argent, on the Argentinian
white wine, you see you get this one big
peak, right in the middle.
Right, so, most of the wine experts just
found this to
be a pretty good wine, It's the rating is
around seventy
to seventy two.
So they found it above average.
But most of them rated it right in that
category.
So it was very, very consistent.
All right.
In contrast to the Australian White, here
you'll see
you're getting a little bit of that
positive skew.
So this one's not looking as normal as the
red wines distributions.
There's a positive skew in this one.
Now let's look at France.
France is sort, their, their distribution
is sort of, the opposite of Argentina.
Right?
Instead of having one big, steep peak,
there is what we call a uniform
distribution.
That is, the ratings were all over the
place.
So, some of the, some of the raters loved
it.
Some of the raters hated it.
Okay?
and then, the United States white that was
the Reisling this has
a bit of a negative skew to it.
Again, the skew is where there's few.
So there's very few ratings right down
here at the low end.
So very few of the wine raters, gave that
US white wine, the Riesling, a really low
rating.
So it's a little bit negatively skewed.
So all of those, are just to show you
that.
There, in many cases, like body
temperature, like the wine
ratings for the red wine, we're going to
get these normal distributions.
And in a lot of cases in the labs, in the
homeworks, we're going to deal with
variables
that give us nice, normal distributions.
But we can't always assume that to be
true.
So we're going to have to look, and see if
there are non normal distributions
lurking in our data.
So to summarize this segment, we use
histograms to display an entire
distribution because
they sometimes reveal information that
summary statistics gloss over,
or, or, or won't tell us.
And many if not most distributions
that we deal with are going to be normal.
but some distributions are not normal.
And for example we looked at the bimodal
distribution
where the 2 classrooms of kids who were
sick.
The ones who were treated, and not
treated.
We looked at positively skewed
distributions, negatively skewed.
We looked at uniform distributions.
So that was like the white wine
distribution in France that's uniform, or
another phrase for that is platykurtic.
and the last type that we looked
at was leptokurtic.
That was like the white wine distribution
in Argentina with that one steep peak is
also called a leptokurtic distribution.
And now I just want to show you
a couple of advance visuals, or advanced
histograms,
and if we could zoom in on these, if you
could zoom in on the top
And then the bottom.
since we've talked about longitude, and
latitude,
and we've talked about histograms, I
wanted
to show just these two, very cool graphics
that I just picked off the internet.
what this shows is the world population As
a
function of latitude, and as a function of
longitude.
So, if you look at the top graph, what
we're
plotting is, you get this like nice,
normal distribution pretty much, right.
What that means is, most people live
around the equator and
as you move away from the equator, fewer
and fewer people live in those places.
the same can't be said about longitude,
right?
So if we look at the bottom graph, we
don't get a nice, normal distribution.
Instead, we get like a peak here, a peak
here.
What are those peaks?
Well, here this peak is probably China.
This peak reflects the population in
India.
All right, so, where you have a normal
distribution of population around
latitude, centered around the Equator, the
same can't be said for longitude.
the distribution is not normal the
population
distribution is not normal across
longitude.
Just one more example, of sort of advanced
graphics that you can do.
there's lots of these available on the
Internet.
This one is right on Coursera's homepage,
so if you want
to know more about where Coursera's
students are logging in from.
And where their country of origin is you
can look at this graphic by Coursera,
and what Coursera did is they just plotted
ar, around the globe.
they colored different countries, and the
darker the color given to a country
reflects more students, more Coursera
students from that country.
So you can see we have allot of students
from China,
we have allot of students from India,
allot of students from
Australia and so on.
These little circles refer to institutions
that are partners with Coursera.
So this is a fun graphic.
It's actually interactive on the home page
on Coursera, you can play with it.
so here we are in, in Asia I can move
around
the globe, and there you see Europe is
very well represented.
Some parts of Africa are represented, but
we have a ways to go I would say.
And then if I keep moving around the globe
to the west.
Oops.
Keep moving around the globe to the west.
Here's the U.S., of course lots of partner
institutions, that's, those are all the
circles in
the U.S., so, lots of students from the
U.S., lots of students from Canada, lots
of
students from Brazil as well, and South
America.
And again, that's available on the
Coursera
webpage if you want to look at that.
So, an example of, sort of Putting
distributions
into advanced graphics, and there are lots
of
other examples you might run into on the
internet, or in the news, that do similar
things.
So that's the end of this segment.