Hi, welcome back we are up to lecture 7,
segment 2
and the topic of lecture, lecture 7 is
Intro to Regression.
In the second segment we are going to
talk about how the regression coefficients
are estimated.
So I am going to dive right in here, I am
not dividing
this segment up into into different
sections, or pointing out specific topics.
Because there's just this one topic.
There's a, a regression equation.
And how do we estimate the coefficients in
the equation?
It's pretty simple, because, at this
point, we're just dealing with simple
regression.
Next week, in the lecture on
multiple regression, this gets much more
difficult, and requires matrix algebra.
So I will give you a little lesson
in matrix algebra as we go into multiple
regression.
But this segment still pretty easy.
So here is the regression equation I can
rewrite
it as the function of the predicted score
of Y.
and now I just have to estimate the
regression constant and the slope.
The key concept here and the math is
really easy there's actually hardly any
new math.
If, if you remember how to calculate the
collation
coefficient, that's basically the math but
there's a really important
new concept right here, and that is the
values
of the coefficients and this is true for
multiple regression.
Are estimated such that the regression
model yields optimal predictions.
Another way to say that is minimize the
residuals.
That's the mantra of regression, minimize
the residuals.
Minimize prediction error.
This is known in statistics as ordinary
least squares estimation.
And is a very important concept that you
should be very familiar with.
Or familiarize yourself with if you're not
familiar with it yet.
and again, the idea's just to minimize the
residuals.
The way we're going to do that is
calculate our residuals.
So that's right here.
Right?
A residual is just the observed score
minus the predicted score.
We're going to square all of those to get
rid of he problem of sine right.
because some I'm going to under predict,
some I'm going to over predict.
So let's square them all, and then sum
them.
And I get sum of squares just like
back in summary statistics when we
calculated variance.
Alright?
So we'll have a sum of squared residuals.
And we want to, we want to minimize that
value.
And you saw that or you've seen that
now repeatedly starting with our
discussion of correlations.
When we put this regression line into a
scatter plot.
Alright?
The regression line goes through the plot,
so that it minimizes the overall
distance between the line and those dots.
Alright?
The regression line doesn't go, say, up
here,
it doesn't go down here.
It tries to minimize the overall distance
between the line and each individual dot.
That's the idea of minimizing the
residuals.
A slightly different way to think about
this is
to think about the, all the variants in y.
And all the variants in x.
And then the co-variants between them.
And I'm going to try and illustrate this
point
through wen diagrams, because it makes a
nice
connection back to our calculation of the
correlation
coefficient and the idea of some of cross
products.
So lets,
bear with me if you don't like wen
diagrams if
you like Venn diagrams like me, you're
going to enjoy this segment.
so let's look at some Venn diagrams.
So imagine I could represent the sum of
the
squares for Y in this one circle, or Venn
diagram.
I have some variance in Y.
Likewise, I have some variance in X.
And we did this when
we talked about correlation.
The overlap between the variance in
y and the variance in x, is the sum of
cross products between x and y.
So the degree to which x and y correlate
is going to be represented by the degree
to which these two circles SS.Y and SS.X
overlap.
Right?
So high degree of overlap, we're going to
get a
correlation approaching one.
No overlap, we're going to get a
correlation approaching zero.
Now that we're in regression, I'm going to
change the notation a little bit.
And now this overlap, I'm going to refer
to as sums of squares for the model.
So this is the model sums of squares.
You can think of this as the explained or
systematic
variance in Y that's explained by X.
So again, how can we think about sums of
squares residual?
Well, it's just what's left over in Y.
So it's the unexplained variance in Y.
So here where we're doing just a, a simple
regression, this is easy.
We just have some of the variance in Y is
explained by the model.
Some of it is unexplained.
That's the residual.
And again, the goal is to minimize the
residual.
So the formula in simple regression is
very easy.
If we calculate the correlation
coefficient, which we
did last week in the lecture on
correlation, then
we just have to multiply by the standard
deviation of Y over the standard deviation
of X.
And the reason we need to do that is we
need to
take into account the scale of Y, and the
scale of x.
So imagine that there's a lot more
variability, or a much bigger scale in y
than there is in x, then a one unit
increase in x is going to be associated
with a large change in y, right?
So, that would take the correlation
coefficient and inflate it.
Okay?
So we have to take into account the
standard deviation
in both y and x, to get the unstandardized
regression coefficient
B 1.
If we wanted to standardize the regression
coefficient, which we
will do and we'll do it in lab this week.
It's very simple in r, there's just one
extra function.
that's even easier.
Because if everything is standardized then
the standard deviation for Y
and the standard deviation for X are both
going to be one.
Right?
If I put everything in the Z scores,
then the mean is zero and the standard
deviation is one.
Well, now look at the formula.
It's just a correlation coefficient times
one
over one, it's just the correlation
coefficient.
So the standardized regression
coefficient, and I'll use beta to signify
the standardized regression coefficient is
equal to the correlation coefficient.
Now, that's only true in simple
regression, with just one predictor.
Next week, all that's are off.
[LAUGH]
We get into multiple regression, it gets
much more complicated.
But for now, let's enjoy the simplicity.
So, to wrap up this segment.
The important concepts to take away,
again, are to understand the regression
equation and the model.
Perhaps the most important concept in this
segment is the idea of ordinary least
squares estimation, the idea that we're
going to
minimize the residuals in our regression
model.
And then understand that we can calculate
both
under, unstandardized regression
coefficients
and standardized regression coefficients.
And I'll show you how to do each of those
in the lab this
week using the LM function, and one extra
function to do the standardized piece.
And that's it for calculating the
coefficients.