Hi, welcome back to Statistics One.
We're up to lecture four, and the topic in
lecture four is summary statistics.
So in the last lecture we talked about
distributions
and the importance of looking at
distributions in histograms.
In this lecture we'll talk about the
importance of summarizing all
that information in just some talking
points that we call" summary statistics".
So this lecture is divided into just two
segments.
First, I'll talk about measures of central
tendency and
in the second segment I'll talk about
measures of variability.
So this first segment, let's look at
measures of central tendency.
To do this, again we're going to go wine
tasting.
Makes this a little bit more fun.
Remember we had this example from the last
lecture, where we had 100 wine experts.
Rate, like overall quality of eight
different
wines; four red wines, four white wines.
And again, higher scores indicated higher
quality.
Now, we might want to ask well which
country had the highest overall wine
rating?
That was important to us as we were doing
this we wanted to see how this would come
out.
And just for the record, to be clear, we
did this completely randomly.
So my assistant David, who is from France,
and I, we to be fair we just said let's
generate this completely randomly so that
we're not biased
and so that we don't insult people around
the world.
a funny thing happened, David actually did
this, he generated random numbers.
He came back to my office with a really
sad look on his
face, and he said," France-lost do we
really have to do this randomly?
[LAUGH]
and I said," Yes, we do have to do this
randomly".
so let's look at the overall rankings if
we just want to look
at the average, and let's just stick with
the reds for now.
Here are the means that we calculated from
the data that we generated.
so the mean for the Argentinian Malbec was
66.73.
The mean for the Australian Shiraz
was 81.76.
the mean for the French red I forget what
the French red was, was 70.97.
And for USA, it was a Cabernet, it was
76.38.
So, in this simulation, Australia won.
Okay, again, this is completely random.
we did not fix this.
But how do we calculate
the mean?
And, hopefully, this is review to you.
But again, this is a, this is supposed
to be an introduction, very first course
in statistics.
So if you're not familiar, The way we did
this is we, we plugged the numbers into r.
But if we wanted to do this by hand.
All we would have to do is take all of the
ratings from the
100 wine experts, just put them in a
column, sum that entire column and
then divide the sum by the number of
ratings.
So that's the formula right here.
So it's the formula for the mean or
average.
Is just the sum of all the scores divided
by the number of scores.
Okay?
So just sum of x, over n, is the mean.
And these are the means for the red ro,
red wines
across those, four countries.
Now, lets consider the white wines.
So which country won, with respect to the
whites, again, this is totally random, I
didn't bias this, even though I had a
favourite in the race, and that favourite
won.
[LAUGH]
so, the US, the Rieslings from upstate New
York.
[LAUGH]
The cameraman's waving hey.
again, this was not, this
was not biased, this was totally random.
just slightly one.
Right?
So it were, it just slightly beat out
Australia and France, for the overall
average, ranking.
But again, let's go back to the topic of
this,
this segment.
It's measures of central tendency.
The mean or average, is the most popular
measure of central tendency.
A, a, it's a very common summary
statistic,
I think most of you are familiar with it.
So, to be clear, what do I mean by a
measure of central tendency?
It's just a measure or a summary
statistic.
That describes the middle point, or is
representative of the middle point of a
distribution.
So it should be representative of the
distribution as a whole.
Of course, we can't describe the whole
distribution with one number.
Right?
This is just what statisticians call a
point estimate.
But it should do a pretty good job, it
should be representative.
The most common examples of measures of
central tendency
in statistics are the mean, the median and
the mode.
So, the mean we saw is just sum up all the
scores, divide by the number of scores.
It's the mean or the average.
The median is just the middle score in a
distribution.
So if I just lined up all of the rankings,
all
of the ratings on the wines, from the
highest ranking to
the lowest ranking, and just plucked out
the middle ranking, say the
50th ranking out of the 100, that would be
my median, ranking.
And the mode is easy.
That's just the score that occurs most
often in the distribution, and if now
that you've seen histograms and know how
to plot histograms, it's real easy to see.
Just look for the peak of the histogram.
That's the mode.
That's why that one non-normal
distribution that we talked about, in
the last lecture was called bi-modal
because it had two peaks.
So, if there are two peaks there are two
modes.
Sometimes there's more than one mode.
So the mean or the average, is by far the
most common measure of central tendency
used insti, in statistics.
It's the one we're going to rely on the
most in this course.
in any intro stats course, that's the one
that you're going to rely on the most.
so for example, the red, red wine ratings,
another classic example is just your grade
point average.
If you want to know how well you're doing
in school, or how well you're
doing acr, across all your Coursera
classes, I'm hoping
that maybe you're taking more than one
Coursera class.
You could get your grade point average.
Your average across all of your courses.
and there are lots more examples.
They're just averages or means that we can
take.
And those are the, the mean is the best
when you have a normal distribution.
If you don't have a normal distribution.
In particular, if you have a distribution
with really extreme scores.
So an extreme positive skew or an extreme
negative skew, then
you might rather go with the median,
rather than the mean.
And that's because those few extreme
scores can really bias the mean, whereas
the median, if you just line the scores
up, and take the middle one.
Those extreme scores are not going to buy
us the
median as much as they're going to buy us
the mean.
So we can look at the white wine ratings
as an example of that, but those weren't
that skewed.
So we'll look at them.
So you won't see a big difference between
the mean and median, you'll see a slight
difference.
another example is a classic example right
now in, in
the US, and, and lots of modern countries
right now,
is household income.
So, household income, particularly in the
US right now particularly in Brazil right
now is really not normally distributed.
So there's a real positive skew in, in
the, income distributions in
the US and in other countires as well, and
we'll take a look at that as well.
So, you'll often see reported in the news
or if you're
reading stuff on the internet, you'll
often hear.
Median salary, or median household income
reported, rather than
mean salary, or average salary, or average
household income.
And that's because those distributions are
skewed.
So first, let's look at the, the wine
ratings again.
These are the white wine ratings.
because remember, these one, these are the
ones that were not normally distributed.
I want to draw your attention to the
Australian distribution.
Remember, it was slightly positively
skewed.
This isn't a real strong skew.
We'll see, we'll see a stronger one in the
income distribution in a moment.
and then remember the US distribution had
this slight negative skew.
So if we look at the means and the
medians, the summary and statistics,
the measures of central tendency for these
wines; you'll see
that there's a slight shift in the
Australian one, and in the US.
For Australia, the median is slightly
lower than the mean,
because the median is less influenced by
those extreme scores.
The extreme scores in, in the Australian
case
were on the high end of the distribution.
Right?
It was positively skewed.
So the median is less influenced by those
really high ratings.
Therefore, the median is going to be
slightly lower than the mean in a
positively skewed distribution like the
Australian whites.
The opposite is true in the US white wine
rating distribution.
So, in that case, there was a slight
negative skew, so those negative, those
extreme negative
ratings are going to, have less of an
influence on the median.
So here, the median is going to be
slightly higher than the mean.
Again, because those low rankings are
going to have less
[INAUDIBLE]
of an influence on the median than they do
on the mean.
So the median is going to be slightly
higher in a negatively skewed
distribution, than the mean.
And we see that in the rankings for the US
white.
Here's a more detailed graphic.
again, this one I just took off the
internet.
This is a histogram of household income in
the United States.
It shows this really extremely positively
skewed distribution.
Okay?
Here you are going to see a large
difference between measures
of central tendency like the mean, the
median and the mode.
Okay, so if I just took the average of all
of these incomes, we're going to have to
average in these extremely high incomes
way up here,
which are, you know, this isn't even that
high.
The graph actually extends way beyond that
to include
people like Bill Gates and Mark Zuckerberg
and so on.
right, if I include their salaries in the
mean, the mean is really
going to be inflated.
In contrast, if I just take the median,
the middle score, that's going to be right
here,
no matter whether I include Mark
Zuckerberg, Bill
Gates, people like that, in my
distribution or not.
the median is still going to fall right
here, it's at about $49,445.
And if
you look at this the mode is actually
right about here that's
way down between like, say, 15 and 20,000.
Okay?
So when you have this extremely skewed
distribution like this.
Like US household income right now, over
the last few years in particular.
You're going to get a real difference
between the mean, the median, and
the mode.
Because it's hard to find a measure of
central tendency that's representative of
the entire group, right?
That's part of the problem.
I'm not going to get into a political
discussion about this.
it's just a good example to illustrate a
non-normal distribution, and how
measures of central tendency can really
differ when you have non-normal
distributions.
If it was perfectly normal,
then the mean and the median, and the mode
would be just about the same.
So finally, the mode is just the peak of
a histogram, it's just the score that
occurs most often.
So, the Argentina white wine distribution,
that was
a real easy one to look at the peak.
Remember, because it was, it was
leptokurtic.
it had that really strong peak.
If you look back at the graph, it was
right around 70 to 72.
It was also about the average.
because it didn't have really
extreme rankings on the negative end or on
the positive end.
a thing about the mode is it can also be
applied to nominal variables.
That's not true of the mean or the median.
Alright, but we can apply it to nominal
variables.
So, what I did for fun, is I just took
these countries
that we've been playing with the US,
France, Argentina, Australia, and I just
said, well in the last year what were the
most common, or what of the model baby
names.
this really surprised me, I don't know if
my source is accurate.
but, in the, in the US, the most common
female baby name in the last year is
Sophia, most common male name is James in
France it's Emma and Nathan in Argentina,
it's Sofia and Juan.
And in Australia, it's Charlotte and
Oliver.
Those are the model baby names.
They're the ones that occur most often.
It's only the mode that we can apply to
nominal variables.
We can't apply the average.
For example, two nominal variables or the
median to nominal variables.
So, to sum up this segment,
[INAUDIBLE]
we're talking about summary statistics.
Some of the most common summary statistics
are measures of central tendency.
By far, the most common is the mean, or
average, but we might want to use
the median, particularly in cases where we
have skewed distributions with, with
really, extreme outliers.
and some cases we might want to just look
at
the mode which is the score that occurs
most often.