Hi, welcome back.
We're in Lecture two, Segment three, and
I'm
still talking abut correlational research,
but this type
of correlational research is a little bit
different
from the first two segments on personality
and intelligence.
In this segment, I want to talk about an
example on the effects of
sports-related concussion on cognition and
on on the brain.
So this is an example of medical research.
So, the effects of concussion or
sports-related
concussion in particular has become a hot
topic of research, particularly here in
the
U.S. and particularly related to American
football.
There's been lots of studies recently,
especially in the last decade, showing
that there are really, sort of, terrible
effects neurally and cognitively,
for athletes who suffer sports-related
concussions, particularly in American
football.
So how do we study that?
Well, these, these studies look like
experiments.
So if you think back to the first lecture
on experimental research, this setup will
look like that setup.
So, there's what looks like an
independent variable, but I'm
going to call it a quasi-independent
variable.
So, this treatment, if you will,
is whether an athlete suffers a concussion
or doesn't suffer
a concussion.
So we can compare athletes to athletes who
are very similar to them, play the same
exact
sport, are the same age, sort of the
same, level of expertise, but don't suffer
a concussion.
So they're the control group.
And then we can measure them on several
dependent variables.
So we can look neurally at measures of the
brain
structure and function, and we can look at
cognitive measures.
So measures of short-term memory and
attention are most common.
but what's
tricky here is this is not a true
independent variable,
in that I don't have random assignment to
conditions.
That is, I can't, as a
researcher, take a group of
athletes and randomly assign
them to be concussed or not
concussed.
All right, that would
be sort of fun and / or evil, but I can't
do that.
I just have to wait for them to happen as
a
researcher and, unfortunately they happen
pretty frequently, especially here at
Princeton.
Our, our football team, they happen pretty
quickly, when our football
players arrive here in the fall is when
they play football
in the U.S..
It's not random assignment to conditions.
So that's not a true independent variable.
That's really important when you think
about making those
causal claims about what's causing these
changes down here.
Is it really the concussion or is it
something, something else about
these athletes that led them to be
concussed in the first place.
We'll get back to that at the end of the
segment.
So, here's an example of one of the
assessments, is, so, once an athlete
suffers a concussion
we might ask them something like this I'm
going to, to assess their concentration,
or their attention.
I'm going to read to you a string of
numbers and when
I'm done, you repeat them back to me in
reverse order.
This is known as backwards digit span in
cognitive psychology.
So, for example, if i say seven, one,
nine, you have to say nine, one, seven.
That's not a great example for New
Yorkers.
That's the area code in New York.
[LAUGH]
917.
That would be too easy.
So if you get that correct, then you go to
a longer string length,
and you can see down here the different
examples that these athletes are given.
And when we give this to athletes at
baseline,
so when athletes come to Princeton, we
actually do this.
We give them baseline assessments when
they
first get to Princeton before they start
playing
a sport.
We give them this sort of test.
They all do really well.
They basically max out on it.
For instance, students can do up to
like five, six numbers and they can do it
backwards very easily.
But after a concussion, after a really bad
hit, if they're
an American football player, sometimes
they're really bad, and so we can
look at their change, this pre-post test
sort of design.
We can look at their change in performance
on a test like this before, that
is baseline before a concussion, and then
post, after, a concussion.
And we can do that for a control group.
We can give them this test once at the
beginning of
the season and then say randomly at some
point during the season.
But they
haven't suffered a concussion so we can
use them as
a comparison group for the group that did
suffer a concussion.
So what we typically see in these types
of studies is that the concussed athletes
perform
much worse on these measures of short-term
memory,
attention, also balance is a good measure,
so
once an, right after an athlete suffers a
hit If you give them a balance test
where they just have to stand on one leg
they can't do it for very long.
Like right now I'm doing it fine I wasn't
concussed this morning
[LAUGH].
So but if I was concussed what would look,
I would just like do
that very quickly and that's a very good
assessment actually of
concussion.
so it looks like we have pretty
nice causal claims that the hit caused
performance on this
balance test or this attention test.
the backward
digit span.
but there are potential confounds, right,
because
we don't have a true independent variable.
There could be other variables that are
leading to this result.
So one problem, and this is a problem
we've dealt with in the research here at
Princeton, is lots of these athletes have
suffered
concussions before, so is it really this
one hit?
that caused
them to become suddenly really off
balance or suddenly interrupt their
short-term memory?
.
Or is it the cumulative affect of several
hits and this one
being the one that really, finally caused
this damage?
So, is it this one hit or this history of
concussions.
We don't know because we don't have true
random assignment to conditions.
we can look at their history of prior
concussions and try and
tease that apart, but it's not as strong
as a true experiment.
Alright that's more like correlational
research.
That's why it's here in this lecture on
correlational research, is
this kind of thing looks like a true
experiment, but it's not.
Okay, so be,
be very careful, especially as consumers
of research and consumers
of statistics, be very careful to be able
to spot sort of correlational
research that's dressed up as experimental
research.
So, this is a great example of that, is it
looks like
experimental research, because you have
people
who are concussed, and people who weren't.
It looks like
a nice experimental group and control
group,
but it's, they weren't randomly assigned
to conditions.
So deep down it's just correlational
research, it's really no different from
the intelligence research that I
mentioned,
and the personality research that I
mentioned.
Okay, so there, there's, this is open up
to lots of different types of confounds.
In particular there might be certain
personality
types that are more likely to put
themselves in
in a position where they're susceptible to
this concussion.
So maybe certain personality types that
are more aggressive, for example,
in American football are more likely to
become concussed than others and maybe
aggressive people have certain types of
brain structure or function or
certain types of work perform cognitive
measures differently than others.
We don't know, again because this isn't
as, sort of
tight as the true experimental research
like the polio vaccine trials.
So again, the main point of this
segment is to point out quasi-independent
variables.
And again, since the independent variable
doesn't
involve random representative sampling,
arguments about causality
aren't as strong, and that's the main
thing to take away from this segment.
To summarize the entire lecture,
just recognize the distinction between
correlational
research and experimental research as we
go forward
and start to get more into the statistics.
This first week has been mostly about
methods but as
I said, as consumers of statistics or now
that you're about
to become people who are skilled in doing
statistics, it's
important to know what type of research
are you engaging in.
Are you engaging in experimental research
or correlational research?
And again, I'll refer to correlational
research
as studies, and experimental research as
simply experiments.
The main important concepts to take away,
are that theories of personality and
intelligence, those have been supported by
investigating patterns of correlations.
Obtained from observation, observational,
correlational studies.
and some things we just simply can't
manipulate ethically.
Right?
All right, so we can't just take people
into, take people to a football
field and randomly assign them to be
concussed or not concussed.
there are lots of things like gender,
male,
female religious affiliation.
I can't randomly assign those things to
people.
The people come to my laboratory or to
a laboratory setting with just those
traits or characteristics.
We can't randomly assign them, so those
are quasi-independent variables.
And they fall under the category of
correlational research.
So those are the main concepts
to take away from this segment,
and from this first week.