Hi, welcome back.
We're in lecture eight, segment two.
The topic of this lecture is
null hypothesis significance testing, for
short, NHST.
In the first segment, I gave you an
overview of how NHST works.
Now in this segment, I'm going to get into
the more controversial aspects of NHST.
I'm going to list several problems that
critics of NHST are quick
to point out.
But I'll also note some remedies that you
can
supplement your NHST's with to overcome
some of these problems.
So, there are several problems with NHST,
and I've listed just six here.
Hard core critics of NHST would probably
list more.
but I just listed I, what I think to be
the six primary problems with NHST.
I'll go through each of this in turn and
then
after I go through the problems, I'll talk
about ways
to overcome those problems, what I call
the remedies.
So lets just go to the list.
The first problem is that it's biased by
sample size.
So, we've already seen this in action if
you looked at your R
output and your p values as they relate to
sample size.
So, for example, in regression, the p
value that you get
in your R output Is based on the t value
that's calculated.
And the t value in regression is the
unstandardised regression coefficient B
divided by standard error.
Where standard error is the square root of
the
sum of squares residual divided by sample
size minus 2.
Okay, we went through these calculations
as we talked about
regression, you can verify them by looking
in your R output.
The important thing to notice here, is N
is in the denominator of the standard
error equation.
And, standard error is in the denominator
of the t equation.
So Here's N.
Imagine that I just jack up N really,
really high.
Imagine I get a huge sample of thousands
of people.
If N goes really, really high, then
standard error is going to go really low.
If standard error goes really low then the
t-value is going to go very high.
And a high t-value is always going to be
associated with a
very low p-value, which would allow you to
reject the null hypothesis.
So regardless of what the actual slope is,
regardless of what B is, if I
just increase N to an astronomical number
then I'll get a very low standard error.
In turn I'll get a very high T value and
in turn
I'll get a very low p value which will
allow me to reject the non-g hypothesis
ever time.
That's what statisticians mean when they
say NH, NHST is biased by sample size.
We'll get a significant result almost all
the
time If we just obtain a really large
sample.
The second problem is this arbitrary
decision rule.
Right?
We just have to pick some cutoff value and
say, once
I get to that value, I'm going to reject
the null hypothesis.
Now, it's become standard, particularly in
the social sciences, particularly in
psychology that a alpha value of 0.05, or
p less than 0.05.
Indicates that you can reject the null
hypothesis, and claim that you have a
statistically significant effect.
But, that's completely arbitrary.
That's just some, we just somehow landed
it on P less then 0.05 as a field.
We can change that to 0.01 if we wanted to
be more conservative.
We could change it to 0.1 if we wanted to
be more liberal.
The point is it's completely arbitrary, so
that's
what I mean by arbitrary decision rule.
On top of that, problems arise and some
sort of funny problems arise in the
literature, in the scientific literature.
When p values come close to 0.05, it's
funny how authors will
twist and turn their language when they
get a p of 0.06.
It's trending towards significance.
It's marginally significance.
It's almost there.
They'll, they'll almost always report the
result as if it's
significant if the P value get close
enough to 0.05.
Which is really violating the rules of the
game, right?
It has to be this binary decision reject,
retain, only if
your, your obtained P value is less than
your specified Alpha value.
But people don't do that in reality,
especially when they're writing Up
results for scientific journals.
This third problem I came up with a sort
of funny name for so forgive me.
the local yokel test.
What I mean by that is that's sort of a
phrase for.
it's just sort of what you do as a, as a
common custom.
So, a lot of people, even really good
researchers,
who have PhDs and are doing cutting edge
research.
Even those people sometimes
just do NHSTs because it's the only thing
they ever learned.
They took one statistics course in
graduate school, on their way to a
PhD and they learn how to do an MHST and
then that's it.
They learn P less than 0.5 means
statistically
significant and that's how they conduct
their research.
So that's what I mean by Yokel local, it's
just,
it's just the custom and it's the only
thing you've learned.
And that's your reason for doing it.
And as we know, that's never a good reason
for choosing one procedure over another or
choosing one tool over another in science.
Just because it's the one that you know
and it's the only
one you know isn't the reason why you
should go with it.
So.
One it's the, it's, this is a problem
because it's the only thing that some
people
know, and in turn it encourages weak
hypothesis testing.
Remember if you set up the rules of the
game, it's
just nothing will happen, the null
hypothesis or something will happen.
Oh, that's not a very strong form of
hypothesis testing.
So if you only know this one way of
doing things, then it encourages weak
hypothesis testing sort
of weak thinking in terms of testing
theories in science.
The next problem is we know it's error
prone, right?
So from the last segment we know that
there's always
a possibilty of type one errors and type
two errors.
And it's actually worse than I outlined in
the last segment, so.
The probability of type 1 errors actually
increases and can get really
high as researchers conduct multiple
tests.
Especially multiple tests on the same
data.
These are called dependent tests.
If you don't correct for the multiple
tests.
Then that probability of a type one error
just keeps compounding and inflating.
So the probability of type one error
can be really inflated if researchers
aren't careful.
On the flip side there are a lot of fields
of research,
especially in the social sciences, and
especially psychology that
are just plagued with a large degree of
sampling error.
We have big populations, but don't have a
lot of resources to obtain big samples.
So we get small samples relative to these
big populations, which
gives us a large amount of sampling error,
big estimates of standard error.
Which means we're going to wind up missing
a lot of
effects even if they really exist out
there in the population.
So, not only is it error-prone, we know we
have
a certain probability of getting type one
and type two errors.
But in a lot of fields of research it's
actually worse than I outlined in the
first segment.
And finally, NHST forces
you to engage in what I call shady logic.
[LAUGH]
And, at first, it seems very clear.
So if you remember from basic logic class,
modus tollens.
Everything on this slide is perfectly
valid.
So Modus tollens just says, if p then q.
Not q, therefore not p.
That's all valid.
It would be valid if we said exactly that.
If the null hypothesis
is correct right, we assume the null to be
to true.
So if the null is correct.
Then, these data that I obtain in my
experiment cannot occur.
The data have occurred, therefore the null
hypothesis is false.
That's exactly modus tollens, that's all
valid.
But unfortunately that's not how we do it.
The problem is,
that the logic becomes probabilistic in
NHST and
in inferential statistics.
So, instead, this is how it goes.
If the null hypothesis is correct, that's
the assumption we
make, then these data are highly unlikely,
that's the probabilistic part.
These data have occurred.
Therefore the null hypothesis is highly
unlikely.
That's what we do when we engage in NHST.
But let's take it out of
NHST and use, just, an everyday example.
So, if
a person plays football, then he or she is
probably not a professional player.
That's true a very small percentage of
people go on to play professional
football.
Right I wish, I wish I could have, I tried
I played
in college didn't make it so I didn't go
pro like most people,
so for person plays football then here she
is probably not a professional player.
But wait this person is a professional
player,
therefore here she probably does not play
football, what?
That doesn't make any sense, but if you
compare these two these two logic outcomes
the
first one, the second one they are exactly
the same.
The problem going from the last slide to
this slide is that we made
it probabilistic and once you do that you
engage in what's called shady logic.
And you come to some pretty odd
conclusions like this one down at the
bottom.
So, given all those problems why do still
use it at all?
Well, there are a lot of people out there
who would say we shouldn't be using it.
We should ban NHST and its reliance on
t-values.
I'm not so strict about that.
I think there are several remedies that
you can.
add to your research that will ameliorate
a lot of those problems.
And just being educated about what NHST
does and doesn't
do is a huge step of what, of the way
there.
So if you understand this segment Or
in this entire lecture then hopefully you
wont
make the mistakes that some people when
interpreting
P values and the idea of statistically
significant.
So first lets go back through the
problems, so biased by sample
size, a simple thing to do and this is
common now in most peer review journals.
Is whenever you report in NHST also report
estimates
of effect size, because effect size tell
you not just
if an, if an effect is significant or not,
but it tells you about the magnitude of
the effect.
So for example in regression we will
report standardized regression
coefficients and the model
R squared that tells us about the
magnitude of effects
same holds for this arbitrary decision
rule.
So, yeah its arbitrary but if you're right
on
the cusp then don't worry so much about
being significant
or not significant report estimates of
effects size that'll tell
people whether you have a large effect or
small effect.
With respect to this Yokel local test
obviously go out and learn other forms of
hypothesis testing and second, consider
adding in multiple alternative hypotheses.
You don't have to have just the null and
one alternative.
You could have the null, alternative one,
alternative two and so on and many
engage in model comparison which we will
do next week when we do multiple
regression.
In terms of the test being error prom
there are
several steps we can take to protect
against the impact
of those errors, so number one most
importantly replicate significant
effects To avoid the long term impact of
Type I errors.
So for example, go back to lecture one
when we
talked about the effect of working memory
training on intelligence.
Those authors found that there was a
significant effect, right?
But that might have been a Type I error.
So we need to replicate that effect over
and over again so that the entire
literature
and society at large doesn't start to
begin,
doesn't start to believe that that's a
real result.
So, significant effects need to be
replicated to avoid long term impact
of type 1 errors.
To avoid type 2 errors, simply obtain
large Random representative samples.
That would give you a shot at obtaining an
effect if it exists in the population.
With respect to the shady logic, there's
no way out of that one.
Except to say remember what a P value is.
And when I teach this course at Princeton
this
is perhaps the one thing that I tell them.
If you walk ou, out of this classroom and
away from Princeton University please
remember this one thing.
That you learn from statistics.
That, what this p-value means.
It's the probability
of obtaining these data or data more
extreme.
Given the assumption that the null
hypothesis is true.
If you just remember that, then you won't
engage in that shady logic.
Now if that's not enough for you, then you
might want to just avoid NHST altogether.
There are alternatives.
One option is just to report confidence
intervals only.
And I'll show you how to do that in
lecture ten.
Or, engage in another form of hypothesis
ten, testing called Byesian Inference, and
that's
really beyond the scope of this course,
but it's, it's an approach that's very
powerful.
And becoming more popular in Statistics,
even in introductory level Statistics.
Which is why as I wrap up this segment you
look at my 6 problems you'll see
they make up the acronym BAYES and that's
the end of this segment.